[{"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "What do you do when priorities change quickly? Give one example of when this happened.", "answers": ["Adapting to change is an essential part of any job, and interviewers want to hear that you'll  happily adapt to change when necessary. Begin by telling the interviewer that you're an adaptable person, and you simply change directions when priorities change while maintaining a positive attitude. Next, think about a time when something really urgent came up. This is your example! There are all sorts of last minute urgent situations that might have occurred. Simply share yours with the interviewer. Try to connect this to an accounting clerk history so they know you can do this in the job and not just in life.\n\nIf you have no accounting experience, use an example from personal experience.", "\"During my regular duties, my manager rushed in one day looking frazzled. I asked if she was ok and she said that her boss had arrived two days early and none of the reports were ready. She asked me to drop everything and handed me a list of reports we needed. I sent urgent emails and  started pulling query reports myself to gather as many of the reports as quickly as possible. We were able to get all the documentation to review with her boss pretty quickly and he was satisfied.\"", "\"In college, I worked at a hotel as a bartender. I was really motivated to learn new job functions so I'd also been trained on front desk and night auditor roles. On New Year's Eve, I was told to keep the bar open until two in the morning. I did and got extra tips from very happy guests. Our night auditor decided to do a no call no show, and the front desk associate had never been trained on night audit, so at one a.m.  I was working both the bar and the front desk. After I closed the bar, I ran the audit reports and easily handled the night shift.  I'd been scheduled for the 7 a.m. to 3 p.m. shift the next morning, so I continued my shift after trying to reach both the assistant manager and general manager. Neither responded. I was exhausted and still in my bartender uniform at 3 p.m. New Year's Day when the 3 p.m. girl called and quit. I was honestly about to cry. I was exhausted, no one was answering their phones, and I couldn't leave the hotel with only a limited housekeeping staff there. No one apart from myself was trained on the front desk. The assistant manager never showed up for his shift that day and the general manager was out of state on vacation. At 7 p.m. I finally got the GM on the phone and explained the situation. She called that night's auditor and he came in several hours early to relieve me. I worked from 2 p.m. New Year's Eve until 8 p.m. New Year's Day without a break to ensure that the hotel ran smoothly. Shortly after that, I was promoted to the assistant manager of the hotel. I believe it was my ability to handle changes and challenges that got me the promotion.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Give me an example of a time you handled documentation preparation for an audit. How did you ensure you had everything required?", "answers": ["Accounting clerks have to wear many hats. Not only do they have to reconcile financial data, but they have to prepare it for the auditors. If you have experience with this, it will be an easy question. Most companies have a system or a list of things required for auditors that clerks have to prepare. \n\nIf you don't have experience, then be honest. It will show your integrity and you can use another story that shows that you're highly organized.", "\"At my previous company, we had an Excel spreadsheet with a master list of what the auditors would ask for and how to review the documents to ensure they were complete. I just followed the list and reviewed what was needed. I found one document that hadn't been properly updated and was able to send it back to the accountant on duty to revise it before handing over the audit package.\"", "\"I've never had real world experience with this, but I'll say that in school I was part of the student government and had to organize everything as the secretary. I ensured everyone had the documentation they needed and kept track of all budgets and accounts to help the treasurer because they weren't as organized as me.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "You may have multiple deadlines to complete your tasks.  When have you been in such an environment and how did you handle it?", "answers": ["Deadline-driven environments are a breeze for you as an accounting clerk!  Planning and organization are key for any environment, and the interviewer simply wants to hear that you're  not daunted by it.  Begin by sharing an example of a deadline-driven environment you've participated in. It can even be a school setting if you're a recent graduate.  Share where you were employed (or were a student), what types of deadlines you had to meet, and how you approached the tasks.  Mention what organizational tools you utilized, and be sure to mention how successful you were in handling the multi-tasking deadline environment.", "\"I've worked on several projects at once with different deadlines. I'm well versed with this as all it takes is good time management skills to handle the completion of different tasks.\"", "\"I have experience in handling various projects at the same time. In college, I was in my week of final exams and projects due, and was working with Habitat for Humanity building homes for the less fortunate. I was a veteran volunteer, so they relied on me for many hours and to help train newcomers. I was able to schedule myself enough time to study and complete my projects while helping the charity I hold so close to my heart.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "How proficient are you with Excel? Please share some projects you created and regular accounting tasks you completed on Excel.", "answers": ["Be candid with the interviewer when sharing your level of experience with Excel.  Your honest response will help the interviewer prepare a better training plan for you if you're hired for the job.  Tell the interviewer if you're a beginner, intermediate, or advanced user of the system.  Then share a few projects you created using Excel as well as accounting tasks that you regularly complete in the system.\n\nDon't assume that you don't need Excel knowledge to handle an accounting role. Yes, there are many types of software available but none can currently replace Excel. It's the most widely used and most companies prefer it.", "\"I'm an intermediate user. I can use formulas to do vlookups and concatenations. I'm well versed with most Excel functions but I can't do power queries yet. I'm open to training opportunities to further my knowledge on this.\"", "\"I'm a basic user. I can do searches and filtering but haven't used it much in my career at this point. In college, I learned how to do use formulas like vlookups and hlookups, and feel comfortable doing those as well as pulling data from one tab and inserting it on another.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Give me an example of time you caught an accounts receivable error and how you fixed it.", "answers": ["This is a straightforward question. If you've worked in accounts receivable before, you've likely found an error, whether it was yours or someone else's, and you followed a process to correct it. Explain that process here. \n\nIf you don't have experience with this, be honest. Entry level candidates are just that, entry level. Provide a story when you found an error at work or school and how you corrected it. This isn't to boast, but to demonstrate your attention to detail, which is important.", "\"I found that a client had been paying ten dollars over their monthly bill at the internet company I worked for. There was no reason for that because they didn't have a balance to pay off beyond their monthly fee. After reviewing the account, I found they'd been paying too much for over a year. I spoke with my manager and we both called the client to let them know that due to the overcharge on their auto-pay, they'd receive free service for the next five months. We adjusted the auto-pay for the correct amount to be withdrawn on the sixth month. The customer was so excited that they weren't even upset about the overpayments.\"", "\"I've never found an error working in accounts receivable, but when I was in college, I started handling the inventory for the restaurant where I worked and found we were being shorted a case of fries every order. I followed up with my manager, who contact the supplier and we were credited the money for the missing case. Apparently, it had been happening for a while and the delivery driver was retrained in how to verify deliveries.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "As an accounting clerk, you'll act as the receptionist for the accounting department. What reception experience do you have?", "answers": ["Some smaller companies use accounting clerks as receptionists as well. This is a question you'll  have to be prepared to answer. Accounting clerks must cover a wide variety of functions beyond  financials, so having some reception and human resources knowledge is helpful.\n\nBeing too proud to answer the phones or do no accounting tasks could cost you a job that could turn out to be an amazing opportunity. There are personal assistants that make six figures that started as accounting clerks. They took on various tasks and worked their way up to the highest tiers of the corporate ladder in this role.", "\"I have some reception experience with answering phones and directing calls. I handled the phones at a small marketing company for a year in college and it was fun. I didn't have to do much apart from direct phone calls and foot traffic when it came in.\"", "\"I've never worked as receptionist, but I'm good at customer service and am a people person so I can definitely handle calls. I keep a very tidy filing system at my house and could definitely handle whatever tasks come along with that part of this job.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "What's your career plan and how does the accounting clerk role fit into it?", "answers": ["This is a career oriented question. Where do you see yourself in five, ten, or twenty years? What are your long-term goals? All of this is basically the same but they want to know why this role fits into your long-term plans. Do you plan to stay with the company or are you a job hopper? While they may not ask this question outright, it's implied.\n\nAnswer honestly. If this doesn't fit into your long-term goals, then maybe you shouldn't be applying for this role.", "\"This is a step toward my goal of helping a company grow. I'd love to start as a clerk here and work my way up to a management role or high level executive position within your company. Ideally when your CFO is ready to retire in about ten years, I will have worked my way up to be his right hand person and will be in line to take over his position.\"", "\"Being new to accounting, the clerk role will give me the experience I need to qualify for my CPA exam. I'll be able to work with your CPA manager and learn from them while getting on-the-job training so I can sit for the CPA exam, which will help me get promoted later on.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "What is your personal method for double checking your work?", "answers": ["In other words, what steps do you take to ensure the accuracy of your work?  The interviewer simply wants to hear that you have a plan in place to catch any possible errors.  Accounting is a detail-oriented field, and the interviewer wants to know you can be trusted with these details.  Share what steps you take to ensure accuracy. \n\n You might discuss that you utilize a buddy system to check each other's work.  You might mention that you simply re-work each task to ensure your numbers match.  Or you might mention that you double check your totals by dropping the data into an Excel spreadsheet.  Simply share what works for you.  Having a plan is key.", "\"I tend to double check my work by completing a task, then putting it on hold for at least thirty minutes, then reviewing the data once more before submitting it. I find that if I missed anything, it will jump out at me when I review it.\"", "\"I'll complete a task, take five minutes to review the process, then review what I completed before submitting it. That way I know if I missed anything.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "If I were to look at your home office, or previous work station before you left, what would it look like?", "answers": ["This isn't about a tidy work station. Yes, it's important to have a tidy work station, but it has been shown that people who work in messy environments are generally less productive. You spend more time searching for what you need, lose paperwork or files, and are generally are late for meetings, etc., more often than those who keep tidy work areas. \n\nYou should always keep you area clean, not only because it's attractive, but because in accounting, there's a lot of confidential information that should never be left in view for anyone to see.", "\"I always keep my work area clean. I have a filing system in place that allows me to quickly find what I need and ensure nothing goes missing.\"", "\"I can't function in a messy environment. It drives me crazy so I tend to be on the neat side. If I do have a lot of clutter, it only lasts for a short time until I organize it. I tend to be a little over-organized with my time and work areas.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Give me an example of an accounting goal you set for yourself and achieved.", "answers": ["This is a variation on the standard question of goal-setting but with an accounting focus. They want to see that you can overcome obstacles and set your goals high. If you think that you haven't set or achieved goals in this area, then look to your education. You set the goal to become educated and take on this career, so you achieved whatever level of education you have.\n\nIf you're self-taught, that's also a goal. Discuss a project you took on or how you became interested in the field.", "\"When I was in college, I worked as a receptionist at a dental clinic four days a week. Their accounting clerk walked out on them in the middle of month end. They asked for help because at the time, I was an economics major and somehow they thought that tied together. I dug in and learned a lot about accounting on the internet. When I got stuck, I went to YouTube and found these walk-through videos that taught me so much. Shortly afterward, I changed my major to accounting because I fell in love with the process.\"", "\"The biggest accounting goal I set for myself was obtaining my Bachelor's degree in Accounting. I started school with no idea what I wanted to do, but after a lot of research and development, I was able to narrow the field to accounting. I set the goal of achieving my Bachelor's degree early to start my career. I was able to double my class load a couple semesters in a row and graduate a year early.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "What accounting tasks did you perform at your former job?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to gain an understanding of your average workload in your most recent position.  A great way to approach this question is to walk through a typical day or week at your most recent job.  Discuss what accounting tasks had to be completed daily by providing a high-level overview.  After doing so, be sure to mention your level of comfort with this workload.  Did it feel comfortable for you?  Were you bored in your past position?  Or did you feel overworked?\n\nIf you have no work experience in accounting, be honest. This isn't the time to exaggerate your knowledge.", "\"In my previous role, I handled all accounts receivable and payable. I balanced the books and ensured that all filing was up to date. I answered phones for the accounting department and routed inquiries where they needed to go.\"", "\"I have no experience in the accounting world at this time. I'm eager to get my foot in the door and would love the opportunity to learn all the aspects of the accounting clerk role.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "When you make a mistake, who usually notices? You or the auditor?", "answers": ["Hopefully, you catch most of your mistakes.  Interviewers understand that we're all human, and it's likely that an auditor will catch one of your mistakes at some point in your career too.  Think through your career.  What's been the average?  Do you routinely catch errors in your work?  Odds are, you do!  Go ahead and share how often you catch your own errors to ensure the  auditor doesn't need to find them for you. \n\nIf you make a lot of errors, this may be a good way for you to explain how you correct the mistakes before they leave your desk.", "\"When I was very new to this career,I thought I'd entered all the journal entries correctly so I got cocky and didn't double check my work before passing it to my boss to submit for the general ledger. She caught a mistake and asked why I didn't check my work. I was so embarrassed that I never made that mistake again.\"", "\"In college, I was late to class one day because I got caught up at work and came in the middle of class. My teacher was talking about the book we were supposed to be reading and they were explaining that we'd be switching books because most of the class had already read it. I was so caught up in my own thoughts that I didn't pay attention and went home and read the same book again instead of picking up the new book at the front of the classroom. I wrote a paper on the wrong book and got an F. I learned to always pay attention. Instead of rushing out of class thinking I knew what was going on, I'd ask the teacher what I missed due to work.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "What do you hope to achieve in the accounting clerk role?", "answers": ["This is an important question that asks if you see yourself growing with the company. They want to know if you'll be looking for advancement or if you're happy to be in the same role year after year. This could be a double-edged sword question as well. If it's a small company, then they may be concerned that if you're too eager, you won't be satisfied without pay raises later on. If you don't seem eager, they may fear you won't help them grow.\n\nBe honest with where you are in your career. If you don't want advancement, let them know so they can place you in the right position.", "\"I'm hoping to grow into a more managerial position in the future and to help this company grow so that it will need multiple new roles that present growth opportunities not only for me but others as well.\"", "\"I'm always open to new possibilities and responsibilities, so if the company is growing, I'd like to grow with it.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Do you enjoy working with deadlines?", "answers": ["This is a straightforward question. Most accounting positions have strict deadlines for the majority of their work. If you can't work with a deadline or are consistently late, that adversely affect your career if it hasn't already. Be honest if you struggle with deadlines and explain that it's something you're improving on daily to ensure you meet your company's timelines.\n\nTalk about your time management system so they know you have something in place to help you meet all deadlines.", "\"I'm great at meeting deadlines. I have a planner that I live by and as soon as I get a task, I break it down into manageable pieces and tackle them one at a time. I ensure that I always turn in my projects early if not on time.\"", "\"I'm great with deadlines. I've never turned in a task late at school and with any job I've had so far.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "What made you decide on a career in bookkeeping?", "answers": ["This is a personal question that you should be able to answer. If you don't know why you want to be a bookkeeper, then you probably don't want to be one. Being a bookkeeper is detail and math-oriented. You have to be organized and able to handle multiple types of accounting functions as well as filing policies the company has in place.\n\nIf you don't have an answer for this, then I suggest researching exactly what the accounting clerk role has to offer and see if you'd enjoy it. If you don't enjoy the job, you'll be more likely to miss a detail important to the role.", "\"I love detail-oriented work and thrive on finding the last detail or piece of the puzzle.\"", "\"While I have no experience in bookkeeping, I've always loved detail-oriented work. I always put a lot of detail in my projects and love to do puzzles. Finding the details and ensuring their accuracy is important to me.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "In your previous accounting experience, what's the toughest group you had to get cooperation from? How did you handle it?", "answers": ["Getting buy-in can be a challenge from time to time for various reasons.  Possible issues might include: major company changes, new company vision, launching new company processes, or even cultural differences.  What has been your toughest sell to get the cooperation of others?  Often, it's the situation that's challenging and not the group itself.  Begin by telling the interviewer your situation.  What were you trying to get cooperation for?  Who were you trying to get cooperation from?  Next, share the group's reaction.  What kind of pushback did you get?  Then, share how you successfully overcame the pushback to achieve cooperation from the group.\n\nSometimes departments do not mesh well together so when you are reliant on another department to get you data it can sometimes be a challenge.", "\"When I worked for my previous company there was a lot of tension between the IT department and the Accounting department. Both departments thought they where the most important in the company and both were equally valuable because you could not run the company without either one. I was able to build a relationship with the IT department and soon became the liason between the departments. I made friends with two of the IT guys and we would regularly go out to lunch to maintain our working relationship and friendship. I still see those guys once a week at our poker game because maintaining that relationship has been very important to us.\"", "\"While this is accounting, when I worked in student government, we had a huge lack of participation from certain groups of kids. I made it my mission to involve everyone in some way. I reached out to the groups individually and got a lot of positive responses. We had the highest rate of participation of any class that school has seen because I went out of my way to involve everyone. We even had a punk rock themed dance at one point to convince the punk kids they could contribute too.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "When given a new bookkeeping assignment, how do you approach it?", "answers": ["In other words, what steps do you take to figure out how to do something new?  If you're  provided training, do you take notes?  If you're not provided training, do you watch a video, read blogs, or conduct an internet search to determine your course of action?  Do you seek other people in your department who can help you learn?  Or do you crack open an old textbook to help you figure it out?  The interviewer simply wants to hear that you're willing to take on a challenge and will determine a way to get the job done.  Go ahead and share your approach.\n\nIf you've never had a bookkeeping assignment, describe another challenge you had to figure out and discuss that.", "\"The first thing I do is get the scope of the project, exactly what my manager is looking for, and then I conduct internet research and ask some of my colleagues how to best present my data.\"", "\"Whenever I'm given a new project that I'm not trained for, I immediately start researching how others have completed similar tasks. I'd ask my supervisor for the specifics they want and start with outlining the process before detailing everything.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Give an example of a time you were helping on a project but maintained your normal duties as well.", "answers": ["This is important. As an accounting clerk, you'll be assisting  accounting managers with projects and they'll expect you to handle all your regular duties like AR/AP and filing. You must demonstrate that you can maintain your work while taking on additional tasks they need assistance with.\n\nIf you don't have this experience, then  you should be honest about it. Anyone in the accounting should be excited about the prospect of new projects to show they have initiative.", "\"I've helped with several projects and maintained my duties. It's all about time management and blocking time for the project while giving yourself time to complete your regular duties. If you start to feel overwhelmed, check the schedule you made, which gets you back on track.\"", "\"I'm just out of school, so I'd block time for the project and work my regular duties around whatever meetings or tasks they needed me to do. If I need to work a little late to get it done, then that's no problem. I love taking on new and fun tasks.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Are you proficient using the 10 key pad?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to learn more about your skill level.  Go ahead and candidly share your level of expertise using 10 key pad.  Discuss where you've utilized 10 key pad as well as how many years of experience you have.  \n\nIf you haven't taken a 10 key test, they offer them free online. Google 10 key test and you can find out your typing speed. It's important to know your speed and practice to improve it.", "\"Yes, I can use my 10 key speed. My speed without errors is 102 keys per minute.\"", "\"I've never taken a certifiable test but when I took one online for free, I managed 85 keys per minute without error.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Give me an example of an ethical dilemma you experienced regarding your work and how you handled it.", "answers": ["This is important because you'll have ethical dilemmas not just at work but in life. Having strong ethics is important in the accounting industry. Being able to differentiate right from wrong is very important. \n\nTaking the ethical high ground is important in accounting. Unethical people only cause the company problems in the future. If you don't get hired because you're unwilling to bend your ethics, then you don't want to work there. It will ruin your career.", "\"There was a month end when I found an error my manager had made. He asked me to adjust the balances to hide it. I told him I didn't feel comfortable with that and after some convincing, he let me adjust the balances to show the error, which we explained. No one got in trouble due to the low amount.\"", "\"In college, I found out that this guy behind me was cheating by copying from my exams. I knew this was unethical so instead of turning him in and getting him kicked out of school, I offered to tutor him. We spent two nights a week studying together and he agreed to move seats to the front of the class where he couldn't see anyone else's paper. He ended up passing the class with a B and avoided unethical situations moving forward.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Outside of inputting sales and expenses, what other accounting tasks have you completed before?", "answers": ["This one should be easy!  The interviewer wants to get a better understanding of your background.  Break down your tasks by each past employer.  State the name of the company, your job title, and the typical tasks you completed in each role.  This will allow the interviewer to understand what tasks you're already skilled with and will help the interviewer implement a stronger training plan customized for you if you're selected for the position.\n\nBear in mind any non-disclosure agreements you've signed. It's not uncommon to sign an NDA in the accounting field. You're dealing with sensitive information, and if you leak that information, it could cost the company investors, which is why most companies require you to sign something. If you've signed an NDA, be vague about the company while going into detail about the work you completed.", "\"At one of the companies I previously worked for, I handled all AR and AP to include updating journal entries and ensuring the accuracy of the general ledger.\"", "\"While I've never worked in real world accounting, as a new graduate I took several courses on AR and AP. I also aced my auditing course as well as the bookkeeping courses. I can use several different accounting software programs like Quickbooks or XERO. I'm eager to learn and grow within this field.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Give me an example of time you had  to fix the journal entries, how you found the error, and how you fixed it.", "answers": ["This is a simple question. If you've ever discovered an error in the journal entries and had to correct it, then you can easily answer this. If you've never found an error, then explain it and describe the process of how your team inputs the data to ensure there are no errors. \n\nIf you have no experience entering journal entries or reviewing them, be honest. This is a low level position and is great for learning the field. Being honest is the best policy here.", "\"I was the reviewer for the journal entries for my previous company and it was common to find an error. Basically, when I found the error, I sent it back to the person who input it and used it as a training moment to show them why it was out of balance.\"", "\"I've never found an error in journal entries as our company has a policy of checking our work before submitting the entries. When we input the data, we verify with another team member  that it's correct. That way, we learn from each other.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "Give an example of a time you had too many extra duties and had to delegate or reject taking on extra duties.", "answers": ["This is important as there will be times when you're overloaded with work and will need a break or someone to help you. The interviewer is trying to determine if you know when to admit you need help and that someone needs to help you.\n\nIf you like to please people, this becomes difficult because you don't want to stop taking on more or helping out, but then you can't say no when it's necessary.", "\"I was doing month-end duties and my boss kept signing me up for training events and extra projects. Finally, I had to sit down with them and let them know that I couldn't take on any more tasks as I was getting in at 6am daily and leaving at 7pm. I wasn't getting any time with  my wife and kids so I had to take a step back from some of the tasks.\"", "\"When I was in high school, I was on three different sport teams, coached my little sister's soccer team, had a part time job at a fast food place, and was concurrently enrolled at a nearby college. When it was time for finals, I had to make some choices. I took three weeks off of work to study for all my finals and missed about a week's worth of practices. My mom covered for me on the coaching standpoint so that I could get all the study time I needed for both high school and college.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "If a customer came to you and asked you to alter their account without payment, how would you handle that situation?", "answers": ["This is an ethics questions as well as a how well you handle guilt. Imagine someone coming to you with a sob story about their finances. They can't afford to pay their bills, they're  overextended. They can't pay for the plasma TV they purchased from your company because they need to feed their six kids. How are you going to handle this both in a respectful but firm manner?\n\nWill you fall for their story and adjust their account to help them steal from the company? Or will you offer other assistance?", "\"I'd talk to them about a payment plan. If they couldn't afford any type of payment, I'd put their account in delinquent statues. I'd discuss the late fees associated with that and if necessary, the return of our product to get them out of the payments all together.\"", "\"I'd let them know I couldn't alter their account without payment. I'd discuss payment plan options or the consequences of making late payments. If the company offers  a grace period, I'd inform them of that.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounting+Clerk", "question": "If a vendor called and tried to demand payment two weeks early, how would you handle it?", "answers": ["This is a rare occurrence, but can happen. If a vendor seriously needs cash or there's an error   regarding the invoice due date, then it will result in an awkward phone call. The important thing to remember is to always check your files. They should have due dates and agreed-upon amounts. \n\nThe correct way to handle this is to take the message, go to your manager to discuss the situation, and then follow whatever your manager says. If they're unavailable, go to your files and let them know the due dates you've recorded and the amount due. Don't authorize payment without permission from a manager.", "\"I'd place them on hold and see if my manager is available to discuss the issue. If they're not, I'd pull the file and review the due date and the amount on file. If they have a special reason for their situation, I'd inform them that I'd contact them after discussing the situation with the manager.\"", "\"I'd let them know our policy on file regarding the due date, and then escalate this to my manager as I'm not allowed to pay something that's not scheduled.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Describe your most ideal work setting.", "answers": ["Before you answer this question, it is important to be aware of what your ideal work setting really is. The answer to this question is almost limitless - you can discuss your preferred company size, the type of company culture you are looking for, and you can add aspects of what you want personally like a work-life balance - you might not want to take your work home with you.  \n\r\nSome examples  of appropriate responses include: \"I want to work in a setting that allows you to learn and grow\" \r\nor\r\n\"My ideal work setting is to be part of a team and collaborating with others\" \r\nor\r\n\"It is important for me to work in an environment that is positive and supportive. For me, positivity is key to a healthy workplace\"", "\"I want to work in a setting that allows you to learn and grow\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "We use the accrual method for our invoicing. Are you familiar with this process?", "answers": ["You want to confirm you familiarity with accrual invoicing by explaining what it is and how you have used it in past jobs. Define the accrual process: \"When using the accrual method of accounting the expense is reported in the accounting period in which the service occurred, not the period in which it is paid...\" \r\nMore importantly, get specific when describing your job responsibilities and experiences that involve using the accrual method. This is the best way to show the interviewer that you are comfortable and confident with using this method and that you can use these skills to benefit the company if you're hired.", "\"When using the accrual method of accounting the expense is reported in the accounting period in which the service occurred, not the period in which it is paid...\"", "\"We book invoices for goods or services that are already received. We check proforma invoices before receiving goods or services and ensure sales prices and down payments are precise.\"", "Good start.  Check your answer to ensure that it is demonstrating an understanding of the accrual method.  More detail is helpful!"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What is your experience with using Microsoft Excel?", "answers": ["Be specific! Answering this question should be straightforward for you. Use your past experience and job duties to compile a list of functions you can perform in Excel. You can include experience data entry, formulas, graphs, charts, formatting, pivot tables, Vlookups, etc. in your list of \n\r\nYou can also state how long you've been using the program for and show the progression of your Excel skills and usage. How often you used Excel in previous jobs is important. For example, if you used it every day, share this with the interviewer.\n\r\nYou can say, \"I started off using Excel for data entry purposes. I created spreadsheets and charts used formatting tools and formulas. I also created monthly, quarterly, yearly and year-over-year comparison reports on Excel - the reports included charts, bar graphs, pie graphs and totals which I calculated with the formula function.\"", "\"I started off using Excel for data entry purposes. I created spreadsheets and charts used formatting tools and formulas. I also created monthly, quarterly, yearly and year-over-year comparison reports on Excel - the reports included charts, bar graphs, pie graphs and totals which I calculated with the formula function.\"", "\"I usually use Excel when exporting data from the SAP system. My main task is to create and maintain a balance sheet confirmation by using simple formulas.   Excel allows us to save a lot of time and to be certain that all the invoices have been processed. I am willing to improve my Excel skills and take trainings. I have taken trainings in the past and will be doing the same if I join your company.\"", "Good start, but give a bit more detail.  Would you characterize yourself as a super-user?  Do you know how to use formulas?  How often do you use Excel?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "How will you measure the success of your work?", "answers": ["This question is designed to see how you hold yourself accountable for your job responsibilities and it gives the interviewer an idea of your work ethic. \r\nYou can answer this question by describing goals you set in the workplace. These can be daily/weekly/monthly/yearly goals pertaining to completing specific tasks and projects. The goals should be measurable - you can use your goals from a previous job as an example - your goal was to process a \"X\" number of invoices, update the general ledger, and reconcile a \"Y\" number of accounts in one day - you consider the day successful because you completed all of these tasks error-free.", "\"I set up personal goals that correspond with the company's KPIs. Under the current circumstances, my daily goals are to process 50 invoices daily, generate CRM cases on time, and respond queries within given SLAs. I consider my day to be successful when I complete these tasks error-free.\"", "Good start.  This question is an opportunity to also highlight past successes.  You have the beginnings here by talking about your daily goals.  Have you reached your goal?  How often?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Walk me through a typical day at your last job.", "answers": ["Interviewers ask this question to get an idea of what exact tasks you are most familiar with. It is also a way for them to know what kind of workload you are accustomed to. Start from the beginning of your day and create a roadmap to the end of your day. Discuss your main responsibilities and the tasks you performed every day, such as sorting and matching invoices. It is important to be specific! For example, provide quantitative results, tell the interviewers how many accounts payable transactions you reconciled, how many invoices you processed on a daily basis, and how many hours a day you allotted to certain tasks. If you prioritize certain invoices ahead of others, discuss how this process works. If your every day duties include data entry, tell the interviewer exactly what type of data you were recording, how much data you recorded (this can be your average daily number of general ledger entries) and what software you used to record it. These details will give the interviewer a clear picture of your productivity in a typical day and showcase how capable you are at your job.", "\"After I check emails I start my daily tasks by auditing my team's invoice entry from the previous day.  I follow up with calls, respond to queries, and resolve any outstanding cases in the CRM tool. When I finish these tasks I check the status of daily invoices and begin processing those that are due.\"", "Good start.  Can you talk about how you execute the lists and plans that you discussed in prior answers?  This would help the interviewer see the end result of all your careful organization and planning."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "How do you manage your time on a typical day?", "answers": ["How you manage your time is a good way for an interviewer to measure how efficient you are at getting your job done. You can go through a typical day in your current or most recent job as a real life example of how you manage your time. If you plan your days out beforehand explain this process - \"I like to plan my week out on Monday\" or \"I make a list of tasks to be completed the next day every night before I leave the office.\" Include the tools you use to help organize and manage your time, such as a calendar or a written log of your daily schedule - this shows the interviewer that these are actual tools you use to manage your time. You should also mention how you prioritize tasks and projects, and how you allot time to work on them. If applicable, tell the interviewer how you deal with receiving a new task - this shows your ability to adapt when unexpected things arise.", "\"I like to plan my days in advance. I create a to-do list and put an estimated duration on each task.\"", "Good.  A list is a great way to stay organized.  Does it work well?  Do you have other methods to ensure you've followed-through on unexpected tasks?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "How do you manage stress in your daily work?", "answers": ["You can spin this question and tell the interviewer how you seem to work better under pressure or that you tend to be reactive to stressful situations instead of dwelling on them. This is a good way of showing the interviewer that you work well under pressure. Give a specific example of a stressful day in your past job and how you handled it. It is important to highlight your ability to complete your tasks in spite of the stress.\n\r\nYou can also include how you use extracurricular activities to help manage work stress - this could include going to the gym before or after work, cooking, playing sports, doing yoga, etc.", "\"I like to be organized and plan my work during the day. I usually create a to-do list for the next day, and this helps me stay focused during a chaotic day.\"", "Good start.  It would enrich your answer if you walked the interviewer through an example so he or she can envision your process."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What was a major accomplishment you had at your previous employer?", "answers": ["When answering this question think about specific accomplishments and ways you improved the accounting/accounts payable department, whether you increased productivity, reduced error or successfully implemented a new system. It is important to provide specifics if you have them available, for example, \"I redesigned the accounts payable system, which led to and 50% increase in the efficiency of our system\" or \"I processed over 3000 check requests in less than three weeks which totaled $90,000 in accounts payable.\"", "\"I redesigned the accounts payable system, which led to and 50% increase in the efficiency of our system\"", "\"I managed my market's country specifics to be compatible with the general accounting procedure. My previous colleagues did not follow these general procedures which caused many conflicts with vendors. After changing procedures, the daily workload was decreased and we reached a healthy state. Feedback from my executives was positive. I am willing to bring the same standards to your company as well.\"", "Great!  This is a good example but give more detail.  What was your role?  How did you accomplish it? What were the procedures you changed?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Describe a time when you delivered more than was expected.", "answers": ["You should answer this question that shows your flexibility and willingness to go the extra mile to make sure things get done. You want to prove to the interviewer that you are hardworking.", "\"In my previous job, my coworker and I were both responsible for preparing and mailing out invoices to our customers. One day my coworker had a family emergency. I offered to stay late to complete her remaining invoices so she wouldn't have to worry about them being processed on time.\"", "\"Two months ago, we had to present country specifics for each market separately. One of my colleagues from another market was terribly sick and she wasn't in a position to present. I offered my help to present for that market.  I prepared and made the presentation. \r\n The presentation went really well, and I got good feedback from my supervisor.\"", "Good!  You're following the STAR format and it's helpful.  Add more detail and \"paint the picture\" for your interviewer so he or she can envision your contribution clearly."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Tell me about a time when you had to deal with an irate customer?", "answers": ["It is a good idea to think about this type of question before your interview. It requires you to think back to a previous situation when you had an unhappy customer. You want to give the interviewer a full story when explaining the situation - this means explaining why the customer was irate, how you dealt with them and how you resolved the issue. The interviewer wants to know that you have the skills to be able to handle any situation in a professional manner."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "When have you had difficulty with a coworker? How was the situation resolved?", "answers": ["Walk the interviewer through the situation: Explain why you had difficulty with this coworker, your plan of action to resolve the issue, and the outcome. This situation could a personal matter or be regarding a specific project/task. It is important not to make your description of the situation overly negative - keep it neutral because the interviewer is looking at how you function in the workplace and how you could potentially fit into their company. You want to show that you are a team player and that you can work through difficult situations.", "\"One of my previous teammates was not taking responsibility for the work. I was new to the team, and I needed his guidance on my tasks. Without escalating the problem I wanted to share my thoughts with him in an informal meeting. I kindly asked for his help and explained why his help was valuable. This approached turned out well and after this discussion, we started to work together more efficiently.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Tell me about a time when you had to assist a coworker.", "answers": ["The best way to answer this question is by telling the interviewer a story. You should start with explaining the overall situation: tell them about the project/task, what your coworker's responsibilities were, what they were having trouble with/needed assistance with, how you helped them (specifically) and the result/outcome of your collaborative work. It is important to show the interviewer that your assistance contributed to the success and/or completion of the task/project.", "\"Some of our team members are not familiar with some of the markets or balance sheet confirmations.  From time to time when they receive such requests, I will help them understand them.  With my help, they are able to respond to queries on time and get positive feedback from their clients.\"", "This is a good example.  To help expand, you may want to make your answer in the STAR format.  Talk about a situation when one of your team was unfamiliar with a market.  What was your task in this situation?  What did you help him or her with? What action did you take and what was the end result?  This kind of detail helps the interviewer envision your teamwork clearly."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Why did you choose a career as an Accounts Payable Clerk?", "answers": ["The interviewer asks this question to gain insight into why you are passionate about being an AP Clerk. One way you could answer this question is by providing a story about past experiences that led you to choose to be an AP Clerk. You can walk them through your path to becoming an AP Clerk or choose one instance that helped you realize this is the path you wanted to take. \n\r\nYou can also express how your career choice has given you a sense of fulfillment and why you are passionate about what you do. Show that your career gives you a sense of pride and you love what you do. \n\r\nSpeak about how the job gives you the opportunity to use your critical thinking skills because it can come with challenges - it keeps your mind sharp. This is a way of showing the interviewer that you chose this career path because it allows you to constantly continue to learn and grow."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What are you best at as an Accounts Payable Clerk?", "answers": ["This question is pretty straight forward. Think about the tasks you were responsible for as an AP Clerk and choose which one you are best at. This can be a task you are most comfortable with.  You should explain why you are so good at this particular task and provide the interviewer with positive results or recognition you were given because of your good work.\n\r\nFor example, if you're best at processing and collecting invoices, explain your process and why it is so effective. You can also mention your successes with this task."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What techniques do you personally use to avoid mistakes?", "answers": ["The best way to attack this question is to think about daily techniques you used in previous jobs. You can also use examples from your past work experience. Mistakes are inevitable but you want to show the interviewer that you know how to do your best to prevent them. \n\r\nSome examples:\r\n- \"I usually have a plan for my project which helps keep me on track.\"\r\n- I create and use templates. The standardized templates allow less room for error. I believe they are created through trial and error so why not use templates to get the best results.\" \r\n- \"I don't like to rush so I give myself enough time to complete my work. This also allows me to look over my work before sending it to my boss.\"\r\nuse checklists.\"\r\n- \"I'm not afraid to ask questions when needed. Instead of assuming I'm doing something the correct way, I ask - this way I avoid making mistakes and having to redo my work.\"", "\"I usually have a plan for my project which helps keep me on track.\"", "\"Double-checking my work, planning, and organizing my efforts are key to avoid mistakes.\"", "Good.  Can you give a typical example taken from your current position that would apply to the one you are seeking?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Why is an Accounts Payable Clerk a vital position to any organization?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to see if you know the importance of an account receivable position to a business. Pick out specific responsibilities you have as an AP Clerks and explain to the interviewer why they are crucial for any organization to function properly.", "\"Accounts payable clerks serve a vital role in the success of any company. We are responsible for dealing with the company's outgoing money - we keep track of the money that is being paid out for bills, invoices, utility payments, employee expense accounts, etc...\"", "\"Because  AP specialists are obligated to check all details and invoices for correctness, I am aware that even a small mistake can cause serious cost issues.\"", "Great!  You're reflecting your understanding of how your position fits into the overall organization's mission.  Nice!"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What is your greatest weakness?", "answers": ["This is a tough question. A good way to interpret it is to find an area of your job that you are still improving on. You want the interviewer to know that you're aware of your weakness and are working on improving/correcting it. This is a time when you can show that you are constantly taking steps to improve on your skills. Ideally, you should mention a small weakness like being too critical of yourself or letting yourself get bogged down by small details. Once you mention this weakness, you should follow up with ways you are improving on it. At the end of the day, you want to choose a weakness that isn't detrimental to your interview - it shouldn't harm your chances of getting the job.", "\"I can sometimes be critical of my own work and get bogged down with small details. Even though my perfectionism ensures I complete the best work, sometimes I can get carried away. I have worked on finding ways to do provide the same quality of work without spending as much time being a perfectionist. I have been making a conscious effort to not be as critical of my own work and to trust my skills.\"", "\"I can sometimes drown in very small details. Since I'm a perfectionist and try to deliver the best quality work,  being detailed oriented can distract me. I try to find ways to provide quality work without spending so much time on the details.  I learned how to trust my skills in such situations.\"", "Good!  It's important to identify the weakness, show your awareness of it, and then your efforts to improve."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What could you tell me about our organization?", "answers": ["Organizations want to know that you've done research about what they do and their culture. Our suggestion is to do an online search of the organization and go on their company website. Go to the company's \"About Us\" and \"Careers\" pages. It is key to familiarize yourself with the organization's history, primary function, mission statement, and values. It is important to show that you have a well-rounded knowledge of what they do. In order to do this, you should watch any career, management or social media videos that the company has posted. Many times these videos provide insight into the company from its top leaders. While reviewing the information, write down or keep in mind key points that you want to bring up in the interview."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Tell me about your relationship with your previous managers.", "answers": ["The key to answering this question is to keep your response positive. It is important that you do not speak negatively of previous management as it will most likely be viewed as unprofessional. You need to show that you can work as part of a team and that you can effectively communicate with management. Discuss the management style of your previous manager(s) and how you responded to their leadership techniques. Be specific when talking about what aspects of their management style you found most effective and what you learned from him/her. For instance, \"I was lucky to have a manager who was clear about what my responsibilities were and of her expectations. She was also very supportive in my role and showed me appreciation when I did a great job.\"", "\"I was lucky to have a manager who was clear about what my responsibilities were and of her expectations. She was also very supportive in my role and showed me appreciation when I did a great job.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What type of boss gets the most productivity out of you?", "answers": ["This question takes into account what type of management style you work best under, what type of boss motivates and inspires you and the qualities your ideal boss possesses.\r\nFirstly, discuss your ideal management style, whether you are an independent worker and don't need much managing from your boss, or if you need your boss to be frequently available for questions. Feel free to use examples from past jobs when answering this question - you should mention the company you worked at and the name of your boss.", "\"My last boss gave me a task, direction, and a deadline, then let me complete it without constantly checking up on me. This allowed me to concentrate on my project and finish it before the deadline. She also acknowledged me for doing a great job!\"", "\"My supervisor should act as a leader more than a boss and open to questions. it is important that I know I can get support. Besides, my supervisor should be open and direct.\"", "Very good.  You're implying that you take feedback well, and that's important.  Can you expand on this point to illustrate your ability to work well with your managers?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Tell me about a situation you encountered where there was no rule or precedent in place for how you should tackle the situation.", "answers": ["Your answer should show that you are able to think on your feet and use your knowledge and resources to create positive results out of the situation. Walk the interviewer through a past situation where you used your problem-solving skills. Describe your thought process, if you did research or sought help from a coworker/manager other than your own, the steps you took to handle the situation and the outcome. You can say how this situation helped you gain confidence in your skills."]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Where do you hope your career will progress to in the next few years?", "answers": ["This is the time to discuss your career goals. Discuss your plan for your career with the interviewer. For example, if you want to gain experience to become an AP Manager, explain how you would prepare yourself to be eligible for this type of position. You want to show that the job you are applying for is playing a part in your overall career goal and that you are committed to a long career at this company. Express your enthusiasm for the job and how you see potential with growing with the company.", "\"I'd like to achieve AP excellence, and at best, my goal is to become an AP Manager.  I'd like a position in which I can take more responsibility and make decisions. To reach this goal, I am learning as much as I can, not only about my market but also about others since each market has its own specifics.\"", "Very good!  Most employers want to keep their talent long-term, so having career goals that the employer can satisfy is important.  Can you connect your career goals with the opportunity?  How can this employer satisfy your career goals?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "Why is this accounting position right for you?", "answers": ["You should talk about what aspects of the job you are qualified for - you want to highlight the parts of your skill set that are associated with this job. Explain why you are excited to join the accounting team at this particular company - talk about what you know about the company and why you want to work for them. For example, you can say you resonate with the company's mission statement or you feel that their culture is a good fit for you and what you're looking for.", "\"I have a detail-oriented personality which helps qualify me for this position since it requires focus and attention to detail.  In my current role, I am able to recognize that many mistakes were done by other groups,  and we prevented many escalations by solving those mistakes early.\"", "Good.  It's also a good idea to show your process.  How does your system of double-check work?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Payable+Clerk", "question": "What accounting systems and software are you familiar with using?", "answers": ["The purpose of this question is to see what specific programs you are accustom to using. You should be able to describe the tasks you can perform on each software platform, how often you've used them in previous jobs, how long you've used them and your proficiency level. Be prepared to answer any questions the interviewer might ask you about using any of the platforms you list.\n\r\nFor example, you can say \"I am proficient in using SAP. I used it in my previous position to process vendor invoices on a daily basis.\"", "\"I am proficient in using SAP. I used it in my previous position to process vendor invoices on a daily basis.\"", "\"I am a proficient  SAP user. I am using it in my current position to process vendor invoices on a daily basis.\"", "Great, can you expand by discussing some of the functionality?  How long have you used SAP?"]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Have you ever been in a situation where you had to bargain on an overdue invoice?", "answers": ["Negotiating is a common task for A/R Specialists, and the interviewer is trying to learn what amount of experience you have. Begin by telling the interviewer if you have negotiated payment terms or an invoice in general, with a customer. Discuss what types of deals you have settled as well as how often you have conducted negotiations. \n\nNext, mention what you liked about the negotiation process, and finish up by discussing one specific example of a negotiation which worked out well for you. If you do not have experience in negotiations, that is okay too. You could mention that you are open to training when it comes to collections, or discuss any sales training you may have.", "\"Back in 2011, when many companies were starting to pull out of the economic slowdown, I was given many faulty customer accounts on which to follow up. One by one, I called these customers who had defaulted, and asked for a payment of some type, to re-establish our business relationships. Most of the clients paid at least 50% upfront, with negotiated terms for the remainder of their balances. At first, the idea of performing collections and naming terms made me very nervous, but I am very proud of what I was able to accomplish. In the first week alone, I was able to recover over $359K for our company.\"", "\"My current employer gives our clients the opportunity to be flexible with payments more often that I would like to see. This flex is normally given to customers that have an established credit history, and have run into slow times. I have learned it's best to re-establish normal payment terms with the client as soon as possible so that extensions do not become the norm. Although I am newer to my career as an A/R specialist, I am quickly learning the ins and outs of payment defaults and the fast impact they have on a company.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "What is an Accounts Receivable Aging Report, and why do they matter?", "answers": ["An aging report is a critical tool used by collections personnel to determine which invoices are overdue for payment, and by how long. Most aging reports will also have the clients' contact information. As an A/R professional, your work performance may be graded based on these reports, so it's important to understand what these reports are and why they matter. Most aging statements address invoices in 30-day sections so that you can run a report based on 30 days, 31-60 days old, 61-90 days past, and so on. Briefly explain to the interviewer what you understand an A/R Aging Report to be, and why they matter to you as an accounts receivable specialist.", "\"An accounts receivable specialist will look at an aging report and be able to see a snapshot of clients who frequently fail to pay their invoices on time, or meet their extended credit obligations as per the contract agreement. This report allows A/R staff to fry the biggest fish first - the companies or people who owe the largest amounts of money. This report is especially important if collection agencies need to be engaged, or when customers are ignoring their outstanding debts.\"", "\"I took a few classes on Accounts Receivable Aging Reports while earning my Accounting certificate. This report is a major business management tool, showing an A/R specialist exactly which companies or people owe money, are past due, need less credit extended, or new payment terms. Most reports can be run from 30 days, 31-60 days, and 61-90 days so that it's easy to get a quick snapshot of who is behind on payments.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "What is your current A/R Specialist salary?", "answers": ["It is important to note that this question may be illegal, depending on your geographical location. If you are in a place where it is unlawful for a hiring authority or recruiter to ask this question, you can politely decline by saying, 'I am aware that this question breaches my rights as a candidate in the state of XYZ.'\n\nA potential employer will often want to base their offer on your current salary. Whenever possible, you should be transparent about your most recent earnings and be prepared to back up any salary requests in states or provinces where it is entirely legal to ask about compensation. Keep your answer simple, and to the point. It is indeed okay to ask the interviewer what they are offering in return!", "\"I am currently making $38,000 per year with two bonus opportunities based on collections on aged accounts. I am looking for compensation that is aligned with the role and provides an opportunity for growth. Could you share further details with me on your compensation plan?\"", "\"As I am a recent graduate, I would like to be offered a fair salary that reflects my new education. I am most concerned with joining an organization that will help me to grow my career in marketing. Compensation is not my primary driver.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "What information is contained in the Accounts Receivable sub-ledger?", "answers": ["The interviewer is looking for your basic A/R knowledge as well as your ability to explain a straightforward concept in an easy to understand way. Walk the hiring authority through the information that an A/R sub-ledger would contain. Briefly describe the purpose of an A/R ledger, and why they are essential in accounting.", "\"An A/R sub-ledger is important because it displays the payment history of a customer who has been extended credit. This information includes all sales, payments, and allowances, allowing anyone looking at the file to have a full snapshot of the customers' financial activity.\"", "\"The accounts receivable sub-ledger is a record of all credit sales made by a business. It is useful for compiling one record for a customer that contains all payments, credit terms, and other important historical information.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Give me an example of when a credit memo would be issued.", "answers": ["Think of a credit memo as store credit! Businesses who have an unsatisfied customer, perhaps from a defective product or an error in delivery or an invoicing mistake, will often issue a credit memo. As an A/R specialist, you may not be able to adjust the original invoice, especially after delivery or if the invoice is past 30 days. Show the interviewer that you have worked with credit memos in the past. If you are new to your A/R career, show that you understand the purpose of a credit memo.", "\"A credit memo is issued to a customer, in a variety of circumstances, to reduce the balance that the customer owes. Credit memos allow for the fixing of errors without issuing a refund to a customer. I have issued many credit memos in my day and am aware of how to record these in most accounting systems.\"", "\"A credit memo is best explained as a store credit given to the customer from the seller. Credit memos are extended if there is an issue with a product or service after an invoice is sent out. The credit can be put towards the existing balance on a customer's account. A credit memo is not a refund.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Do you have experience setting up auto-invoicing for customer accounts?", "answers": ["The hiring authority is seeking further clues on your technical competency. It's one thing to use invoice templates as an A/R professional, but another skill to be able to customize these invoices and set up auto-invoices in a company's accounting software. Simply put, do you know how to set up recurring payments? Most accounting software allows businesses to set up automatic invoices or recurring invoices. Be ready to explain your proficiency in these systems.", "\"Auto-Invoicing allows a business to automatically invoice a customer on a regular basis through a recurring setup. This option is perfect for customers billed on a fixed time basis. There's no fuss with generating the invoice and in some cases sending the invoice to the customer. It's all done automatically and saves time. In the system we use, after setting up a recurring profile, I set up auto billing. After working in A/R for the past eight years, this is a very straightforward task for me.\"", "\"The way an A/R specialist will set up recurring payments will vary for each accounting software. While training, I learned to do this in QuickBooks, Xero, and Sage. I begin by setting up an invoice to occur at a particular time or chosen interval. Once this happens, I can set up auto-sends for the client on the same day, every month.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Why is excellent A/R execution important for a business?", "answers": ["The interviewer is testing your business understanding of the A/R function. There are a few reasons why organized and accurate accounts receivable execution is essential.\n\n1. Integrity and ethics associated with maintaining exceptional business records\n2. Ensuring customers are paying their bills means your business is receiving income\n3. Every business needs accurate records to know where the company is at financially\n4. Enables easier reporting when the A/R function is exceptional", "\"I believe in the phrase, 'Cash is King,' and that is where an accounts receivable department comes in. A/R is an asset on the balance sheet, but if a customer has not paid and has been extended credit, there is always the chance it can become a liability due to nonpayment. The A/R and Collections departments are responsible for collecting the cash flow for the company to pay the expenses and debt.\"", "\"Accounts receivable is important because it's the area of a business where customer debt becomes cash. Many customers will pay their debts within the normal amount of time, but calculations show that it takes a small business owner an average of 71 days to be paid.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "How much time needs to pass for an A/R account to be considered delinquent?", "answers": ["This question is a very straightforward one, as the industry standard is usually 90 days. This question is testing your very basic A/R knowledge. Feel free to expand on your response, showing that you are aware of different credit terms for various clients.", "\"From my experience, a delinquent account is 90 days; however, I have some clients with shorter credit terms who pay their invoices every 30 days, and some every 180 days. Is 90 days the average for our accounts here at Company ABC?\"", "\"The industry standard for an account to be considered delinquent is 90 days past from the due date. This timeline is the norm; however, not always. Some organizations may have tighter credit terms.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "How do you manage your time in Accounts Receivable?", "answers": ["With this behavioral based interview question, the hiring authority wants to hear that you are working wisely and not wasting much time during the day. Think about the ways that you control your time during the day. Perhaps you have a to-do list or plan your day using a particular app or software program. Whatever your method, ensure the interviewer that you are mindful of your time. Show that you deliver quickly on your work while maintaining exceptional quality and accuracy.", "\"Among the most effective ways to improve accounts receivable is by prioritizing the credit and collections activities. As a Senior A/R team lead, I take care of businesses most critical activities first, such as the largest outstanding invoices, delinquent accounts, etc. before moving on to less critical activities. This strategy helps to collect more efficiently, get paid faster, and increase cash flow. Without the right tools and processes in place, an A/R department can be slowed down significantly.\"", "\"When I first started with ABC Company, it was my first job out of college, and I felt that my days were unorganized. I am a very organized individual, but it felt as though I was always jumping from one thing to the next without completing a task. Finally, I asked a co-worker in my department, who did her job exceptionally, if I could shadow her for a day. With my manager's approval, I sat with this colleague for a full day and observed her workflow. To this day, I follow her methods with a few tweaks for myself, including the introduction of Trello for project management.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "What is a Customer Master Record?", "answers": ["The hiring authority would like to see how well you understand basic accounting terminology. Briefly describe the purpose of a Customer Master Record, and what type of information should be stored in the CMR. Also, discuss why an accurate Customer Master Record is essential for a business to keep.", "\"In my current position we keep Customer Master Records on everyone with whom we do business. The critical information included in these digital records consists of shipping and billing addresses, sales tax information, credit references, payment terms, primary contact information, and all signed documents. This record is essential for business operations to run smoothly, and for the accuracy of accounts.\"", "\"From my understanding, the Customer Master Record is originally set up by the salesperson in our company, and then it's maintained by me, the A/R Specialist. The information that I maintain and change when needed includes new company name, banking information for payment, business address, and contact information.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Have you ever worked in a cross-functional environment?", "answers": ["If you work for a larger company, you may have been asked to work on a project with teams from another department. Your ability to work with cross-functional teams will be a significant asset to your potential employer, especially if they are a larger organization. Maybe you headed a collections project which required you to collaborate with the members of the accounting and sales teams. Share any challenges that came up and what you learned from the experience.", "\"Yes, I have indeed worked in many cross-functional environments. Currently, I lead the A/R team and collaborate with the sales folks very regularly. We all work well together to ensure customer satisfaction and prompt payment with reasonable terms.\"", "\"My current company is pretty flat, as it's a family owned business with a few A/R clerks like myself. I can certainly see how a cross-functional environment would be helpful when it comes to having different team members with varying levels of expertise.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Walk me through your accounts receivable experience.", "answers": ["Bring your resume to life, walking the interviewer through a brief history of your accounts receivable experience. This question is open-ended, and it can be easy to give a long-winded answer. Remain focused by discussing your past job titles, how long you were employed there, and the volume of work you handled. You could also explain the type of customers you were typically working with, or what your most significant achievement was in each role. Mention one thing that you enjoyed about each job. This question offers an excellent opportunity to show the interviewer your passion for accounts receivable.", "\"I have spent the last eight years as a Senior Accounts Receivable and Collections Specialist. I currently oversee a team of three A/R specialists, focused primarily on keeping accounts receivable current by collecting from customers 15 days in arrears, or more. With a total of four team leads, my department has the lowest Days Sales Outstanding in over three years. This low DSO is something I'm very proud of, and it shows how diligent my team has been in collecting payment promptly.\"", "\"I currently work for Company ABC as an Accounts Receivable Specialist. This role has been my only A/R position since graduating with my Associates' Degree in Accounting. I'm solely responsible for invoicing, applying payments to the correct accounts, and collections. I am in a department of thirteen other A/R specialists, and I report directly to the accounts receivable manager. I have worked for my current employer for two and a half years and have drastically helped to reduce aged receivables and increase customer cash flow.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Explain to me the term DSO or, Days Outstanding.", "answers": ["The interviewer is looking for your level of familiarity with the term DSO or Days Outstanding. DSO or Days Outstanding and is a measure of the average number of days that it takes a company to collect payment after a sale is made. This metric is a significant one in accounts receivable. DSO = Total Accounts Receivable/Total Sales x Number of Days.", "\"Days Sales Outstanding is a method used to evaluate how active a company is at collecting receivables. This metric is used to measure the average number of days it takes a company to collect what is owed to them after a sale is complete. Put in fewer words; it is the average collection period. DSO has always been an emphasis for all companies I have worked and is calculated by total accounts receivable over total sales, multiplied by the number of days passed. A low DSO is an excellent thing!\"", "\"From what I learned in my latest accounting course is that DSO, or Days Outstanding, is determined on a monthly, quarterly and annual basis. It is a calculation of a company's average collection period. A low DSO can have a remarkable effect on a company's cash flow.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "How do you reconcile customer payments from credit card, ACH or wire, to cash or check,  in the A/R system?", "answers": ["Your response may vary based on your level of experience, but the main points are:\n\n1.  Recognize customer payment. Once payment is received, then it will need to be applied to the customer account in the system. This means that accounts receivable is debited (decreased) and cash will be credited (increased).\n\n2. Reconcile the payment type. Depending on how the customer payment was received, it will need to be reconciled. For example, if the payment was an ACH, then it's essential to double check the bank entry matches the system entry, and this includes any banking fees.", "\"Having worked in A/R for over 15 years, I know this is a process the must be done on a daily basis, no matter the size of the company.  'Cash is King' and timelines of cash recognition is critical to a business. As a team leader, I reconcile all cash accounts on a daily basis and ensure all A/R team is also doing this. The receiving of cash promptly allows Senior Level Managers to view the cash flow statement and understand how much money the business receives on a weekly basis to help them manage the business and be able to make timely payments on the expenses. All this is part of the forecast, and my side of the equation is to ensure accurate recording of cash and receivables.\"", "\"In my current job I am the only A/R clerk, and at month end the Accounting Manager will reconcile the cash account. My daily duties are to ensure all payments are reconciled and processed daily, so each month the Accounting Manager is double checking my work. The entries I'm not responsible for, are any fees associated with wire transfer or credit card fees. This is an entry done by my Supervisor.  I have a daily routine, and this includes checking all customer payment systems at the beginning and end of each day.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Have you ever had to prepare a bill or invoice for services rendered? If so what should be included?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear proof that you understand the basics of accounting. The information you need to include on an invoice varies depending on the specific services you perform, but most invoices should consist of: \n\n- Company contact information\n- Company logo\n- Customer purchase order number (also known as a PO)\n- Number of service hours, or price per item\n- Dates\n- Client contact information\n- Total amount due\n- Item descriptions\n- Freight, for physical products\n- Payment terms\n- Payment due date\n\nExpress to the interviewer that you understand the work that goes into invoicing. Also, if you have ever made invoice templates before, you can mention this experience.", "\"Depending on the company and what they are purchasing, there might be some differences, but the preparation of a bill usually includes: service provider's details, description of service or product, the organizations name and address, taxes, appropriate dates include the invoice and the due date, and net terms. I have created thousands of invoices in my A/R career and fully understand the importance of accuracy and consistency.\"", "\"For the most part, we used templated invoices when I was learning about billing and invoices, in school. I can follow any template or create custom invoices, depending on your needs. A bill for services rendered should have appropriate contact information, dates, a clear breakdown of the services rendered, total amount with tax rates, and due date with payment terms.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "When have you had to be extra thorough in completing tasks?", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to know that you are willing to go the extra mile when it's required. Some accounts receivable tasks will require a keener eye and additional diligence. Discuss a time when you were extra thorough during work-related tasks.", "\"In my current inventory control job the company was getting a lot of complaints about late deliveries. I met with the delivery staff and discovered that the problem seemed to be with the stock arriving on time. I investigated and found kinks in our new inventory request process. The backlog was in the orders department as they were not following up adequately with the suppliers. I implemented a system for faster and more accurate follow-up. This system sorted out the stock problems, and the delivery staff was able to meet their deadlines.\"", "\"We changed our product catalog recently, so I had to re-memorize a lot of products, codes, and pricing. That following week was month end, so I needed to have my product knowledge up to snuff so that I could invoice quickly. I was proud of my ability to retain all of that data in such a short amount of time.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "If a customer is also a vendor and not paying their invoice, do you think it is good practice to pay them with the open A/R dollar amount?", "answers": ["The interviewer is looking to see how you troubleshoot, and where you stand when it comes to handling cross-over accounts that are in arrears. It's not a common practice to do this, and one that most Controllers dislike. Most schools will agree when you are taking your A/R training, that this is not the best practice; however, a business must do what they have to, to receive payment. Discuss your thoughts on this practice.", "\"I have found that in small to mid-sized businesses, where the customer is also a vendor, the businesses will swap A/R and A/P amounts to settle accounts. I worked for a small metal shop with annual sales revenue of $6M, and the company hit a very slow sales window for four months. This dip in business put the company behind on paying off the vendors. The A/P was almost 90% over 45+ days, and the vendors were threatening to cut us off on a daily basis. The Accounting Manager was forced to swap the open A/R balances to pay down the open vendor invoices. This swap was done on several accounts, and was used as a last option to keep day to day business and operations running.\"", "\"My current experience is with a large multinational company, and it will not allow a business swap their A/R or A/P to pay down one. But, as I learned in school, business owners and Senior Managers must do what they have to to keep the business operating. I am sure that I will see more of this practice as I gain further accounting experience.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Name for me the most important functions of an A/R department.", "answers": ["The accounts receivable department is critical, for any company. The responsibilities of the department may include: \n\n- Customer credit limit applications/approvals\n- Establishing payment terms with new customers \n- Overviews of customer credit history\n- Sending customer invoices and follow up on them \n- Updating customer data in master files  \n- Follow up on late payments \n- Communicating payment issues and flagging unstable accounts \n- Creating invoices \n- Receiving payments and applying them to the correct accounts \n\nShow the interviewer that you take pride in your job, as an A/R Specialist. Discuss why you believe your role.", "\"A/R performance has a significant effect on a company's cash flow, so it's crucial that business employes talented A/R people who are organized, detailed, and unafraid to pick up the phone and collect payment. An excellent accounts receivable department will track customer payments, send invoices promptly, keep updated master records, follow up on overdue accounts, and take action when customers are non-responsive.\"", "\"I believe that an accounts receivable department has a major role in any company. The responsibilities of the department are the approval of a customers' credit limit by studying the history of the customer. The department sends invoices promptly, updates customer statements and make sure to follow up with the customers' payment commitments.  An A/R department can have a huge impact on a business' cash flow situation by ensuring few payments are left outstanding.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Have you encountered Factoring in your professional experience?", "answers": ["If you are unaware, Factoring is when one company will purchase another company's accounts receivables. This purchase gives a company immediate cash flow to work with, to pay for business needs such as payroll or new equipment. Factoring will generally occur when one company is in financial trouble due to too many outstanding receivables. This situation is never one that a company would desire. Discuss your exposure to factoring, and how you dealt with the process.", "\"I understand that some companies with extraordinarily long payment terms may find themselves in trouble with cash flow and too many outstanding receivables. This situation is when factoring would come into play. This circumstance is not one that I have ever encountered as an accounts receivable specialist. It's essential that I am highly diligent with every account, never allowing payments to slip through the cracks.\"", "\"Unpaid accounts can be a slippery slope and, for some businesses that are cash poor, this can lead to the Factoring. I understand this practice to be that of selling receivables, at a discount, to another company. Somewhat like collections. Companies will only do this if they need quick cash and cannot wait for the duration of the credit terms.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "What are the most common issues related to Accounts Receivable?", "answers": ["The issues which you most often come across in your role as an A/R specialist will show the interviewer the level of responsibility that you currently take on in your position. What you deal with will say a lot about the tasks required of you on a daily basis. \n\nSome examples may include: \n\n- Your customers cannot pay their invoice on time\n- You are responsible for collection calls or setting up customer payment plans\n- You are fixing inaccurate invoices with old customer information \n- Customers are short paying accounts", "\"Some issues that I continually face in my current role include slow paying customers with too much credit extended, short payments from customers without any prior communication, customers bringing up dissatisfaction for their service after the invoice has aged over 30 days. I am, of course, able to handle these issues swiftly and professionally.\"", "\"The current issues that I experience in my A/R role include invoice discrepancies, client dissatisfaction with the goods or services, customers changing invoice terms despite a contract being in place, and many aged accounts resulting in a high amount of bad debts.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "After receiving a customers' payment, what do you do next?", "answers": ["This question is a very straightforward one that you can answer by drawing on your experience or academic knowledge. Because it is an open-ended question, it is easy to get stuck on your response. Think of the processes that you follow every day, and walk the interviewer through those steps.", "\"Depending on how the customer payment was received; prepayment or final payment, will determine the next steps. If the customer payment is cash, check, ACH, or wire then it needs to be appropriately applied to outstanding customer invoice. Once I take this step, then I recognize the cash deposit in the cash account.\"", "\"From my understanding, when a customer payment is received, the payment is applied against the open invoice and properly posted to the general ledger. Then the cash will need to be recognized and the invoice updated.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "As an A/R Specialist, you will be customer facing. Have you received any formal customer service training?", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to know about any formal training you have received, related to customer service. This training could include a robust onboarding plan, on-the-job training, courses taken, or even books that you have read in your spare time. Show the interviewer that you have an interest in bettering your customer service delivery. This question is a great time to ask the interviewer about their company-specific customer service training and manuals.", "\"Near the beginning of my career, I did take a course on customer service basics as well as training on collection calls. There are best practices that I still implement today, such as active listening, not interrupting, and repeating the problem back to the customer. Because much of my role is over the phone and computer, I have to rely on my voice or wording so keeping a pleasant tone is important.\"", "\"I am newer to my career so I cannot say that I have received any customer service-specific training. I would be happy to take any training that you recommend and would love to hear more about your specific training program.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Have you ever broken company rules, or payment terms, to make a customer happy?", "answers": ["Breaking the rules, and bending them, CAN be different from each other. Often, organizations are okay with you bending the rules to keep a customer happy. You need to know your audience, though! If the company is very stringent when it comes to their policies and procedures, then approach this question with caution. If the organization is well known for being flexible, then you can indeed be more free with your answer.", "\"My current company is pretty strict with their policies, so I do not bend to make a customer happy, but I will escalate the issue to someone who has the seniority to decide that. I agree with your organization that it's important to offer some flex on policy, within reason of course.\"", "\"I have been trained to know that rules and policy are there for a reason. If I were not sure what to do or were asked to break or bend a rule, I would refer to my employee manual or ask a manager to assist.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "In your opinion, what makes you a great problem solver?", "answers": ["Employers want to know that you have a systematic approach to problem-solving. Consider the skills and qualities that help you successfully face problems. Perhaps you have a keen eye for detail. Maybe you can see opportunity when others can only focus on the issue. Share your strengths as a problem solver, and your ability to come up with innovative solutions.\n\nStrong problem solvers are: \n\n- Systematic thinkers\n- Open minded\n- Okay with being wrong sometimes\n- Always researching and exploring\n- Able to identify the core problem \n- Able to reverse engineer a challenge to avoid future issues\n- Ready to come up with multiple avenues that work well for all stakeholders\n- Are do-ers and not worriers", "\"I am a great problem solver because I can compartmentalize all aspects of a problem before studying it. I also like to bring more experienced team members in to add to the solution. I will never try to be a hero and solve a complicated problem without tapping into the resources around me.\"", "\"What makes me a great problem solver is that I have a keen ability to research, read, and explore so that my recommendations are based on fact and study rather than guesses.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Do you have any plans for continued education?", "answers": ["Some A/R roles do not require post-secondary education, while others need an Associate's Degree or even a Bachelor's Degree. The interviewer would like to know if you are planning to complete some higher education. If you are, it is essential that you express your desire to work in tandem with your classes. The concern of the interviewer is that you will be hired, trained, and then want to leave your job to go back to school full time.\n\nSome organizations will offer tuition support or a reimbursement program for their employees who wish to continue their education. If they do provide this type of perk, you can indeed show interest but make sure that your continued education aspirations are related to the industry and job. If you are working as an accounts receivable professional, you want to avoid saying that you would like to take courses in zoology.", "\"I believe that continued education is always a good idea. I like to expand my knowledge when possible. With that said, my job would always come first. I understand that you have a tuition reimbursement program for your employees seeking related coursework. I would be interested in learning more about this down the road.\"", "\"I like the idea of taking some coursework in Excel and Powerpoint; however, I have no plans to exit the workforce to gain another degree for instance. If other industry related opportunities present themselves, I would be interested.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "How do you handle an insufficient funds notice after trying to process a customer payment?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know how you handle uncomfortable customer situations. Show the interviewer that, despite the position you're in being awkward, you can stay calm, cool and respectful while following company procedures. Keep in mind that most customers have great intentions, and odds are, they just made a mistake.", "\"In my current role, we have processes and procedures in place to handle this type of scenario. In my case, I will call the customer directly and be casual about it, on the first call. In all my years of working, I have only had this happened a handful of times, and typically there is a logical explanation like the customer had a check bounce from someone, used the wrong check from a closed account, or their credit card expired, and they were unaware. When you are friendly with customers, they will always find a way to repair the situation as soon as possible.\"", "\"A bounced client payment has only happened to me once, and I started by calling the company directly. I learned that the client accidentally paid the invoice with a check from a closed account. They apologized for any inconvenience and sent another payment right away. We run credit checks on our clients who pay Net 30 or longer, which is why this is generally not an issue in my current role.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Do you think cash should be accepted as a form of payment?", "answers": ["There are some industries where cash payments are not accepted and other sectors, such as retail and food where cash payments are welcome. Your response is going to depend on the company and the industry with which you are interviewing. Either way, try to respond in a way that does not single out a particular payment type.", "\"From what I have read in the news recently, some countries are trying to become a cashless society, such as Sweden, where this is a hot-button topic at the moment. For myself, I love to have cash available, and I will use it when paying for food or other quick transactions. Larger purchases; however, are tracked much better when there is a trail associated with a credit card or cheque based transaction. I have worked in 3 different industries; manufacturing, restaurant, and banking. I do not see banks moving to a cashless option any time soon. I do know that many small restaurants are moving to a cashless option, due to the growing concern of having to deposit the cash. In my opinion, this is a risk. Moving to a cashless option is slowing happening, but all industries will not embrace it.\"", "\"In my growing experience and coming from a younger generation, I rarely carry or use cash. I mostly use a debit or credit card. We debated this topic while I was earning my associates' degree, and our class was divided on this topic. I know of a few restaurants in New York that have moved to a cashless policy but feel this is more of an isolated case. I believe this scenario is a slow trend that we will be seeing it happening more and more. Cash-heavy businesses are an easy target for robbers, and e-transactions are an easy target for hacking and have higher fees for business, so there are two sides of the coin in this debate. I also see cryptocurrency transactions increasing, because of the meager fees involved.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "Have you ever worked for a company that accepted cryptocurrency as a form of payment?", "answers": ["Since cryptocurrency is still not mainstream, there is a high likelihood that your response to this question will be 'no.' The point of the interviewer asking this question is to find out if you have taken the time to research and learn about crypto payments. \n\nBriefly discuss what you know about cryptocurrency and be sure to express interest in learning more. An excellent question for the interviewer in return is if the interviewing company currently accepts any form of cryptocurrency. If they do not, perhaps it's in the works!", "\"I'm very familiar with cryptocurrency, and it's a very hot topic in the Revenue Recognition arena, which impacts accounts receivables. Cryptocurrency may not be currently recognized as revenue on our income statements when the payment is received, but the time is coming. I am eager to learn more about these forms of payment and how they will affect business accounting, overall.\"", "\"In my six months of accounts receivable experience, I have not yet worked with cryptocurrency as a form of payment. I'm familiar with the concept; however, and follow a few blogs on the topic. Cryptocurrency values fluctuate dramatically so for some businesses; it does not make sense to accept this form of payment quite yet. I do look forward to seeing how this plays out in the future months and years.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "When a customer is unable to pay, what are steps that you have taken to retrieve the money?", "answers": ["As an accounts receivable specialist, you will come across situations where you need to get creative with clients, to collect payments. Some common steps are:\n\n1. Communicate the aged invoice/invoices to your direct report\n2. Follow up with the client by phone, regularly\n3. Send reminder letters and emails\n4. Escalate your calls to the department head \n5. Legal action/outside collection firms are an option once all avenues have been exhausted", "\"My current employer has annual sales of $480M, and one part of the job that is inevitable is contacting customers who are unable to pay. The four steps that I take to retrieve money from a customer unable to pay are to be proactive, contact the client immediately and consistently, and be ready to accept the inevitable, which is usually going to collections. I am sure never to make empty threats and to remain professional at all times. The best case scenario is to agree on repayment terms, and to get those terms in writing.\"", "\"In my recent A/R training, I learned that it's important to be persistent and consistently follow up by phone, email, and letters. Documentation of every interaction is also key. If my attempts go unrecognized, I am to engage the accounts receivable manager and communicate with them on the aged invoice.\""]}, {"topic": "Accounts+Receivable+Specialist", "question": "When you see a large account starting to age, and they are a very good customer, what do you do?", "answers": ["The interviewer is looking for an answer that displays the fact you are detailed oriented, willing to take the initiative and are proactive. As an A/R professional, healthy client relationships can be the difference between a client who pays late and a client who respects your payment terms. Show the interviewer that you understand the balance between great client relationships and timely payment collections.", "\"Working in accounts receivable for over eight years, I have heard almost every story and excuses for not paying on time. My first A/R job was for an assisted living facility. The facilities aging report was over 90% past due, and the largest customer was Medicare. The regulations and proper submission of paperwork into Medicare are very time-consuming, and I dedicated over 20 hours a week to submit all the proper requested paperwork. Frustrated with returned paperwork, I dedicated six weeks of calling into Medicare and talking with customer service, who walked me through the proper online submission of new claims and earlier active claims. I created instructions on how to properly submit claims to Medicare and brought the aging report to current. The experience helped me to be patient, and seek information. Once I had the information, then I was able to troubleshoot the root cause and create an iron-clad process we could all follow in the future.\"", "\"I have worked as an Accounts Receivable Clerk for six months, managing one customer account that is worth nearly 30% of my employers' revenue. Shortly after starting my job, the customer's aging report started to grow from the 30-60 days outstanding into the 60+ day's arrears mark. I notified my manager, at which point the account status escalated to the President of the company. Payment was received in full, within 30 days.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What have you done recently to become a better bookkeeper?", "answers": ["This question allows the interviewer to gauge how motivated you are to learn new skills.  They will most likely be looking for a candidate that takes initiative to learn, so be sure to call out recent examples where you have acquired new skills.", "\"I am always looking for ways to learn more about my profession and acquire new skills.  As an example, I recently took a two week online course called Advanced Bookkeeping where I learned new skills related to inventory accounting.  Since your organization is a retailer, I believe I could use the knowledge obtained from this course in the bookkeeper role.  Once in the role, I would also seek out continuing education that allows me to apply skills acquired to help the organization.\"", "\"To become a better bookkeeper I make sure that I am staying up to date on relevant topics. I also look for opportunities where I am able to grow.\"", "Great.  Can you bring both of these topics back to the opportunity?  What relevant topics have you learned about lately?  Is this an area that would be interesting to the interviewer (and a way to engage in conversation)?   In what ways would you like to enhance your skills (and as a result, add more value to the job)?"]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "How would you handle working in an increasingly remote work environment?", "answers": ["This is a question to gauge if you are disciplined enough to work from home.  Be sure to touch on how you would stay focused and communicate with team members.  Even after things return to normal, remote work may continue to be more common across many industries including accounting.", "\"I have experience working remotely.  At my internship, we were able to work from home on Fridays in the summer.  I enjoyed working from home and was able to stay on task and communicate effectively with my team members.  There were some ground rules I implemented, such as maintaining regular hours, keeping my morning routine as if I was going to the office, and scheduling breaks to take care of non-work related tasks. I also had a standing meeting with my manager and team members every morning to discuss priorities for the day.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are some methods you use to self-review your work?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to evaluate your ability to check your own work and, as a result, save your manager precious time by catching mistakes before they reach his or her desk.  Give specific examples of procedures you have implemented in previous roles to catch mistakes.", "\"Being able to self-review my work and catch mistakes is something I take very seriously.  A bookkeeper spends a lot of time in the details, so it is sometimes difficult to catch errors.  Given this, I implement checklists that require me to tie out balances, subtotal transactions, and other to-dos before I move forward in the close process.  In a way, I am auditing my work to catch any mistakes or errors.  This not only saves me time in the long run, but also saves my manager time as there is less back and forth resolving issues.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Do you have experience working with external auditors?", "answers": ["A key responsibility of a bookkeeper is to interact with and assist the external auditors.  You may be asked to assist with walkthroughs, which are interviews where the auditor documents the processes you follow each month, as part of their assessment of internal controls.  You may also be asked to either provide existing schedules (bank reconciliations, debt schedules, etc) or prepare schedules for the audit.", "\"Yes, in my last role I interacted with our external auditors frequently in a variety of ways.  First, as part of their assessment of internal controls, I would sit down with them to complete walkthroughs of the processes I follow each month.  Additionally, I would prepare schedules that they would test as part of their audit.  Examples of these schedules include balance sheet reconciliations and amortization schedules for our intangible assets.  Finally, I would prepare draft footnote schedules for the audited financial statements.  I believe it's very important to have a good working relationship with the organization's auditors.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Do you have experience explaining complex accounting concepts to non-financial personnel?", "answers": ["Bookkeepers will frequently interact with other departments within the company.  Many times, the employees in these departments do not have extensive knowledge of accounting concepts and terminology.  This question is an opportunity to highlight your communication skills.", "\"Yes, in my previous role I was able to interact with non-finance personnel when I would meet with the marketing team to review their results each month.  They didn\u2019t have a strong understanding of accounting principles, so I tried to \u2018speak their language\u2019 as much as possible when discussing their department\u2019s results vs budget.  I believe I have the ability to communicate effectively with all personnel in an organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What is your comfort level with interacting and communicating with senior leadership?", "answers": ["A bookkeeper role is staff level but is unique in that the role interacts regularly with senior leadership. Highlight that you not only have experience presenting in front of leadership, but also that you are comfortable doing it.  Be specific with what you presented.  For example, monthly results, pitches for new initiatives, etc.", "\"I have ample experience getting in front of leadership and presenting.  In my previous role, I would present to the CEO, CFO and other senior leaders during our monthly Finance Review meetings.  I always felt the need to prepare in advance for any questions that might arise, and would often circle back promptly on follow-ups that developed during those meetings.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Are you proficient in Excel?", "answers": ["Excel proficiency is a must for not only a bookkeeper, but any role in accounting.  At a minimum, a bookkeeper should be able to sort through large amounts of data and analyze that data using pivot tables.", "\"Yes, I am proficient in Excel.  I have used Excel extensively throughout my time in school, as well as in my previous role.  For example, I used data sorting and filtering, as well as pivot tables to organize large amounts of data.  Additionally, I have experience using V-Lookups and H-Lookups to pull together analysis for our external auditors.  I have even dipped my toes into data visualization software such as Tableau, but that is a skill I would like to continue to nurture.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Give some examples of non-cash expenses.", "answers": ["This is a technical question that tests whether you are able to identify non-cash expenses.  Non-cash expenses are items that reduce profitability even though there isn't cash being paid in the period.  A good example is depreciation expense, where the asset is purchased and then expense is recognized over its useful life.", "\"Depreciation expense is the most common non-cash expense, as the cash is spent upfront and then expense is recognized over the life of the asset.  Amortization expense is another example, and it is most commonly associated with items such as software, intangible assets and long-term contracts.  It's important for a bookkeeper to be familiar with these items, as they are added back to net income on the statement of cash flows.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What accounting software are you familiar with?", "answers": ["Speak specifically to the accounting systems you have used and some of the functions you performed.  Many job descriptions specifically state which accounting software the company uses.  If any event, make sure to highlight that you are quick to learn new software systems.", "\"In my last role, I used SAP to book journal entries and run queries.  As an independent contractor, I also used Quickbooks to complete monthly bookkeeping for various clients.  I used that software to book journal entries, complete bank reconciliations, run monthly reports, and invoice customers.  Since I have an underlying understanding of accounting, I am easily able to learn new software packages.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Are you a detail oriented person?", "answers": ["The bookkeeper position requires great attention to detail, as the role is in charge of producing and maintaining meticulous financial records.  It is expected that the bookkeeper can catch mistakes before reporting is provided to leaders of the organization.", "\"Yes, I am extremely detail oriented.  Part of what makes me a great bookkeeper is my organization skills and ability to self-review my work.  I know that providing financial information containing errors creates doubt among leadership that the financial records are accurate.  Therefore, I implement systems that allow me to check the details, such as monthly checklists and reviews.\"", "\"Yes, I am a detail-oriented person. It is important to me to make sure I am reviewing and looking over everything. My strong organization skills help me stay efficient in being able to look at the details in every task.\"", "Great start.  Can you give an example that will help show your detailed orientation in action?"]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are the steps involved in the accounting close process?", "answers": ["This question is used to assess whether your understanding of the accounting close process aligns with the organization's.  Don't go into too much detail - rather, just hit the key steps and then ask how it compares or differs from the organization's process.", "\"First and foremost, there needs to be a closing calendar so that deadlines are set for all departments.  Next, all data must be gathered.  This includes departments such as payroll and accounts payable preparing reports needed for journal entries.  Next, all journal entries are booked.  After journal entries are booked and reviewed, financial statements are prepared and balance sheet reconciliations are completed.  Finally, the results are reviewed with leadership.  Is there anything I described that differs from the process here at XYZ Corporation?\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are the steps involved in the bank reconciliation process?", "answers": ["Bank reconciliations are a key responsibility of any bookkeeper role.  These days, most accounting software packages (such as Quickbooks) make the process easy.  However, a bookkeeper should know the steps that are involved.", "\"In order to complete a bank reconciliation, a bank statement or export file of bank activity needs to be obtained for the prior month.  The bookkeeper should enter the ending bank balance in the accounting software.  Next, the bookkeeper should check off the transactions that have cleared the bank.  There may be some transactions that need to be added to the general ledger, such as bank charges.  If the reconciliation ties out to the bank balance, the reconciliation is complete.  If not, differences should be investigated.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are the different inventory valuation methods?", "answers": ["The goal of inventory valuation is to assign a monetary value to inventory the company owns that has not yet been sold.  There are generally four accepted inventory valuation methods:  Specific Identification, First In, First Out (FIFO), Last In, First Out (LIFO) and Weighted Average Cost.  Each has its own advantages and disadvantages, so be prepared to briefly speak to each.", "\"There are four widely accepted inventory valuation methods.  The most clear cut is specific identification, where the cost of every item in inventory is specifically tracked.  This method is best used when the company sells a low volume of high value items (such as rare cars).  Next is First-In, First-Out, which presumes the first inventory purchased by the company is the first sold to the customer. Most companies use FIFO to value their inventory.  Last-In, First-Out assumes the newest inventory in stock is the first sold.  Finally, there's weighted average cost, which takes the cost of all products in inventory divided by the number of units.  This method is used when the products a company sells are very similar.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "How do you mitigate and manage stress?", "answers": ["The life of a bookkeeper can be stressful, especially during busier times like monthly close and the annual audit.  The interviewer wants to gain insight into how you react to stressful situations.", "\"Due to tight deadlines and the demands of the bookkeeper role, stress is inevitable.  However, there are steps I take to help mitigate stress.  First, I try to be as organized as possible.  I am constantly prioritizing my workload to make sure time-sensitive tasks are handled before they are due.  Next, I try to leave work at work.  When not at work, I enjoy hiking, cooking, and traveling.  Being able to enjoy these activities makes me feel calmer and rejuvenated at work.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are the differences between accrual accounting and cash accounting?", "answers": ["Accrual basis accounting and cash basis accounting are the two most commonly used accounting methodologies.  A bookkeeper should understand the differences between the two methodologies, and understand that most company\u2019s use accrual accounting as it presents a clearer picture of financial health.", "\"The main difference between accrual accounting and cash accounting is when revenue and expenses are recognized.  Under cash basis accounting, revenue and expenses are recognized when cash is received and paid.  Under accrual accounting, revenue is recognized in the period it is earned and expenses are recognized in the period they are incurred.  While cash basis accounting is easier to implement, accrual accounting is used by most businesses and presents a clearer picture of a company\u2019s overall financial health.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are the three main financial statements and what do they indicate about an organization\u2019s financial position?", "answers": ["The three main financial statements are the income statement, balance sheet, and statement of cash flows.  A bookkeeper should know the statements in detail, as they will likely be preparing all three each month.", "\"The income statement shows profitability over a period of time by showing revenue less expenses.  The balance sheet summarizes a company's assets, liabilities, and equity at a point in time.  And a cash flow statement shows the net cash inflows and outflows over a period of time.  Each statement is essential in order to gain insights into the financial health of an organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "How do you manage your manager?  In other words, what steps do you take to make sure you get what you need from your boss and make both your lives easier?", "answers": ["Also known as 'managing up', 'managing your manager' is a soft skill that can be developed over time.  It essentially means doing whatever is necessary to make your manager's job easier.  Some clear-cut benefits of managing up include increased productivity and better working relationships between boss and employee.", "\"I am a firm believer in the benefits of managing my manager.  At the end of the day, I want to make the audit engagements we work on together run as smoothly as possible.  One area where I really focus on is communicating and prioritizing workload on a regular basis.  This ensures that I'm always working on the highest-priority items.   Another thing that is crucial is understanding my manager's style.  For example, do they like regular check-ins by email throughout the day, scheduled catch-up meetings, etc.  Then, I tailor my communication to their style.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are Days Sales Outstanding, and what is indicated when days outstanding grows?", "answers": ["This is a question that gauges whether you understand metrics and can use them to catch trends in the business.  Days Sales Outstanding is a metric that measures the health of Accounts Receivable.  A high or growing balance indicates that there is a collections problem.", "\"Days Sales Outstanding is an important metric that measures the health of Accounts Receivable.  The metric indicates how many days of sales are hung up in accounts receivable at any given time.  A growing balance indicates that there may be some issues with collections, which could lead to cash flow problems in the near future.  Given this, collections should be monitored closely and adjusted accordingly, if DSO is growing.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Why did you want to become a bookkeeper?", "answers": ["This question is a way for the interviewer to find out a little bit about what makes you tick.  Be honest and direct - don't give a phony answer that the interviewer will see through.", "\"Since I was young, I have always liked math and have been good with numbers.  I took an accounting class in high school and really enjoyed it - the concepts came naturally to me.  I also aspire to be a key contributor to an organization, and I know that the bookkeeper role is visible to leadership.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What do you do when you don\u2019t know the answer to something?", "answers": ["There is no shame in being stumped - it happens to everyone at all levels of an organization.  This question is an opportunity to highlight your ability to be independent and resourceful.", "\"I have no problem seeking solutions to questions I encounter.  If I am unsure about the accounting treatment for a certain transaction, I can reach out to our external auditors for advice on the appropriate accounting treatment.  If it\u2019s something technical, such as using a new Excel formula, I am good at researching online and following examples.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What have you done at your previous job to reduce costs or save time?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know if you have the ability to improve processes.  Speak to a specific action you took that resulted in reduced costs, saved time or gained better insights.", "\"My last role was bookkeeper for a small, established company.  However, my predecessor did not have established procedures in place, and it sounded like he had made constant mistakes.  One of the first things I did when I started was I made a monthly checklist that detailed all the steps I took during the monthly close.  Included in these steps were checks I performed to self review my work.  The checklist served as a cover sheet that I would hand off to my manager so that she would know exactly what steps I completed.  This led to increased efficiency as we estimated it saved 4-6 hours a month in error corrections.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Are you willing to work extra hours if needed during busier times?", "answers": ["The life of a bookkeeper is tied to the month-end close calendar, which could result in a schedule that is \u2018lumpy\u2019 and not a typical 9-5.  The candidate should expect there to be some additional time worked during busier times and should highlight that they are flexible.", "\"Yes, I am willing to work extra hours as needed.  I understand that the work required ramps up during month-end close, tax filings and other busier times.  I am happy to be flexible and work as needed to make sure the job gets done.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are Days Inventory on Hand, and what is indicated when days on hand grows?", "answers": ["This is a question that gauges whether you understand metrics and can use them to catch trends in the business.  Days Inventory on Hand is a metric that measures the health of the inventory asset.  A high or growing metric indicates that there are problems selling through inventory.", "\"Days Inventory on Hand is an important metric that measures the health of Inventory.  The metric indicates how many days of cost of goods sold are hung up in inventory at any given time.  A low number of days indicates that the company is efficiently selling through inventory.  A growing number of days indicates that there may be some issues with sell-through, which could lead to obsolescence issues in the future.  Given this, sales strategy should be adjusted if Inventory DOH is growing.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are Days Payable Outstanding, and what is indicated when days outstanding grows?", "answers": ["This is a question that gauges whether you understand metrics and can use them to catch trends in the business.  Days Payable Outstanding is a metric that measures the health of accounts payable.  A high or growing metric indicates that you are able to pay your vendors on increasingly favorable terms, which is beneficial to cash flow management.", "\"Days Payable Outstanding is an important metric that measures the health of accounts payable.  The metric indicates how many days of expenses are hung up in accounts payable at any given time.  A low number of days indicates that the company is paying their bills quickly.  A growing number of days indicates that the company is taking advantage of favorable vendor terms, which helps with cash flow management.  As long as bills are not overdue, it is a sound strategy to have longer payment terms with vendors.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What are some examples of internal controls that impact the bookkeeper role?", "answers": ["Internal controls are rules or procedures that are put in place to protect financial and accounting information and to prevent fraud.  Some are required by laws and regulations, while others are implemented to protect the company.  There are many examples of internal controls that can impact the bookkeeper role, including preventative controls (segregation of duties, chains of approval, physical control of assets (locks on doors), training programs) and detective controls (monthly reconciliations, budget to actual comparisons, inventory counts).", "\"There are many examples of internal controls that would impact my role.  Preventative controls like segregation of duties and approval requirements will limit the activities I can perform.  I will also be involved in detective internal control procedures, such as monthly reconciliations of balance sheet accounts and budget to actual comparisons.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "What is depreciation expense, and how is it recognized?", "answers": ["Depreciation is the gradual expensing of the cost of a fixed asset over its useful life.  Depreciation expense aligns with the accrual method of accounting, as the total cost of the asset is spread over a period of time, rather than expensed in full when purchased.  Most companies use straight-line depreciation, which spreads the cost evenly over the asset's useful life.", "\"Depreciation expense is the portion of a fixed asset cost that is being used up during the current period.  When a fixed asset is purchased, the cost is capitalized on the balance sheet.  Each period, depreciation expense is recognized which reduces the asset balance. While there are many ways to depreciate an asset, most companies use the straight-line method of depreciation.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Do you have any experience with invoicing vendors?", "answers": ["A common responsibility of a bookkeeper is to invoice vendors and ensure that balances are paid timely.  In your response, be sure to highlight that you know the steps of the invoicing process and possess the qualities needed to perform the duties.", "\"Yes, in my previous role, I was responsible for managing the accounts receivable process from start to finish.  First, I would produce an invoice each time a service was performed and record the sale to the general ledger.  Next I would send out the invoices to the clients.  At my previous company, clients were invoiced both electronically and by mail.  When payments were made, I would apply the payments against the client's outstanding invoices.  Finally, I would follow up with customers who had not paid their invoices timely.  I am very detail oriented and organized, which I believe are necessary to perform the invoicing process effectively.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Imagine that you are producing a month-end report and notice the ledger is off.  What would you do to rectify this situation?", "answers": ["This question is being asked to assess your self-review skills, as well as your problem solving skills.  First discuss how you would discover the error during your review.  Then, cover the steps you would take to resolve.", "\"I pride myself on self-reviewing my work.  During month-end, I follow a checklist that helps catch errors.  If I discovered an error during my review, I would first check formulas to make sure the report itself is footing correctly.  If there is nothing wrong with the report itself, I would then drill down to the account level by searching for the amount of the error. If the error was not in the account ledger, I would then drill down to the source document level.  I enjoy problem solving and would find the issue efficiently.\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "Which statements or reports would you prepare as part of your month-end close package?", "answers": ["A bookkeeper is often responsible for producing month-end reports.  An income statement and balance sheet are almost always produced, as well as a statement of cash flows.  Additionally, there may be specific reports that a company can use, such as key performance indicators (KPIs), and customer/vendor detail.", "\"Month-End Reporting should give leadership the information they need to see how the business is performing.  To achieve this visibility, there are some core reports I would include in the reporting package each month.  First and foremost, I would include a balance sheet, income statement and statement of cash flows.  For supplemental schedules, I would include a summary of key performance indicators, as well as a sales breakdown.  Are there any other schedules that leadership at this company would like to see each month?\""]}, {"topic": "Bookkeeper", "question": "True or False:  For vendor invoices, it is always best to pay the bill as soon as possible.", "answers": ["This is a bit of a trick question, and tests your understanding of cash flow.  As a general rule of thumb, it is almost always better to receive cash from customers as quickly as possible and pay vendors as slowly as possible (while still adhering to the payment terms).  The goal of doing this is to maximize cash on hand which provides flexibility for the company.", "\"That statement is false.  When it comes to Accounts Payable and the payment of invoices, it is better to use the vendor payment terms to our advantage.  If we pay bills as soon as they are received, that ties up cash that could have been used for other purposes.  The only time it may be advantageous to pay sooner than the due date is if there is a discount for paying earlier.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Are you familiar with Simply Accounting? Rate yourself as a Beginner, Intermediate or Advanced user.", "answers": ["Discuss with the hiring manager your level of knowledge in Simply Accounting. If you have been recently tested on your abilities, be sure to include those results as well. Mention any courses or additional training that you have taken in Simply Accounting.", "\"I would consider myself an Advanced level user in Simply Accounting. I have used the program for six years and have trained others on the proper use of the program as well.\"", "\"I have a small amount of hands-on training in Simply Accounting so, for that reason, I would rate myself as a beginner in this program. If you desire stronger skills than I currently possess, I am happy to take some related training, before starting this position with your company.\"", "\"I have a small amount of hands-on training in Simply Accounting so, for that reason, I would rate myself as a beginner in this program. If you desire stronger skills than I currently possess, I am happy to take some related training, before starting this position with your company.\"", "Bravo! Offering to strengthen your skills before you start is the best thing you could have said :)"]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Are you familiar with QuickBooks? Rate yourself as a Beginner, Intermediate or Advanced user.", "answers": ["Discuss with the hiring manager your level of knowledge in QuickBooks accounting software. If you have been recently tested on your abilities, be sure to include those results as well. Mention any courses or additional training that you have taken in QuickBooks.", "\"I would consider myself an intermediate user in QuickBooks. I was tested last year and came out in the 75th percentile. I am very open to taking additional coursework to become an Advanced user, should you require that.\"", "\"I have a small amount of hands-on training in QuickBooks so, for that reason, I would rate myself as a beginner in this program. If you desire stronger skills than I currently possess, I am happy to take some related training, before starting this position with your company.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "How do you handle a larger than average workload?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to be assured that you can handle the workload required of you in this position and that you will not become overwhelmed if/when workloads unexpectedly increase. When workloads increase, stress levels do too. How do you react?", "\"When I have a large workload on my plate, I do not stress over the tasks that are in front of me. Rather, I make a simple plan of which tasks are a high priority and which tasks are a lower priority. The higher priority tasks, I complete first. Through this system, I can focus on my tasks individually, rather than stress out by the multitude of tasks ahead of me.\"", "\"Here are some suggestions on how to handle a large workload:\n\n- List your tasks and prioritize them\n- Think of which tasks add to the company's bottom line, and start there (Closest to the money!)\n- Exhale. Relax for a minute and collect yourself\n- Organize your tasks by which ones you can complete independently and which ones you need help with\n- Take sufficient breaks, so you do not exhaust yourself \n- Communicate your struggles with your leadership or team\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Have you ever used an SAP or ERP program? If so, which one(s)?", "answers": ["Tell the hiring manager about any type of SAP/ERP program that you have been exposed to, and how comfortable you are in using these types of programs.", "\"I have used an SAP based program for the past 5 years. I am very comfortable using a variety of systems including Sage and 4HANA Finance.\"", "\"As I am new to my career as a cost accountant, I do not have notable exposure to any SAP or ERP programs. With that said, I am tech savvy and eager to learn. If you could tell me the programs and modules most used here, I am happy to get a head start with some online training.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "When you suffer a setback, how does that emotionally affect you and your work?", "answers": ["Everyone handles the stress and disappointment of setbacks differently. Discuss with the interviewer how you typically cope with delays in the workplace.", "\"Experiencing a setback is always disappointing, and can be a bit disheartening, but I understand that it happens from time to time. If I experience a major setback, I will take a few moments to debrief with my manager and discuss what I could have done differently. Then, I move on!\"", "\"Setbacks happen for a reason, and they do not affect me emotionally in the least. I am a very pragmatic thinker and stay focused despite the challenges that come my way.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Do you plan on furthering your accounting education?", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to know your plans regarding your accounting education. A willingness to learn and improve are very important assets to a hiring manager. Discuss with the interviewer your plans for further education.\n\nIf you do not plan to further your accounting education: \"Currently, I am satisfied with my level of education in accounting, however; I would be more than happy to further my education in any way that your organization may require.\"", "\"Currently, I am satisfied with my level of education in accounting, however; I would be more than happy to further my education in any way that your organization may require.\"", "\"If you plan to further your accounting education: \"I have completed my BA in Accounting and plan to obtain my CPA designation in the next couple of years. I am confident in my abilities to be successful in this role with simply my BA, but I do value education and would like to challenge myself professionally, anywhere that I can.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Why did you choose Cost Accounting rather than another field of accounting?", "answers": ["Because there are so many choices when it comes to types of accounting, the hiring manager should have a good understanding of why you specifically chose cost accounting. Talk to the hiring manager about your choice and why you are pleased with it.", "\"I chose cost accounting over other accounting fields simply due to my interest in business costs when it came to production and manufacturing. I find the business analysis components to be very intriguing.\"", "\"While completing my accounting degree, I found that I performed the best when it came to cost analysis, business analysis, and strategic planning. These components are all important when it comes to being an effective cost accountant.\"", "\"While completing my accounting degree, I found that I performed the best when it came to cost analysis, business analysis, and strategic planning. These components are all important when it comes to being an effective cost accountant.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "What do you know about our organization?", "answers": ["Researching the interviewing company is a critical step to success in your job search process. Display to the hiring manager that you have taken a strong interest in what their organization does.", "\"Prior to coming to the interview today I was able to take some time looking through your website, your social media accounts, and read some online reviews. One thing that I really appreciate about your organization is that you truly seem to care about your clients, your employees, and giving back to your community. Your brand messaging is strong and that makes me feel confident in this company's capabilities.\"", "\"I have researched your company through your social media channels, and on glassdoor.com. Your employees have great things to say, and overall it seems that you have fun while you work. I am looking forward to joining an organization, like yours, that is upbeat and thoughtful with an eye on helping the community at the same time.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Why are you looking for a new accounting position?", "answers": ["When an interviewer asks you this, make sure you always keep your answer positive. If you are leaving your position because you don\u2019t like your boss, be sure to phrase it more eloquently. Remember - it's always a safe bet to focus your answer on career growth and exciting opportunities.", "\"I recently graduated with my Bachelor's in Accounting and completed my summer internship with Company ABC. I am now looking for a full-time, permanent opportunity.\"", "\"Since the company merger last year, the workplace culture I admired so much, is no longer there. I am on the search for a supportive and positive environment where I can continue to flourish.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "What are your salary expectations?", "answers": ["Before your interview, make sure you have researched the median salary for the position (and location). You can look at salary reviews on Glassdoor.com or Payscale.com.\n\nAlways make sure you give a salary range, not just a number. Providing a range allows you to negotiate down the road if you are given an offer. However if you just tell the employer you are looking for $50K it doesn\u2019t leave room for negotiating later on. Also, make sure the lowest number of your range is something you are comfortable with!\n\nAnother great option is to tell the interviewer what you are currently earning and tell them that you are seeking a competitive offer.", "\"I am currently earning a base salary of $68K per year plus an opportunity for bonus, based on my results. I am looking for a position that will offer me competitive growth and salary.\"", "\"I am new to my career as a cost accountant, so I would appreciate a salary that aligns with my balance of experience and education. I understand that to be in the $55K range for this city and size of an organization. What are you offering for this role?\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "How do you explain complicated concepts to those who may not understand?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know that you are capable of explaining complex ideas without being condescending to your co-workers or talking over their heads. Give the interviewer an example of how you break down information to make it more easily digestible for the average person. \n\nThink of a presentation about a complex topic, as a proposal to solve a challenging problem. The solution may seem obvious to you, but everyone else in the room is scratching their heads trying to figure out what you're talking about. When you can define key terms and phrases to make them more relevant to your audience, you have skill! Not everyone can do this. \n\nPrepare an example that demonstrates your communication skills and your ability to convey complex information in easy to understand terms.", "\"I find that when there is a complicated concept to teach, visual aids are always the way to go. Did you know that 65% of people are visual learners and that presentations with visual components are 43% more persuasive? I took a course on creating effective info-graphics and will often implement those in my presentations.\"", "\"Keep it simple silly!  If you cannot explain a concept simply, then you do not understand it well enough.  I recently rolled out a complex compensation plan with many anomalies.  I took the approach to share a broad overview and provide detail for reference. I often try to make analogies or share complex information in the form of a story.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Why do you believe you are the best fit to be our cost accountant?", "answers": ["This is the time to sell your skills and abilities to the hiring manager! Do not be afraid to brag about yourself a little bit and be sure to tell the interviewer something unique about your skill set that will set you apart from the rest of the candidates.", "\"I believe that I am the best fit as your cost accountant because, in addition to meeting all of your requirements, I am also bi-lingual. This allows me to assist both your English and French speaking clients. You will find that I come with glowing references and a strong reputation in this industry.\"", "\"I am the best fit for your cost accountant role because my education is fresh and I am eager to make a strong entrance into my career. I graduated top of my class and plan to put that same level of dedication to my workload here.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Why do you feel cost accounting is important in our business?", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to have the assurance that you take pride in your work and understand why your role as a cost accountant is essential. It is critical to display to the hiring manager that you know the significance of your role as a cost accountant. Do you feel that you play an active role in the success of your organization?", "\"I feel that efficient cost accounting is critical to your business. Managing the costs of manufacturing and production is incredibly important and will help provide you with the tools needed for proper management.\"", "\"I believe that a cost accountant is more important than many people think. We have multiple specialties and can create enormous cost reductions for nearly any business, in any industry.\"", "\"I believe that a cost accountant is more important than many people think. We have multiple specialties and can create enormous cost reductions for nearly any business, in any industry.\"", "Excellent! You know exactly what your purpose is, and how you make a difference. Well said :)"]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Are you a detail oriented person? Do you like to be organized?", "answers": ["As a cost accountant, it is incredibly important that you pay close attention to detail and remain highly organized. Tell the hiring manager about your abilities in these areas and be sure to include any feedback that you have received from previous supervisor reviews.", "\"I am highly detailed and organized on the job and truly, that is the only thing you can be when in this line of work. I was able to establish very good habits from the start of my career. When you speak with my previous manager for a reference, she will attest to my strong organizational skills.\"", "\"My attention to detail is a point that I have been working on a lot this past year. I am meticulous but, in the past, have pushed my documentation back a little bit. It's something I am conscious of and continually working on.\"", "\"My attention to detail is a point that I have been working on a lot this past year. I am meticulous but, in the past, have pushed my documentation back a little bit. It's something I am conscious of and continually working on.\"", "Your response is very honest but also shows that you are self-aware and willing to admit when you fall short. Good job on taking action as well!"]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "What was the most difficult assignment you have faced? How did you complete the task?", "answers": ["As a cost accountant, you will often face difficult and challenging tasks. Share with the hiring manager how you are able to complete these tasks and face these workplace challenges with confidence.", "\"The most difficult assignment that I have faced recently was a company-wide audit ordered from our headquarters in Boston. We had to gather the required information in a very short period of time and, at the same time, continue our regular workload as per usual. Teamwork is truly what helped me to complete my tasks successfully. Also, I am not afraid of working overtime hours as needed.\"", "\"The most challenging point in my career so far was gaining a reputable and challenging internship. Luckily I was able to find an opportunity with a large firm in our city, thanks to a family connection. I realized through this challenge that it's essential to keep a positive and active network.\"", "\"The most challenging point in my career so far was gaining a reputable and challenging internship. Luckily I was able to find an opportunity with a large firm in our nearby city, thanks to a LinkedIn connection. I realized through this challenge that it's essential to keep a positive and active network.\"", "You discussed what the challenge was, how you overcame it, and what you learned. A perfectly crafted response!"]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "How long do you see yourself working for our company?", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to know that you see this role as a long-term fit. What would cause you to stay in a position long term? Talk to the hiring manager about your previous tenure and discuss what motivates you to continue working for a company.", "\"I see your organization as a long-term fit for me. As you can see, I have a strong work history that includes minimal job hopping. This position offered is one that I have been on the lookout for, for quite some time, and I see it as a long-term fit.\"", "\"I want to begin my career with a strong start, and stay as long as possible. I plan to learn as much as I can from your company, and your senior leadership. Your organization seems like a perfect fit for me, and I would like to stay as long as possible.\"", "\"I want to begin my career with a strong start, and stay as long as possible. I plan to learn as much as I can from your company, and your senior leadership. Your organization seems like a perfect fit for me, and I would like to stay as long as possible.\"", "Well said! It sounds like you have a genuine interest in the ways that you can grow with the company."]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about any disputes you have surrounding material costs for a particular project you worked on.", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to know about a time that you have had to dispute material costs. Assure the hiring manager that you are capable of managing any material cost disputes. Keep your reply concise and avoid speaking negatively about any conflicts that have come up in your current role.", "\"I worked on a project this year where the material and labor costs were both being disputed by the client. In this situation, I went through every line and was able to uncover a few areas that were not aligning. I am accustomed to working around disputes such as this and feel confident in my abilities to do so.\"", "\"I am new to my career as a cost accountant and have not had the experience of a dispute surrounding material costs. If I were to come across a situation like this, I would dig into the data until an explanation was found. If I needed a second set of eyes on the situation, I would ask for assistance.\"", "\"I am new to my career as a cost accountant and have not had the experience of a dispute surrounding material costs. If I were to come across a situation like this, I would dig into the data until an explanation was found. If I needed a second set of eyes on the situation, I would ask for assistance.\"", "You answered perfectly. Despite lacking the experience, you readily discussed what you would do in this situation. Great response!"]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "What areas could you improve to be a better accountant? What are you currently doing to improve your skills?", "answers": ["Everyone has room for improvement in some area of their career. Be honest with the hiring manager on where you feel that you could expand your knowledge. Be sure to keep your answer positive and avoid criticizing yourself to the point that you no longer look like a strong candidate.", "\"I feel that an area I could improve in would be my level of knowledge and ability in Excel. I am an intermediate user, however; there is a plethora of things that I do not know yet. I have signed up to take a weekend course starting in March.\"", "\"As a recent graduate, I am aware that there are many things for me to learn in this industry. I am willing to do everything it takes to become well skilled as a cost accountant. This includes taking additional workshops, furthering my formal education, and finding a mentor in this industry.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Bring your experience to life for me and highlight some of your biggest wins in your career as a Cost Accountant.", "answers": ["The interviewer would like to have an overall snapshot of your career successes. Discuss with the hiring manager some of your proudest career moments. Take the time to bring your resume to life for the interviewer.", "\"While attending University, I began working for XYZ firm as an apprentice. I was hired on full time after graduating with my Bachelor's Degree in Accounting. I spent three years at that particular firm learning directly under the Sr. Cost Accountant which I feel gave me a major advantage in kick-starting my career. Since then, my biggest highlights include some great promotions. My career trajectory has been strong.\"", "\"I recently graduated with my Bachelor's Degree in Accounting. Post graduation, I was a successful applicant for Nestle USA's 2017 Finance & Accounting Summer Internship Program. I had the opportunity to work on high-value projects during those 12 weeks. I gained a great deal of analytical and business knowledge. Now, I am ready to enter my career in a full-time, paid position.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "What questions do you have for me about this cost accountant role?", "answers": ["It's always a great idea to have questions ready for the interviewer. Review the company website and other online resources to ensure the questions you are asking are not mundane, or redundant. The last thing an interviewer wants to hear is a list of items you could have found the answers to from merely watching a video on their company site.", "\"A few questions come to mind. Who would you say your biggest clients are at this time and are there new markets that your firm plans to break into in the next few years?\"", "\"Here are some sample questions: \n\n- When would you like to have this position filled? \n- How long has this role been vacant? \n- Is this a replacement search or a newly created role? \n- What is your favorite part about working here? \n- What is the company's primary goal for this position in the next 12 months? \n- Is there anything from my background and experience that I can clarify for you? \n- What do you see as the most significant change in this industry over the past three years? \n- Is there any reason why you would not hire me?\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "What role do you usually take in team projects?", "answers": ["The interviewer truly wants to understand the role that you naturally take on, when put into a team-based environment. If you tend to take the lead, let the interviewer know this, but avoid sounding overbearing. If you usually like to generate new ideas and allow someone else to execute them, share your creative side but express that you prefer for others to take the lead.", "\"I am usually the 'ideas person' in team projects. In my current position, I am not the most seasoned cost accountant, but I am highly creative. This means that, in most projects, I am great at creating a strategic plan but am most comfortable passing the final client-facing tasks to our more extroverted personnel.\"", "\"When it comes to team projects I do not mind taking a backseat and, rather than being the leader, being more of an administrator. I like to organize data and analyze progress rather than lead others.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "How do you handle stress on the job?", "answers": ["Are you someone who can handle stress on the job? How do you manage the stressful times? Talk to the interviewer about your ability to control pressure in the workplace.", "\"I handle stress very well, and when you call my references, they will attest to this fact. When I am under pressure on the job, I focus on the task at hand and make sure not to get distracted. Staying on deadline is very helpful, and I will delegate when necessary to alleviate some stress.\"", "\"Stress is part of any demanding job and I embrace it to the fullest.  I take good care of myself personally and prioritize my workload to maintain a healthy balance in my stress levels.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Have you ever broken a confidentiality agreement?", "answers": ["Companies will have confidentiality agreements for a variety of reasons. These could be to protect their trade secrets or to ensure that you do not bring clients over on the occasion that you leave their company. Talk to the interviewer about your thoughts on confidentiality agreements.", "\"I never have, to my knowledge, broken a confidentiality agreement. Despite my reasons for leaving a position, I would never choose to hurt a previous employer in any way.\"", "\"No.  I have only once had a confidentiality agreement and had no problem adhering to it.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "Are you familiar with Microsoft Excel? Rate yourself as a Beginner, Intermediate or Advanced user.", "answers": ["Discuss with the hiring manager your level of knowledge in Microsoft Excel. If you have been recently tested on your abilities, be sure to include those results as well. Mention any courses or additional training that you have taken in Excel.", "\"I would consider myself an Advanced level user in Excel, and the entire Microsoft Office Suite. I have used the program for six years and have trained others on the proper use of the program as well.\"", "\"I would consider myself a Beginner level user in Excel. I am very open to taking additional coursework to become a stronger user, should you require that.\""]}, {"topic": "Cost+Accountant", "question": "How will you earn the trust of your coworkers?", "answers": ["Workplace relationships are essential to nurture. Talk to the interviewer about how you plan to earn the trust of your new co-workers, should you be offered the position.", "\"I feel that the best way to earn the trust of my co-workers is to be helpful, always do what I promise, and be honest with them at all times. Strong relationships have to be built on these principles.\"", "\"I will win my new coworkers over by going above and beyond the expectations given to me. I want to be a helpful team member that they can always come to.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What does being a team player mean to you as it relates to accounting and finance?", "answers": ["Most of an accounting professional's work is interrelated to other employees and departments.  Therefore, being a team player is essential.  Speak to some of the ways you can demonstrate that you are a team player, including working additional hours as needed and being an effective communicator..", "\" I understand how important it is to be a team player when working in accounting and finance.  All finance functions are connected to each other.  In order for the monthly close to be completed efficiently each month, each professional and department needs to meet  their deadlines.  To this end, I would work the hours required to complete my work so it does not delay other processes.  Additionally, I would be in constant communication with others that rely on my deliverables so that they are in the loop.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What is deferred revenue?", "answers": ["This question tests your ability to explain a basic concept of accounting.  Under the accrual method of accounting, deferred revenue arises when cash is received before revenue is earned.  This most commonly occurs when a customer prepays for a good or service.", "\"Deferred revenue is a liability that arises when cash is received before revenue is earned.  This typically occurs when a customer pays before a service is performed or goods are delivered.  That liability is then reversed in the period the revenue is earned.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What are some steps you would take to ensure you are meeting your manager\u2019s expectations?", "answers": ["There are several actions that can be taken to ensure you are doing your job effectively.  First and foremost, completing the tasks assigned to you completely and efficiently is a great start.  During one on one meetings with your manager, you can ask for feedback on your job performance as well as actions you can take going forward.", "\"In order to perform my job duties to my manager's satisfaction, I would first complete the responsibilities I am given promptly and effectively.  I would then check in with my manager on a regular basis to review work I have completed and actions I can take in the near future to continue performing effectively.  My goal is to exceed my manager's expectations, and I think these actions would help achieve that goal.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "How do you stay up to date on the latest accounting trends?", "answers": ["This question is to see if you take the initiative to stay current on the latest accounting developments.  By doing so, you demonstrate that you are committed to growing in the accounting profession.", "\"I stay up to date in various ways.  First, I subscribe to e-newsletters from the Financial Accounting Standards Board for updates to generally accepted accounting principles.  Additionally, as an alumnus of my university, I have access to a large continuing education library.  I try to select courses that align nicely with the roles and responsibilities of an entry level accountant.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What is a bank reconciliation?", "answers": ["A bank reconciliation is a process that matches the cash balances in an organization's general ledger to the balances on the corresponding bank statements.  Bank reconciliations are commonly the responsibility of entry level staff, and therefore it's important for the candidate to be able to describe what a bank reconciliation is and what it entails.", "\"A bank reconciliation is an important part of the monthly accounting process.  It involves verifying that the cash balances on the books tie to the balances per the bank statements.  As a new accountant, I understand that bank reconciliations may fall under my responsibilities. It is a skill I look forward to learning and mastering.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Are you willing to work additional hours as needed?", "answers": ["The life of an accountant is tied to the month-end close calendar, which could result in a schedule that is 'lumpy' and not a typical 9-5.  The candidate should expect there to be some additional time worked during busier times and should highlight that they are flexible.", "\"Yes, I am willing to work extra hours as needed.  I understand that the work required ramps up during month-end close, tax filings and other busier times.  I also understand that if I want to advance in my career, I will need to go the extra mile.   I am happy to be flexible and work as needed to make sure the job gets done.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Why do you want to work for XYZ Corporation?", "answers": ["The question is a chance to show that you have done your research on the company.  In your answer, be sure to include some facts that required you to research the company beyond what is available on their website (for example, recent financial performance).", "\" I would be excited and proud to work for XYZ Corporation because I believe that they are on the cutting edge of innovation in the HR Solutions space.  For example, the new software platform launched last month that allows remote workers to change all of their HR records with a click of a mouse is a game changer.  Additionally, the company is growing and healthy financially, with EBITDA growing by an average of 11% over the last five years.  I believe working at XYZ Corporation would be a great way to begin my career.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What are the steps in a monthly accounting close?", "answers": ["Even as a new staff member, you will likely be very involved in the accounting close process.  This question is used to assess whether your understanding of the accounting close process aligns with the organization's.  Don't go into too much detail - rather, just hit the key steps and then ask how it compares or differs from the organization's process.", "\"First and foremost, there needs to be a closing calendar so that deadlines are set for all departments.  Next, all data must be gathered.  This includes departments such as payroll and accounts payable preparing reports needed for journal entries.  Next, all journal entries are booked.  After journal entries are booked and reviewed, financial statements are prepared and balance sheet reconciliations are completed.  Finally, the results are reviewed with leadership.  Is there anything I described that differs from the process here at XYZ Corporation?\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Are you proficient in Excel?", "answers": ["Like most college graduates from this generation, it is expected that the candidate has extensive experience using Excel.  Given that, beyond saying that you are proficient in Excel, speak to some of the advanced skills you have that would be useful in the accounting field.  These include SUMIF formulas, Lookup formulas, and pivot tables.", "\"Yes, I am very proficient in Excel.  In college, I took electives on advanced Excel skills.  I am very comfortable sorting and filtering data and creating pivot tables.  Additionally, I have used Lookup and Sumif formulas to build reports.  I look forward to expanding my skills even further as I begin my career.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Give examples of common financial ratios.  What do they tell about a company\u2019s finances?", "answers": ["Financial ratios are simple calculations that give a quick snapshot of a company's financial health.  Several common ratios are:  current/quick ratio, working capital ratio, days sales outstanding, days payable outstanding, debt to equity ratio and return on equity.", "\"There are many financial ratios that can help give a glimpse into a company's financial position.  One common one is the working capital ratio, which is calculated by taking current assets divided by current liabilities.  The ratio measures an entity's ability to pay off its short term liabilities with liquid and semi-liquid assets.  Another ratio is days sales outstanding, which measures how many days of sales are sitting in accounts receivable.  The higher the number of days, the worse off the company may be because they may not be collecting cash from customers in a timely fashion.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Why do companies have internal auditors?", "answers": ["Internal auditors are an important department in any large finance function.  They are responsible for evaluating the company's internal controls and accounting processes.  They also identify problems or opportunities in the company's financial policies and procedures", "\"There are several reasons why companies have internal audit functions.  First, they help give management assurance that the financial statements are correct and financial processes are running smoothly.  They accomplish this by documenting all procedures and internal controls, and identifying weaknesses and misstatements before they are caught by an external audit.  Additionally, external auditors can oftentimes rely on work completed by internal auditors, which saves time and money during the audit..\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What are the three financial statements and what do they indicate about a company\u2019s finances?", "answers": ["The three main financial statements are the income statement, balance sheet and statement of cash flows.  A new accountant should know the statements in detail as they will be expected to have learned them in their college coursework.", "\"The income statement shows profitability over a period of time by showing revenue less expenses.  The balance sheet summarizes a company's assets, liabilities, and equity at a point in time.  And a cash flow statement shows the net cash inflows and outflows over a period of time.  Each statement is essential in order to gain insights into the financial health of an organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Do you have any experience using accounting software?", "answers": ["As an entry level accountant, it won't be expected that you have extensive experience using full scale accounting software packages.  Therefore, speak to what you have used. Many job descriptions specifically state which accounting software the company uses.  If any event, make sure to highlight that you are quick to learn new software systems.", "\"In my college program, we were able to demo SAP accounting software.  In that software, I was able to book journal entries, generate reports and run queries.  Since I have an underlying understanding of accounting, I believe I will be able to learn new software packages fairly quickly.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What qualities or skills do you believe make a good accountant?", "answers": ["This question is a good opportunity to show you have an understanding of what qualities make a good accountant.  Some key areas to hit are ethics (honesty/integrity), ability to interact with colleagues and clients (communication skills, people person), ability to limit mistakes (focused/attention to detail) and ability to get to the correct answer (skeptical/inquisitive/problem solver).", "\"First and foremost, I believe an accountant should be honest and have great integrity.  Without this, it will be impossible for the person to perform the role effectively.  Next, the individual should have the education and technical skills to perform the job.  They should have exceptional people skills as they will be required to communicate effectively with colleagues, clients and other parties.  Finally, they should have an inquisitive mind and a keen attention to detail.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What steps do you take to ensure there aren\u2019t any mistakes in your work?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to evaluate your ability to check your own work and, as a result, save your manager precious time by catching mistakes before they reach his or her desk.  Give specific examples of procedures you have implemented in previous roles to catch mistakes.", "\"Being able to self-review my work and catch mistakes is something I take very seriously.  An accountant spends a lot of time in the details, so it is sometimes difficult to catch errors.  Given this, I would implement checklists that require me to tie out balances, subtotal transactions and complete other checks before I move forward in the close process.  In a way, I would audit my work to catch any mistakes or errors.  This not only saves me time in the long run, but also saves my manager time as there is less back and forth resolving issues.  I understand that the work I produce is not only a reflection of me, but of my department as well.  Given that, catching mistakes would be a priority for me.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Where do you see yourself in five years?", "answers": ["In some ways, this can be a trap question.  You want to sound ambitious but also humble.  In order to accomplish this, talk about how you are excited in the immediate term by the role you are interviewing for.  Then talk about how you like to learn and continue to grow in the organization.", "\"I am very excited about the staff accountant role because I think it will be a great opportunity to learn about the accounting profession from the ground floor.  Over the next few years, I look forward to expanding my accounting skills and learning more about the company.  As long as I can continue to grow I believe that I will be fulfilled.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Describe an accounting project that you successfully completed in school?", "answers": ["As a recent graduate, you won't have too many on-the-job experiences to recount to the interviewer.  Therefore, it is wise to have an example in mind from your college coursework.  If the example is related to accounting, that is all the better.", "\"In a financial accounting course in college, we were tasked with completing a mock accounting close and developing an executive summary that would be shared with leaders of the company.  As a team of three, we closed the books for the month.  In a couple instances, we completed research to find out the proper accounting treatment of transactions.  We then built an attractive deck that shared the results.   I am proud of this particular project because we worked together as a team and received a special shout out from the professor.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What is the difference between auditing and accounting?", "answers": ["An audit is an independent examination of financial statements of an entity with the purpose of expressing an opinion on those statements.  Accounting is the measurement, processing and reporting of financial information about a business.  Accounting is typically done in-house, while an audit must be performed by an independent firm.", "\"Accounting involves the recording and reporting of financial information for an entity and is typically done by internal employees of the company.  Auditing is an independent examination of the financial information prepared by the company in order to express an opinion on the financial statements.  The personnel conducting the audit are from an independent firm.  While many large organizations have an internal audit function, it is the external auditors that issue the opinion.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What is an accrued expense?", "answers": ["This question tests your ability to explain a basic concept of accounting.  Under the accrual method of accounting, an accrued expense arises when an expense is incurred in the current period but will be paid in a future period.", "\"Accrued expenses are very common in accounting, and arise when an expense is incurred in the current reporting period but won't be paid until a future period.  A common example is accrued bonus, where expense is recognized throughout the year even though the bonus is typically paid once per year.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Why do you want to be an accountant?", "answers": ["This question is a way for the interviewer to find out a little bit about your background and interests.  Be honest and direct - don't give a phony answer that the interviewer will see through.", "\"Since I was young, I have always liked math and have been good with numbers.  I took an accounting class in high school and really enjoyed it - the concepts made sense to me.  I am also interested in a career with good growth opportunities, and I know accounting is a field that I can start at entry level and advance with experience.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Do you have any experience working with data?", "answers": ["With advances in computing technology, accountants can now take large amounts of data and analyze it.  Speak to a specific example where you utilized big data to solve a problem or complete a task.", "\"At my internship last summer, I helped the staff accountant responsible for inventory estimate obsolescence for several months.  To do this, we exported over 10,000 lines of data each month, sorted and created pivot tables so that we could break down sales by type.  This allowed us to book a more precise estimate than if we didn't have access to the data.  I was also exposed to data visualization software in college, and I would love to continue to hone my skills in that space.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "Do you plan on obtaining your CPA license?", "answers": ["While not always required, many professionals in the accounting field become Certified Public Accountants (CPAs).  For a new graduate, planning to become a CPA shows commitment to the accounting profession.  Be open with your intentions as it relates to the CPA license.", "\"As a new professional in the field of accounting, one of my primary goals in the first few years of my career is to obtain my CPA license.  I have completed the necessary education hours, and have already signed up for a study course for the Regulation section of the exam.  I am looking forward to obtaining my license and applying the knowledge gained during the exam process to my career.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "How would you show professionalism in the workplace?", "answers": ["It is not always clear to new graduates how to act professionally in an office setting.  Speak to your ability to act professionally in how you dress, how you act, and the work you produce.", "\"As a new employee, there are many ways that I can show professionalism at work.  First, I can be professional in my appearance by adhering to the company's dress code.  I can also display professionalism in my behavior by arriving promptly everyday, not listening to loud music and not taking personal calls.  Lastly, I can show professionalism in my work by reviewing my work before sharing with others and using the proper etiquette in emails, meetings and phone calls. \""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "How would you handle working in a remote or hybrid environment?", "answers": ["This is a question to gauge if you are disciplined enough to work from home as there are many distractions, especially for young professionals.  Be sure to touch on how you would stay focused and communicate with team members.  Even after things return to normal, remote work may continue to be more common across many industries including accounting.", "\"I have experience working remotely.  At my internship, we were able to work from home on Fridays since it was summer.  I enjoyed working from home, and was able to stay on task and communicate effectively with my team members.  There were some ground rules I implemented, such as maintaining regular hours, keeping my morning routine as if I was going to the office, and scheduling breaks to take care of non-work related tasks. I also had a standing meeting with my manager and team members every morning to discuss priorities for the day.\""]}, {"topic": "Entry+Level+Accountant", "question": "What is an allowance for doubtful accounts and how is it reflected on the balance sheet?", "answers": ["This is a technical question that tests your understanding of accounting reserves, such as the Allowance for Doubtful Accounts.  Accrual accounting methodology requires that certain reserves be made during a month, even if the cash impact occurs in a future month.  For example, bad debt expense is recognized in the month of sale, even though it may be months until customer accounts are written off.  The Allowance for Doubtful Accounts is a 'contra asset' that is netted against Accounts Receivable on the balance sheet.", "\"The Allowance for Doubtful Accounts is a reserve account related to bad debt on customer sales.  The bad debt is estimated each month in accordance with accrual accounting, and is usually a small percentage of total sales. The bad debt reserve sits in the Allowance for Doubtful Accounts account.   It is considered a 'contra account' that nets against Accounts Receivable on the balance sheet.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Please rank these asset classes in order from shortest useful life to longest:  Leasehold improvements, computer, and furniture.", "answers": ["All fixed assets are capitalized and then depreciated over their useful lives (the amount of time an asset can be in service before it is considered obsolete).  This question tests whether you have a basic understanding of the useful lives of some common asset classes.", "\"Computers usually have the shortest useful lives at three to five years.  After that, technology begins to become obsolete and should be replaced.  Furniture commonly has a useful life of five to ten years.  Finally, leasehold improvements have the longest useful lives as they are permanent changes to a physical space, such as walls.  Typically, the useful life of a leasehold improvement is anywhere from ten years to forty years.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What are some methods you use to self-review your work?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to evaluate your ability to check your own work and, as a result, save your manager precious time by catching mistakes before they reach his or her desk.  Give specific examples of procedures you have implemented in previous roles to catch mistakes.", "\"Being able to self-review my work and catch mistakes is something I take very seriously.  An accountant spends a lot of time in the details, so it is sometimes difficult to catch errors.  Given this, I implement checklists that require me to tie out balances, subtotal transactions and double check certain items before I move forward in the close process.  In a way, I am auditing my work to catch any mistakes or errors.  This not only saves me time in the long run, but also saves my manager time, as there is less back and forth resolving issues.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "How do you mitigate and manage stress?", "answers": ["The life of an accountant can be stressful, especially during busier times like monthly close and the annual audit.  The interviewer wants to gain insight into how you react to stressful situations.", "\"Due to tight deadlines and the demands of the accountant role, stress is inevitable.  However, there are steps I take to help mitigate stress.  First, I try to be as organized as possible.  I am constantly prioritizing my workload to make sure time-sensitive tasks are handled before they are due.  Next, I try to leave work at work.  When not at work, I enjoy hiking, cooking, and traveling.  Being able to enjoy these activities makes me feel calmer and rejuvenated while at work.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Are you a detail-oriented person?", "answers": ["The fixed asset accountant position requires great attention to detail, as the role is in charge of producing and maintaining meticulous financial records.  It is expected that the accountant can catch mistakes before reporting is provided to leaders of the organization.", "\"Yes, I am extremely detail oriented.  Part of what makes me a great accountant is my organization skills and ability to self-review my work.  I know that providing financial information containing errors creates doubt among leadership that the financial records are accurate.  Therefore, I implement systems that allow me to check the details, such as monthly checklists and reviews.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What do you do when you don\u2019t know the answer to something?", "answers": ["There is no shame in being stumped - it happens to everyone at all levels of an organization.  This question is an opportunity to highlight your ability to be independent and resourceful.", "\"I have no problem seeking solutions to questions I encounter.  If I am unsure about the accounting treatment for a certain transaction, I can reach out to our external auditors for advice on the appropriate accounting treatment.  If it's something technical, such as using a new Excel formula, I am good at researching online and following examples.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Why did you want to become an accountant?", "answers": ["This question is a way for the interviewer to find out a little bit about your interests and background.  Be honest and direct; don't give a phony answer that the interviewer will see through.", "\"Since I was young, I have always liked math and have been good with numbers.  I took an accounting class in high school and really enjoyed it; the concepts came naturally to me.  I also aspire to be a key contributor to an organization, and I know that the fixed asset accountant role is visible to leadership.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "How do you manage your manager?  In other words, what steps do you take to make sure you get what you need from your boss and make both your lives easier?", "answers": ["Also known as 'managing up', 'managing your manager' is a soft skill that can be developed over time.  It essentially means doing whatever is necessary to make your manager's job easier.  Some clear-cut benefits of managing up include increased productivity and better working relationships between boss and employee.", "\"I am a firm believer in the benefits of managing my manager.  At the end of the day, I want to make the audit engagements we work on together run as smoothly as possible.  One area I really focus on is communicating and prioritizing workload on a regular basis.  This ensures that I'm always working on the highest-priority items.   Another thing that is crucial is understanding my manager's style.  For example, do they prefer regular check-ins by email throughout the day, scheduled catch-up meetings, etc.  Then, I tailor my communication to their style.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "How would you handle working in an increasingly remote work environment?", "answers": ["This is a question to gauge if you are disciplined enough to work from home.  Be sure to touch on how you would stay focused and communicate with team members.  Even after things return to normal, remote work may continue to be more common across many industries, including accounting.", "\"I have experience working remotely.  At my internship, we were able to work from home on Fridays in the summer.  I enjoyed working from home and was able to stay on task and communicate effectively with my team members.  There were some ground rules I implemented, such as maintaining regular hours, keeping my morning routine as if I was going to the office, and scheduling breaks to take care of non-work related tasks. I also had a standing meeting with my manager and team members every morning to discuss priorities for the day.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What are the differences between accrual accounting and cash accounting?", "answers": ["Accrual basis accounting and cash basis accounting are the two most commonly used accounting methodologies.  Any accountant should understand the differences between the two methodologies and understand that most companies use accrual accounting, as it presents a clearer picture of financial health.", "\"The main difference between accrual accounting and cash accounting is when revenue and expenses are recognized.  Under cash basis accounting, revenue and expenses are recognized when cash is received and paid.  Under accrual accounting, revenue is recognized in the period it is earned, and expenses are recognized in the period they are incurred.  While cash basis accounting is easier to implement, accrual accounting is used by most businesses and presents a clearer picture of a company's overall financial health.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What have you done recently to become a better accountant?", "answers": ["This question allows the interviewer to gauge how motivated you are to learn new skills.  They will most likely be looking for a candidate that takes initiative to learn, so be sure to call out recent examples of when you have acquired new skills.", "\"I am always looking for ways to learn more about my profession and acquire new skills.  As an example, I recently took a two week online course called Advanced Bookkeeping, where I learned new skills related to fixed asset accounting.  I believe I could use the knowledge obtained from this course in the fixed asset accountant role.  Once in the role, I would also seek out continuing education that allows me to apply skills acquired to help the organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What is Section 179 Expense?", "answers": ["Section 179 Expense is a common IRS-approved method to recognize full depreciation of fixed assets in the year of purchase.  There is a limit on the amount of equipment that qualifies for Section 179 in a given year (up to $1,050,000 in 2021).  It is advisable to mention how Section 179 expense differs from straight-line depreciation.", "\"Section 179 Expense was instituted by the United States government to encourage companies to buy equipment and invigorate the economy.  Section 179 allows a company to deduct the full purchase price of equipment in the year of purchase, as opposed to depreciating over the useful life of the asset, as required by financial accounting standards.  Section 179 is a nice option for companies that invest in themselves to reduce taxable income.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What are the three main financial statements and what do they indicate about an organization\u2019s financial position?", "answers": ["The three main financial statements are the income statement, balance sheet, and statement of cash flows.  An accountant should know these statements in detail, as they will likely be preparing all three each month.", "\"The income statement shows profitability over a period of time by showing revenue less expenses.  The balance sheet summarizes a company's assets, liabilities, and equity at a point in time.  A cash flow statement shows the net cash inflows and outflows over a period of time.  Each statement is essential in order to gain insights into the financial health of an organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Do you have experience explaining complex accounting concepts to non-financial personnel?", "answers": ["Accountants will frequently interact with other departments within the company.  Many times, the employees in these departments do not have extensive knowledge of accounting concepts and terminology.  This question is an opportunity to highlight your communication skills.", "\"Yes, in my previous role I was able to interact with non-finance personnel when I would meet with the marketing team to review their results each month.  They didn't have a strong understanding of accounting principles, so I tried to 'speak their language' as much as possible when discussing their department's results vs budget.  I believe I have the ability to communicate effectively with all personnel in an organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Why is depreciation expense considered a non-cash expense?", "answers": ["This is a technical question that tests whether you are able to explain why depreciation expense is considered non-cash.  The reason is that when a fixed asset is purchased, the cash outflow occurs at that time.  However, depreciation expense is recognized over the useful life of the asset.", "\"Depreciation expense is the most common non-cash expense.  The reason it is considered non-cash is because the cash outflow occurs up front when the asset is purchased.  However, depreciation expense is recognized over the useful life of the asset to comply with accrual accounting principles.  On the Statement of Cash Flows, depreciation expense is an add-back to net income to recognize the fact that it is non-cash.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Do you have experience working with external auditors?", "answers": ["A key responsibility of an accountant is to interact with and assist the external auditors.  You may be asked to assist with walkthroughs, which are interviews where the auditor documents the processes you follow each month, as part of their assessment of internal controls.  You may also be asked to either provide existing schedules (bank reconciliations, debt schedules, etc) or prepare schedules for the audit.", "\"Yes, in my last role I interacted with our external auditors frequently and in a variety of ways.  First, as part of their assessment of internal controls, I would sit down with them to complete walkthroughs of the processes I follow each month.  Additionally, I would prepare schedules that they would test as part of their audit.  Examples of these schedules include balance sheet reconciliations and amortization schedules for our intangible assets.  Finally, I would prepare draft footnote schedules for the audited financial statements.  I believe it's very important to have a good working relationship with the organization's auditors.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What are the steps involved in the accounting close process?", "answers": ["This question is used to assess whether your understanding of the accounting close process aligns with the organization's.  Don't go into too much detail. Rather, just hit the key steps and then ask how it compares or differs from the organization's process.", "\"First and foremost, there needs to be a closing calendar so that deadlines are set for all departments.  Next, all data must be gathered.  This includes departments such as payroll and accounts payable preparing reports needed for journal entries.  Next, all journal entries are booked.  After journal entries are booked and reviewed, financial statements are prepared and balance sheet reconciliations are completed.  Finally, the results are reviewed with leadership.  Is there anything I described that differs from the process here at XYZ Corporation?\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "How are fixed asset purchases accounted for to comply with the matching principle (recognizing expense in the period incurred)?", "answers": ["This is a question that gauges whether you understand why depreciation expense is recorded for fixed assets.  Depreciation expense is recognized evenly over the useful life of a fixed asset so that a proportionate expense is recorded in each period the asset is in use.", "\"Fixed assets are unique in that they are purchased at a given time, but used for years and sometimes decades after purchase.  To align with accrual accounting principles, an accountant must estimate the useful life of a fixed asset in months.  Then, each month a proportionate depreciation expense is recognized for each period an asset is in use.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What is an impairment of a fixed asset and what is the accounting treatment?", "answers": ["An asset impairment occurs when there is a drop in the fair value of an asset below its recorded cost.  The accounting treatment is to write off the difference between the fair value and the recorded cost of the asset.  Impairment occurs when the decline in value is not recoverable.", "\"Impairment of fixed assets occurs when the fair value of owned fixed assets drop below the carrying amount of the asset on the balance sheet.  When this happens, a write-off of the difference is recorded.  It is important to periodically assess whether material fixed assets are impaired to the point where the value cannot be recovered.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What accounting software are you familiar with?", "answers": ["Speak specifically to the accounting systems you have used and some of the functions you performed.  Many job descriptions specifically state which accounting software the company uses.  In any event, make sure to highlight that you are quick to learn new software systems.", "\"In my last role, I used SAP to book journal entries and run queries.  As an independent contractor, I also used Quickbooks to complete monthly bookkeeping for various clients.  I used that software to book journal entries, complete bank reconciliations, run monthly reports, and invoice customers.  Since I have an underlying understanding of accounting, I am easily able to learn new software packages.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What have you done at your previous job to reduce costs or save time?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know if you have the ability to improve processes.  Speak to a specific action you took that resulted in reduced costs, saved time, or better insights gained.", "\"My last role was bookkeeper for a small, established company.  However, my predecessor did not have established procedures in place and it sounded like he made constant mistakes.  One of the first things I did when I started was make a monthly checklist that detailed all the steps I took during the monthly close.  Included in these steps were 'checks' I performed to self review my work.  The checklist served as a cover sheet that I would hand off to my manager so that she would know exactly what steps I completed.  This led to increased efficiency, as we estimated it saved 4-6 hours a month in error corrections.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Are you willing to work extra hours, if needed, during busier times?", "answers": ["The life of an accountant is tied to the month-end close calendar, which could result in a schedule that is 'lumpy' and not a typical 9-5.  You should expect there to be some additional time worked during busier times and should highlight that you are flexible.", "\"Yes, I am willing to work extra hours, as needed.  I understand that the work required ramps up during month-end close, tax filings, and other busier times.  I am happy to be flexible and work as needed to make sure the job gets done.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Are you open to travel with this role?", "answers": ["The fixed asset accountant position may require some travel, as the role will likely be involved in procedures that may require visits to facilities where fixed assets are located.  Most job descriptions mention the travel required, so be sure to align your response with that requirement.", "\"As a fixed asset accountant, I understand I will be involved in asset verification procedures at various warehouses throughout the East Coast.  The job description for this position mentioned 25% travel, and I am very comfortable with that.  I think the travel will be a great way to get out of the office and understand the operations of the organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "Are you proficient in Excel?", "answers": ["Excel proficiency is a must for not only a fixed asset accountant, but any role in accounting.  At a minimum, a bookkeeper should be able to sort through large amounts of data, and analyze that data using pivot tables.", "\"Yes, I am proficient in Excel.  I have used Excel extensively throughout my time in school, as well as in my previous role.  For example, I used data sorting and filtering, as well as pivot tables, to organize large amounts of data.  Additionally, I have experience using V-Lookups and H-Lookups to pull together analysis for our external auditors.  I have even dipped my toes into data visualization software such as Tableau, but that is a skill I would like to continue to nurture.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What is the fixed asset turnover ratio and how is it calculated?", "answers": ["The fixed asset turnover ratio (FAT) measures a company's ability to generate sales from its fixed-asset investments by comparing net sales to fixed assets.  A higher ratio indicates that a company is effectively using its fixed assets to generate sales.", "\"The fixed asset turnover ratio is a simple calculation that helps measure a company's effectiveness with using its fixed asset investments to help generate sales.  It is calculated by taking Net Sales divided by average fixed assets balance over a certain period. A higher ratio indicates that a company is effectively using its fixed assets.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What is your comfort level interacting and communicating with senior leadership?", "answers": ["A fixed asset accountant role is staff level but is unique in that the role interacts regularly with senior leadership. Highlight that you not only have experience presenting in front of leadership, but also that you are comfortable doing it.  Be specific with what you presented.  For example, monthly results, pitches for new initiatives, etc.", "\"I have ample experience getting in front of leadership and presenting.  In my previous role, I would present to the CEO, CFO, and other senior leaders during our monthly Finance Review meetings.  I always felt the need to prepare in advance for any questions that might arise and would promptly follow-up on anything that developed during those meetings.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What are some examples of internal controls that impact fixed assets?", "answers": ["Internal controls are rules or procedures that are put in place to protect financial and accounting information and to prevent fraud.  Some are required by laws and regulations, while others are implemented to protect the company.  Some internal controls that relate specifically to fixed assets include those that mitigate physical risks (verify the existence, condition and custody of fixed assets) and financial risks (keeping records of all asset purchases).", "\"Internal controls are important for fixed assets.  Some internal controls focus on mitigating physical risks, such as periodically verifying the existence and condition of fixed assets.  Another set of internal controls focus on mitigating financial risks, such as keeping meticulous records of all fixed asset purchases.  Having accurate fixed assets helps ensure a more accurate balance sheet, which is vital for any company.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What types of costs should be capitalized when an asset is purchased or acquired?", "answers": ["Many people think the purchase price of a fixed asset is the only cost that should be capitalized when purchasing an asset. However, there are other costs associated with the purchase that should also be capitalized.  These costs include sales tax and delivery, as well as installation and labor costs, if it is a larger asset.", "\"While the purchase price of a fixed asset is typically the main cost that should be capitalized when purchasing an asset, there are other costs associated with the asset acquisition that should also be included in the capitalized cost.  For example, delivery charges, sales tax, installation and labor should be added on to the asset price and depreciated over the useful life of the asset.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "After acquisition of a fixed asset, are there any instances when additional costs related to the fixed asset can be capitalized?", "answers": ["This question tests your knowledge of the difference between regular repairs and maintenance and improvements to fixed assets that would warrant capitalization.  If a cost is incurred to return a fixed asset to its original working condition, it should be expensed as repairs and maintenance.  For example, if a machine breaks down, the repair cost should be expensed.  If the costs incurred improve the asset, the cost should be capitalized.", "\"When assessing whether a subsequent cost related to a fixed asset should be capitalized, I follow the Bigger, Better, Longer rule.  If the cost makes the asset bigger, such as an addition to a building, it should be capitalized.  If the cost makes the fixed asset better, such as an enhancement to equipment that makes it run more efficiently, it should be capitalized.  If the cost extends the useful life of the asset, it should be capitalized.  Any other cost should be treated as repairs and maintenance, and should be expensed in the period incurred.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What are some examples of startup costs that should be capitalized when a new business is launching?", "answers": ["When a new business is launching, there are a couple startup costs that can be capitalized and expensed over time vs all at once, when incurred like normal expenses.  The capitalized startup costs are typically amortized over fifteen years.  Some examples of costs that can be capitalized include acquisitions of trademarks and patents.", "\"When a business is getting ready to launch, most of the costs incurred during the startup phase should be expensed, including legal fees, branding and licenses.  However, some are permitted to be capitalized such as trademarks, copyrights and patents.  These items are typically capitalized and then amortized straight-line over fifteen years.\""]}, {"topic": "Fixed+Asset+Accountant", "question": "What is the Sum-of-the-Years Digits Method of depreciation and what is the reasoning for using the method, as opposed to standard depreciation?", "answers": ["The Sum-of-the-Years Digits (SYD) is an accelerated method for calculating depreciation.  In most cases, assets are depreciated evenly over the useful life of the asset.  However, SYD allocates the highest depreciation expense in the first year and the lowest in the last year.  The reasoning is that an asset is most useful in the first years of its useful life.  Picture the purchase of a new car, where the value drops quickest in the first year or two of ownership.", "\"The Sum-of-the-Years Digits Method is an accelerated method of recognizing depreciation expense on an asset.  Under this method, the highest depreciation expense is recognized in the first year, and the lowest in the last year.   The reasoning for using the Sum-of-Years method is that the fixed asset is most useful (and therefore most valuable) in the early years of its useful life.  The value then diminishes over time.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are some methods you use to self-review your work?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to evaluate your ability to check your own work and, as a result, save your manager precious time by catching mistakes before they reach his or her desk.  Give specific examples of procedures you have implemented in previous roles to catch mistakes.", "\"Being able to self-review my work and catch mistakes is something I take very seriously.  An accountant spends a lot of time in the details, so it is sometimes difficult to catch errors.  Given this, I implement checklists that require me to tie out balances, subtotal transactions, and double check other to-dos before I move forward in the close process.  In a way, I am auditing my work to catch any mistakes or errors.  This not only saves me time in the long run, but it also saves my manager time, as there is less back and forth resolving issues.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "How do you mitigate and manage stress?", "answers": ["The life of an accountant can be stressful, especially during busier times like monthly close and the annual audit.  The interviewer wants to gain insight into how you react to stressful situations.", "\"Due to tight deadlines and the demands of the inventory accountant role, stress is inevitable.  However, there are steps I take to help mitigate stress.  First, I try to be as organized as possible.  I am constantly prioritizing my workload to make sure time-sensitive tasks are handled before they are due.  Next, I try to leave work at work.  When not at work, I enjoy hiking, cooking, and traveling.  Being able to enjoy these activities makes me feel calmer and rejuvenated while at work.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Are you a detail-oriented person?", "answers": ["The inventory accountant position requires great attention to detail, as the role is in charge of producing and maintaining meticulous financial records.  It is expected that the bookkeeper can catch mistakes before reporting is provided to leaders of the organization.", "\"Yes, I am extremely detail oriented.  Part of what makes me a great accountant is my organization skills and ability to self-review my work.  I know that providing financial information containing errors creates doubt among leadership that the financial records are accurate.  Therefore, I implement systems that allow me to check the details, such as monthly checklists and reviews.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What do you do when you don\u2019t know the answer to something?", "answers": ["There is no shame in being stumped - it happens to everyone at all levels of an organization.  This question is an opportunity to highlight your ability to be independent and resourceful.", "\"I have no problem seeking solutions to questions I encounter.  If I am unsure about the accounting treatment for a certain transaction, I can reach out to our external auditors for advice on the appropriate accounting treatment.  If it's something technical, such as using a new Excel formula, I am good at researching online and following examples.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Why did you want to become an accountant?", "answers": ["This question is a way for the interviewer to find out a little bit about your interests and background.  Be honest and direct - don't give a phony answer that the interviewer will see through.", "\"Since I was young, I have always liked math and have been good with numbers.  I took an accounting class in high school and really enjoyed it - the concepts came naturally to me.  I also aspire to be a key contributor to an organization, and I know that the inventory accountant role is visible to leadership.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "How do you manage your manager?  In other words, what steps do you take to make sure you get what you need from your boss and make both your lives easier?", "answers": ["Also known as 'managing up', 'managing your manager' is a soft skill that can be developed over time.  It essentially means doing whatever is necessary to make your manager's job easier.  Some clear-cut benefits of managing up include increased productivity and better working relationships between boss and employee.", "\"I am a firm believer in the benefits of managing my manager.  At the end of the day, I want to make the audit engagements we work on together run as smoothly as possible.  One area where I really focus on is communicating and prioritizing workload on a regular basis.  This ensures that I'm always working on the highest-priority items.   Another thing that is crucial is understanding my manager's style.  For example, do they prefer regular check-ins by email throughout the day or scheduled catch-up meetings, etc.  I try to tailor my communication to their style.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "How would you handle working in an increasingly remote work environment?", "answers": ["This is a question to gauge if you are disciplined enough to work from home.  Be sure to touch on how you would stay focused and communicate with team members.  Even after things return to normal, remote work may continue to be more common across many industries, including accounting.", "\"I have experience working remotely.  At my internship, we were able to work from home on Fridays in the summer.  I enjoyed working from home and was able to stay on task and communicate effectively with my team members.  There were some ground rules I implemented, such as maintaining regular hours, keeping my morning routine as if I was going to the office, and scheduling breaks to take care of non-work related tasks. I also had a standing meeting with my manager and team members every morning to discuss priorities for the day.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are the differences between accrual accounting and cash accounting?", "answers": ["Accrual basis accounting and cash basis accounting are the two most commonly used accounting methodologies.  Any accountant should understand the differences between the two methodologies and understand that most companies use accrual accounting, as it presents a clearer picture of financial health.", "\"The main difference between accrual accounting and cash accounting is when revenue and expenses are recognized.  Under cash basis accounting, revenue and expenses are recognized when cash is received and paid.  Under accrual accounting, revenue is recognized in the period it is earned, and expenses are recognized in the period they are incurred.  While cash basis accounting is easier to implement, accrual accounting is used by most businesses and presents a clearer picture of a company's overall financial health.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What have you done recently to become a better accountant?", "answers": ["This question allows the interviewer to gauge how motivated you are to learn new skills.  They will most likely be looking for a candidate that takes initiative to learn, so be sure to call out recent examples where you have acquired new skills.", "\"I am always looking for ways to learn more about my profession and acquire new skills.  As an example, I recently took a two week online course called Advanced Bookkeeping where I learned new skills related to inventory accounting.  Since your organization is a retailer, I believe I could use the knowledge obtained from this course in the inventory accountant role.  Once in the role, I would also seek out continuing education that allows me to apply skills acquired to help the organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What is obsolescence expense?", "answers": ["Obsolescence refers to inventory that no longer has value or has reduced value.  It is inventory that either cannot be sold or will be sold at a steep discount.  The interview candidate should be able to define obsolescence and also speak to its accounting treatment.", "\"Obsolescence occurs when inventory becomes obsolete.  As a result, the inventory cannot be sold or is expected to be sold at discounted pricing.  The obsolescence reserve is a contra asset on the balance sheet that reduces the gross inventory to its expected value net of obsolete inventory.  Obsolescence expense on the income statement reflects the periodic changes in that reserve balance.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are the three main financial statements, and what do they indicate about an organization\u2019s financial position?", "answers": ["The three main financial statements are the income statement, balance sheet, and statement of cash flows.  An accountant should know these statements in detail, as they will likely be preparing all three each month.", "\"The income statement shows profitability over a period of time by showing revenue less expenses.  The balance sheet summarizes a company's assets, liabilities, and equity at a point in time.  A cash flow statement shows the net cash inflows and outflows over a period of time.  Each statement is essential in order to gain insights into the financial health of an organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Do you have experience explaining complex accounting concepts to non-financial personnel?", "answers": ["Accountants will frequently interact with other departments within the company.  Many times, the employees in these departments do not have extensive knowledge of accounting concepts and terminology.  This question is an opportunity to highlight your communication skills.", "\"Yes, in my previous role I was able to interact with non-finance personnel when I would meet with the marketing team to review their results each month.  They didn't have a strong understanding of accounting principles, so I tried to 'speak their language' as much as possible when discussing their department's results vs. budget.  I believe I have the ability to communicate effectively with all personnel in an organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Are you open to travel with this position?", "answers": ["The inventory accountant position may require some travel, as the role will likely be involved in physical inventory counts.  These counts are typically performed at retail and warehouse locations.  Most job descriptions mention the travel required, so be sure to align your response with that requirement.", "\"As an inventory accountant, I understand I will be involved in the physical inventory counts at various warehouses throughout the Northeast.  The job description for this position mentioned 25% travel, and I am very comfortable with that.  I think the travel will be a great way to get out of the office and understand the operations of the organization.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Do you have experience working with external auditors?", "answers": ["A key responsibility of an accountant is to interact with and assist the external auditors.  You may be asked to assist with walkthroughs, which are interviews where the auditor documents the processes you follow each month, as part of their assessment of internal controls.  You may also be asked to either provide existing schedules (bank reconciliations, debt schedules, etc.) or prepare schedules for the audit.", "\"Yes, in my last role I interacted with our external auditors frequently in a variety of ways.  First, as part of their assessment of internal controls, I would sit down with them to complete walkthroughs of the processes I follow each month.  Additionally, I would prepare schedules that they would test as part of their audit.  Examples of these schedules include balance sheet reconciliations and amortization schedules for our intangible assets.  Finally, I would prepare draft footnote schedules for the audited financial statements.  I believe it's very important to have a good working relationship with the organization's auditors.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are the steps involved in the accounting close process?", "answers": ["This question is used to assess whether your understanding of the accounting close process aligns with the organization's.  Don't go into too much detail. Rather, just hit the key steps and then ask how it compares or differs from the organization's process.", "\"First and foremost, there needs to be a closing calendar so that deadlines are set for all departments.  Next, all data must be gathered.  This includes departments, such as payroll and accounts payable, preparing reports needed for journal entries.  Next, all journal entries are booked.  After journal entries are booked and reviewed, financial statements are prepared and balance sheet reconciliations are completed.  Finally, the results are reviewed with leadership.  Is there anything I described that differs from the process here at XYZ Corporation?\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are the steps involved in a physical inventory count?", "answers": ["Periodic inventory counts are crucial for businesses with material inventory value.  The physical count ensures that the value of inventory, as reflected on the books, is materially close to the actual value.  Most audits require inventory counts, and companies often view the counts as good business practice.", "\"First, the count must be planned.  This includes setting dates, identifying inventory to count, training staff, and ensuring the appropriate scanners and other technology is set up.  Next, on the date of the count, all inventory activities must be frozen so that the records are static.  Then, the physical inventory count is completed using printed count sheets.  Finally, any discrepancies are investigated and resolved.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are the different inventory valuation methods?", "answers": ["The goal of inventory valuation is to assign a monetary value to inventory that the company owns that has not yet been sold.  There are generally four accepted inventory valuation methods:  Specific Identification, First In, First Out (FIFO), Last In, First Out (LIFO) and Weighted Average Cost.  Each has its own advantages and disadvantages, so be prepared to briefly speak to each.", "\"There are four widely accepted inventory valuation methods.  The most clear cut is specific identification, where the cost of every item in inventory is specifically tracked.  This method is best used when the company sells a low volume of high value items (such as rare cars).  Next is First-In, First-Out, which presumes the first inventory purchased by the company is the first sold to the customer. Most companies use FIFO to value their inventory.  Last-In, First-Out assumes the newest inventory in stock is the first sold.  Finally, there's weighted average cost, which takes the cost of all products in inventory divided by the number of units.  This method is used when the products a company sells are very similar.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What accounting software are you familiar with?", "answers": ["Speak specifically to the accounting systems you have used and some of the functions you performed.  Many job descriptions specifically state which accounting software the company uses.  If any event, make sure to highlight that you are quick to learn new software systems.", "\"In my last role, I used SAP to book journal entries and run queries.  As an independent contractor, I also used Quickbooks to complete monthly bookkeeping for various clients.  I used that software to book journal entries, complete bank reconciliations, run monthly reports, and invoice customers.  Since I have an underlying understanding of accounting, I am easily able to learn new software packages.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What have you done at your previous job to reduce costs or save time?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know if you have the ability to improve processes.  Speak to a specific action you took that resulted in reduced costs, saved time, or better insights gained.", "\"My last role was bookkeeper for a small, established company.  However, my predecessor did not have established procedures in place and it sounded like he had made constant mistakes.  One of the first things I did when I started was I made a monthly checklist that detailed all the steps I took during the monthly close.  Included in these steps were 'checks' I performed to self-review my work.  The checklist served as a cover sheet that I would hand off to my manager so she would know exactly what steps I completed.  This led to increased efficiency, as we estimated it saved 4-6 hours a month in error corrections.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Are you willing to work extra hours if needed during busier times?", "answers": ["The life of an accountant is tied to the month-end close calendar, which could result in a schedule that is 'lumpy' and not a typical 9-5.  The candidate should expect there to be some additional time worked during busier times and should highlight that they are flexible.", "\"Yes, I am willing to work extra hours, as needed.  I understand that the work required ramps up during month-end close, tax filings, and other busier times.  I am happy to be flexible and work as needed to make sure the job gets done. \""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are 'Days Inventory on Hand', and what is indicated when days on hand grows?", "answers": ["This is a question that gauges whether you understand metrics and can use them to catch trends in the business.  Days Inventory on Hand is a metric that measures the health of the inventory asset.  A high or growing metric indicates that there are problems selling through inventory.", "\"Days Inventory on Hand is an important metric that measures the health of inventory.  The metric indicates how many days of cost of goods sold are hung up in inventory at any given time.  A low number of days indicates that the company is efficiently selling through inventory.  A growing number of days indicates that there may be some issues with sell-through, which could lead to obsolescence issues in the future.  Given this, sales strategy should be adjusted if Inventory DOH is growing.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Are you proficient in Excel?", "answers": ["Excel proficiency is a must for not only an inventory accountant, but any role in accounting.  At a minimum, an accountant should be able to sort through large amounts of data, and analyze that data using pivot tables.", "\"Yes, I am proficient in Excel.  I have used Excel extensively throughout my time in school, as well as in my previous role.  For example, I used data sorting and filtering, as well as pivot tables, to organize large amounts of data.  Additionally, I have experience using V-Lookups and H-Lookups to pull together analysis for our external auditors.  I have even dipped my toes into data visualization software such as Tableau, but that is a skill I would like to continue to nurture.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "Imagine you are reviewing inventory balances vs last year.  What would you expect to happen to ending inventory, if sales were lower than last year, and receipts were higher than last year?", "answers": ["This is a question that gauges whether you understand how different key metrics drive inventory changes.  In this specific example, lower sales and higher receipts would both cause inventory to grow vs last year.", "\"In this example, I would expect inventory to grow at a higher rate than it did last year.  Higher receipts means more product coming into inventory, and lower sales means fewer products leaving inventory.  This would be a concern to me, as higher inventory balances would indicate a higher obsolescence risk.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What is your comfort level with interacting and communicating with senior leadership?", "answers": ["An inventory accountant role is staff level but is unique in that the role interacts regularly with senior leadership. Highlight that you not only have experience presenting in front of leadership, but also that you are comfortable doing it.  Be specific with what you presented.  For example, monthly results, pitches for new initiatives, etc.", "\"I have ample experience getting in front of leadership and presenting.  In my previous role, I would present to the CEO, CFO, and other senior leaders during our monthly Finance Review meetings.  I always felt the need to prepare in advance for any questions that might arise and would promptly follow-up on anything that developed during those meetings.\""]}, {"topic": "Inventory+Accountant", "question": "What are some examples of internal controls that impact inventory?", "answers": ["Internal controls for inventory is vital for businesses of any size, as the company needs to make sure they have goods available to sell to their customers.  There are internal controls that help with tracking (bar-codes, inventory numbers), security (locks, security codes), and audits (physical inventory counts, obsolescence reviews).", "\"There are many examples of internal controls that would impact my role.  For example, there are audit controls that help with auditing the inventory balance, such as physical inventory counts and obsolescence reviews.  Other controls center around asset security, such as locks and security clearances.  Finally, there are tracking controls such as barcode setup and inventory numbering systems.\""]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Describe a time when you helped reduce costs.", "answers": ["You might have helped save costs in all sorts of ways!  Did you notice a common key expense that could be reduced while completing your accounting work?  Do you participate in a company committee where you helped save money?  Did you come up with a great idea to save the company money on a holiday party?  Or, maybe you are just starting out your career, but you have helped reduce your family's grocery bill by putting your accounting knowledge to work creating a budget.  The interviewer's goal is to determine if you are a cost conscious person, so go ahead and share one example of a time you helped reduce costs or save money!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Are you efficient with your time?", "answers": ["Yes, I am!. You understand that all accountants have a lot of work to accomplish every day, and you must be efficient with how you use your time to achieve your goals. You may even mention that you spend time each day prioritizing your focus for that day to ensure you are meeting deadlines, responding to urgent needs, and staying on track with meeting goals."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Why did you choose to pursue a career as an accountant?", "answers": ["What led you to become an accountant?  Did you have a mentor who encouraged you to pursue the field due to your strong attention to detail?  Have you always enjoyed working with numbers?  Do you enjoy financial concepts?  Or, did you complete a job shadow during high school that you really enjoyed?  Now is the time to share your story!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What type of schedule are you looking to work?", "answers": ["Each person has their own scheduling needs, and it is important to be candid with the interviewer about your availability.  Begin by telling the interviewer if you are seeking full-time or part-time hours.  Then, define what days/times you are available for work.  You might state something like this, \"I am looking for a full-time schedule hopefully working Monday-Friday 8:00 a.m. - 5:00 p.m.  I am available to work later into the evenings, and I am happy to come in on an occasional to weekend to help out when necessary.\"", "\"I am looking for a full-time schedule hopefully working Monday-Friday 8:00 a.m. - 5:00 p.m.  I am available to work later into the evenings, and I am happy to come in on an occasional to weekend to help out when necessary.\""]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Would you be available to work extra hours if needed?", "answers": ["Be open & honest with the interviewer sharing if you are available to work extra hours if necessary understanding that you may eliminate yourself from consideration if you are unable to work additional hours.  It is better to learn now that additional hours are required rather than later!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What has been the most significant decision you made at work this year?", "answers": ["What decision led to the biggest payoff?  What decision had the impact on the largest number of people?  What decision led to a culture change or major process change?  These questions will help lead you to determine your most significant decision in the past year.  Once you know your most significant decision, provide the interviewer with an overview of the decision you had to make.  Discuss why the decision needed to be made, the pros and cons of a few possible outcomes, and what decision you ultimately made.  Next, share how your decision played out highlighting the positive results from the decision you made."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What position in a team environment, do you normally take?", "answers": ["Be candid with the interviewer expressing where you typically land in a team environment.  Are you the person always leading the pack?  Or, are you an actively involved participant?  Maybe you tend to be the quiet one who offers great suggestions and creative ideas.  Or, perhaps you like to be the person who takes the lead on executing ideas that others come up with.  Be true to yourself expressing what role you typically took in a team setting."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Take me through your latest budget preparation.", "answers": ["Begin by telling the interviewer what your latest budget preparation was for.  Was it for a large project?  Or, was it a year-end budget?  Share how large of a budget you were working with.  In many cases, you will not be able to disclose exact amounts for confidentiality reasons, and that is okay!  Instead, ballpark the number using phrases like 'tens of thousands' or 'hundreds of millions' to define your budget framework for the interviewer.  Share how you determined where the money will be spent, who approved the budget, and how the budget is tracked against actual spending."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What do you know about our company?", "answers": ["With any job interview, it is crucial to understand the organization you are applying to. We recommend visiting the company's website to learn key information such as company history, key services offered, who the current CEO is, mission & vision, and even fun facts such as recent events the company has posted on social media! As a bonus, be sure to mention any positive interactions you have had with current employees as well as what they have told you about the company."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What makes you a great fit for this position?", "answers": ["The key is in the job description!  Before arriving for your interview, we encourage you to review the job description the company posted when you applied for the job.  Take note of the Qualifications section.  What is the company looking for?  These things will make up your answer!  Simply list off the qualifications that you possess!  For example, you might state, \"I have an excellent eye for details.  One of my college professors commented that I never seem to make any errors!\"", "\"I have an excellent eye for details.  One of my college professors commented that I never seem to make any errors!\""]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about your math skills.", "answers": ["Basic math is essential for an accountant, and the interviewer is trying to learn more about your level of expertise.  Share what college math courses you took.  Talk about what math you typically utilize in your job on a day-to-day basis.  Mention any math honors that you have received such as winning a math competition, and be sure to mention how you utilize programs like Excel to keep math simple on the job!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What have you done recently to become a better Junior Accountant?", "answers": ["Interviewers love hearing that you continually work on furthering yourself as a professional.  Have you read any good business books recently?  Are you a part of any professional associations?  Have you taken a seminar or attended a conference?  Or, have you received mentorship from another accountant?  Simply list 1-2 things that you have done recently to further your professional career."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What are your greatest strengths?", "answers": ["This is the time to discuss the talent you offer, and employers want to see that you know yourself and work within your strengths. Jump right in offering your key strengths! Maybe you are really good at analyzing data, understanding financial concepts, building rapport with internal customers, or ensuring you have a balanced budget. Be sure to mention how you use these strengths in the workplace!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "How have you monitored the regulations that affect your accounting position?", "answers": ["Keeping up with laws and regulations is important in most industries.  How do you keep up with those affecting your accounting position?  Do you subscribe to email updates that keep you in the loop?  Do you attend seminars and conferences that help you stay tuned into this information?  Or, do you have one person on your team who is responsible for this and keeps your whole group up-to-date?  Simply share how you stay in touch with regulation updates."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Why do you want to work for our company?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear that you are passionate about some aspect of the organization. What do you like most about this company? Have you heard great things about it? Do they offer great benefits? Does the job have a unique aspect that appeals to you? Simply share what you like most about the company, and share that this is a big part of why you want to work for this organization!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Why are you the best candidate for us?", "answers": ["Talking about ourselves in this way can be challenging. We recommend reaching out to a few colleagues, family members, and friends. Ask them for their opinion. You'll probably be surprised at the consistency in their responses! Their answers will give you the response to the question. Tell the interviewer what sets you apart, and explain how your colleagues, family members, and friends have encouraged you with your gift in this area."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What are your career goals as a Junior Accountant?", "answers": ["In other words, what do you hope to achieve in this position?  This question is all about you, and the interviewer is trying to determine if they can help you achieve your goals.  What are you hoping to get out of this position?  Simply share what you hope to achieve in this position, and be sure to mention that you look forward to learning as much as possible along the way!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What are your greatest weaknesses?", "answers": ["We all have weaknesses, and it is okay to share yours! Pick a weakness to share that is not a priority for a junior accountant. Common answers might be: \n\r\n- Having to negotiate a sale...like when buying a new car. I would prefer to just be given the best price first! \r\n- Hosting company at my house. It stresses me out! \r\n- Giving a speech in front of a large crowd of people. \r\n- Being afraid of trying adventurous things such as bungee jumping, sky diving, or riding the latest roller coaster. \n\r\nSimply share a couple of your weaknesses with the interviewer."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "How do you minimize the risk of errors in your work?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear that you have some sort of method for ensuring the accuracy of your work.  Do you read your work out loud to help you catch errors?  Do you utilize dual monitors to help you cross-check information?  Do you use a buddy system to cross-check each others work?  Whatever method you are accustomed to using, share it with the interviewer!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about your computer skills.", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear what computer programs you are proficient with.  Simply tell the interviewer which programs you comfortably use.  You might consider Word, Excel, Outlook, PowerPoint, QuickBooks, any accounting software, as well as the internet for business research.  When discussing accounting software, be sure to include a high-level overview of what you typically utilize the software for to help the interviewer understand your level of expertise."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Describe a situation in which you received instructions with which you disagreed.", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear that you work for the betterment of the organization while respecting your company's leadership.  Think about a time a decision was made that you disagreed with yet you had a positive reaction.  Tell the interviewer the instructions you were given and explain why you disagreed with the instructions.  Next, describe your positive response.  Did you simply comply with the instructions because you wanted to respect your leadership team?  Did you mention key information that the person may not have thought of before giving you the instructions that made the person change their mind?  Be sure to mention that being a team player is key, and there are times when you just go with the flow of leadership's direction, and there are times when you need to speak up with key information that others may not have thought about."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What have you done at your present/last company to increase revenues, reduce costs, or save time?", "answers": ["Interviewers love hearing that you help the organization achieve a better bottom line whether it is through dollars or time saved to get more work accomplished.  Think about how your actions have impacted the organization's bottom line recently.  What have you done to create a better bottom line?  Did an idea you had recently get implemented which resulted in cost savings?  Did you come up with a new promotional strategy that increased revenues for your company?  Or, maybe you found a way to make a process more efficient saving your company time!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Do you work well under pressure?", "answers": ["Yes, I do! A Junior Accountant's job is filled with meeting endless expectations of internal & external customers, and the interviewer wants to hear that you thrive under this pressure. Tell the interviewer that the pressure of the industry motivates you, and you like knowing that you have an opportunity to thrive in pressure-filled situations."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "How do you handle stressful situations?", "answers": ["The interviewer is really looking for past experiences that you have been in that have been stressful. They want to get to know your background better. Highlight these examples, tell them how you remained calm, and held your composure. Tell the interviewer what you learned from those experiences. A good example, when you have been in stressful situations, you have found its best to remain calm so you can think through any challenges that you are facing. Try to think of these examples before the interview, because this is a very common interview question and may likely be asked."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "What are the most challenging aspects of your work?", "answers": ["An interviewer wants to hear that your work is challenging because having a challenge often helps keep employees engaged.  What is the most challenging aspect of your work?  Is there one specific task that is challenging?  Or, is it staying on top of a very busy workload?  Go ahead and share your greatest challenge!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "How did you maintain confidentiality when managing information?", "answers": ["Easy!  You just don't talk about things that others do not need to know about!  Interviewers need to hear that maintaining confidentiality is easy for you.  Share that maintaining confidentiality is of the utmost importance, and you just don't share things that others do not need to know about.  Additionally, share that you ensure papers are turned over on your desk when you are away to add protection from wandering eyes.  Mention if you lock your filing cabinet drawers.  Discuss if you lock your office door each night.  And, mention if you use a screen cover to keep others from being able to read your computer monitor."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "How have you managed potential payment problems with your customers?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear that you hold your customers accountable for payments while remaining positive and professional when working through payment problems.  A great example of this scenario is an excellent long standing customer who simply made a mistake with a payment at one point in time.  Give the interviewer a high-level overview of a time when you had a payment issue with a customer.  Define the problem, and share how you realized there was an issue.  If the customer was a long standing excellent customer, be sure to mention that you have worked with this customer many times in the past and there was never a mistake before.  You knew the customer had good intentions, and it was probably an honest mistake on their part.  Next, share how you responded to the situation by courteously addressing the situation with the customer to resolve the issue.  Be sure to mention that most customers are wonderful about their payments, and the challenging ones are few and far between.  Share that you focus on the good customers and happily work through any bumps in the road that occur along the way!"]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me how you reacted when someone elses errors were impacting negatively on your job.", "answers": ["Interviewers are hoping to hear that you react positively as a team player during times when you are impacted by another person's errors.  Think about a time this happened to you, and you had a pleasant reaction.  Tell the interviewer what error the other person made, and discuss how the error impacted you.  Next, tell the interviewer that mistakes happen, and you just did what needed to be done to ensure everything was correct on your end."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Do you have previous experience as an accountant?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to learn about any accounting background that you have.  Did you complete an internship?  How about a job shadowing experience?  Did you previously work with A/R or A/P?  All of these make great examples!  Share any accounting related experience that you have mentioning where you worked, your role, and how long you were a part of the team.  If you are a recent graduate with no official experience, that is okay too!  Tell the interviewer that you recently graduated, and share any large accounting projects you worked on during your collegiate studies."]}, {"topic": "Junior+Accountant", "question": "Where do you see yourself in 5 years?", "answers": ["Interviewers want to hear that you will be in the accounting field still working for the same company! Tell the interviewer that you see yourself actively engaged within the field. Explain how you hope you have grown professionally, and mention that you see yourself having continued to create a positive career path within the organization.  You may even mention if you hope to have received a promotion by the five-year mark!"]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What courses did you enjoy most while completing your accounting/payroll education?", "answers": ["Share your thoughts on the courses you most enjoyed during your post-secondary education, and be sure to include details as to why. The answer you provide will show the interviewer your greatest strengths and interests regarding accounting and payroll topics. Also, the hiring company could use this knowledge to help you follow a career path inside their company that plays to your interest and greatest strengths.", "\"I have always enjoyed working with numbers, and thus attending school to become a Payroll Compliance Practitioner made sense to me. In school, I really enjoyed learning about Payroll Compliance Legislation and how laws change from region to region. These regulation and compliance-related courses gave me a great feel for the work involved in effective payroll practices and how my work can contribute to my employer.\"", "\"When I was in school to become a Certified Payroll Manager, most of my coursework was highly enjoyable. I thrived in accounting, compensation theory, and organizational management. Most of all, I enjoyed learning about Benefits and Compensation Management. I like to educate employees on monetary and non-monetary reward and compensation programs. In my current position, I helped to optimize the company's incentive plans, including profit-sharing options.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Describe a typical payroll day in your current position.", "answers": ["The interviewer would like details around how you organize your payroll days. Perhaps you have a special checklist that you utilize on the day you run payroll, or maybe your software system has a checklist for you. Provide the interviewer with an overview of what an average payroll day looks like for you, remembering that the interviewer's goal is to hear that you are organized, diligent, and pay attention to detail.", "\"I have a monthly checklist with different due dates. I split tasks from the start, middle, and end of the month. Then, I put all of these tasks in my Google calendar and set up alerts. Using these organizational tools, I never miss a deadline and focus on efficiency rather than waste time trying to remember what tasks are next. Missing even a single pointer can mean a delay in employee salary distribution which is unacceptable. This importance is why I am sure to remain diligent and pay attention to every deadline and detail.\"", "\"One of the things I love most about my work as a Payroll Specialist is there is no such thing as a 'typical' day.  I am always managing an aspect of the payroll cycle, whether in preparation, inputting, processing or auditing. As always, things will come up that my team and I address, such as payroll inquiries from business leaders or employee compensation questions. This variety keeps my role interesting since I love to problem-solve. I'd love it if you could take me through an average day in this position with Company XYZ.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What experience do you have implementing a new payroll system?", "answers": ["If you have experience implementing a new payroll system, discuss your involvement in detail. For instance, the interviewer may want to know how you approached researching new payroll systems. Perhaps you asked for input from other payroll professionals, watched demonstrations, met with vendors, and received numerous quotes before making suggestions to your leadership team. Talk about how you analyzed your organization's needs to select the correct product suggestions and determine which components of the new system would be most critical. \n\nDiscuss the stakeholders you worked with to implement the new system, and how you integrated data from the company's existing system. You can also discuss how you communicated with staff to bring them up to speed on locating their pay stubs, and any other pertinent details in the new system. \n\nThe interviewer will want to hear that you handled this process carefully while navigating the complex landscape of system changes. \n\nIf you have not been part of implementing a new payroll system, be open and honest with the interviewer. Inform the interviewer of the payroll systems you have worked with, and assure them that you are ready to handle tasks that require critical thinking and calculated decision making.", "\"I researched and then implemented a new payroll system while working with Company ABC. First, I researched new payroll systems and asked other payroll professionals in my network for their professional opinions. The next step was to analyze our organization's needs to select the correct product as well as product components. Once I narrowed down these components, I watched demonstrations online to determine the top three systems that could meet the organizations' unique needs. Then, I met with vendors and received quotes. I worked in sync with our finance and IT departments to avoid technical or functional errors when we integrated our existing data into the new system. Then, I arranged team training on the new system. Overall, the implementation was a great success. Our company was able to automate many aspects of payroll and there were fewer errors as a result.\"", "\"My work has been with organizations that have solid payroll systems in place. I have worked on a variety of payroll systems in my career, including A, B, and C. Is your organization considering an overhaul of its existing payroll system?\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What information do you need to properly set up an employee into a payroll system?", "answers": ["This basic question will allow the interviewer to gauge your level of experience and knowledge in payroll. It will also show the interviewer your ability to properly set up an employee in a payroll system. Your response should be straightforward and to the point. Be sure to include information on the payroll systems or accounting software you are familiar with.", "\"To set up an employee into a payroll system, such as Quickbooks, the details I would include are the employees' full name, date of birth, social insurance number, pay rate, commission and bonus details, and any other variable forms of payment. Also, if the employee would like additional income tax deduced, I would include that information, and any other details the company deems necessary to log.\"", "\"From my understanding, to set up an employee into a payroll system, I should include personal details such as the employee's full name, government ID, compensation details, and any other information required to ensure the employee is paid correctly and within pay regulations for the company's region.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Describe to me any payroll process that you have developed or revised.", "answers": ["Think of a payroll-related problem you helped solve. Give the interviewer a brief overview of the problem that was brought to your attention. Discuss the action steps you took to address the issue and any processes you put in place to ensure the problem did not occur again in the future.  Explain why you chose this revision and be sure to include the result of your actions. If you are new to your career, think of a problem you faced in school, a team sport, or a volunteer activity. Talk about how you contributed to a solution.", "\"While working for Company ABC as a Payroll Assistant, I realized that the timesheets were not populating correctly, and this was resulting in a problem with the calculations of the working hours for the employees. I solicited the help of the finance and IT department, and we worked together to troubleshoot the issue. We were able to repair a bug in the timesheet system, which resulted in well-sorted and accurate data for the employees' logged hours from then on.\"", "\"During my time as Payroll Manager for Company ABC, the organization was growing rapidly. As a result, the payroll department had to reevaluate the entire payroll process. At first, we were using Paychex and calling in the hours each week. As our locations expanded, our headcount increased, and our compensation packages became more complex and varied, we decided to upgrade our payroll technology and process. I led the project, pricing and negotiating a new contract with ADP.  We also changed over our time clock system from manual to electronic to eliminate time and errors. It was a significant improvement to the overall process which solved a lot of payroll issues moving forward.\"", "\"There were some inaccuracy issues with our system when we processed payroll, which affected the employee\u2019s check. I realized that if the totals didn't match, then the error lay in the parts of the sum. I suggested that we customize a report that compared specific elements such as the hours entered and other relevant components with the timesheet to reconcile the data. We would implement a quick glance at it after completing payroll entry to ensure accuracy. This eliminated inadvertent errors immediately.\"", "Good thinking on your part! It would be great to include more detail in your story surrounding how you came to your idea. This way, you can take the interviewer through your problem-solving thought process."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Each of our buildings has a designated payroll timekeeper that reports biweekly. Two reports are late. How would you approach this situation?", "answers": ["The way you answer this scenario-based question will help the interviewer gauge your level of expertise and learn more about how you react when roadblocks occur in the workplace. \n\nShow that you understand mistakes will occasionally happen. If it is not a recurring issue, you may simply call the responsible party and ensure the missing information is provided as soon as possible. If the issue becomes ongoing, perhaps you would schedule a face-to-face meeting to talk through the problem. \n\nDisplay that you are a strong communicator by expressing the way you would approach this conversation. For instance, you might let this person know that their actions are impacting the company. You might also create an action plan for change that included consistent follow-ups until the behavior was corrected. Inform the interviewer that you would work with the individual to put a plan in place to eliminate future problems, and if the issue was not resolved, you would escalate the issue appropriately.", "\"If this incident was the first time, I would call the person in charge and make sure that the reports were sent to me before any further delays occurred. I would thank them ahead of time for ensuring this situation did not happen again. If this scenario became a regular occurrence, I would arrange a face-to-face meeting with the timekeeper to find out why the problem is recurring. After identifying the root cause of the issue, I would collaborate with my co-worker to formulate a plan so that it didn't happen in the future. If the problem persisted, I would contact the appropriate supervisor and work toward a longer-lasting solution.\"", "\"In this situation, I would reach as soon as the reports were late and ask some open-ended questions, to see if the issue was an isolated incident. If the situation happened again, I would ask to meet with the person to make sure there are no roadblocks such as training, or timing. If the situation called for it, I would invite the associate to cross-train and learn what the reports are used for on the other end. This knowledge might broaden their understanding of the process and the impact a late report can have on other departments and stages of payroll. If the behavior continued, I would take measures to initiate a performance improvement plan.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What are your salary expectation?", "answers": ["In many states, it is now illegal for hiring authorities to ask about your current earnings. For that reason, a vague question regarding your expectations will give the interviewer a solid idea of what you are hoping to earn without crossing any ethical lines. \n\nTypically, when you change jobs, you want to see an increase in wages. Most interviewers aim for a 7-15% increase for each time they change jobs. This range offers room for negotiations with the new company. This percentage increase reflects economic inflation, unique skills you bring from the last time you joined an organization, and an increase in responsibilities. \n\nSalary is an important conversation to have, and now is the time to share your desires and expectations openly.  \nBe open, and honest. Transparency is the best choice when salary-based questions arise.\n\nIf you are newer to your career, or the area, and are unsure of what a fair ask may be, there are many reliable salary calculators available online. \n\nIf you do not have salary expectations, it's time to do your research. The more prepared you are with data on fair pay for the market the more the interviewer will respect you and your stance.", "\"I am looking for growth in terms of responsibilities as well as in monetary terms. Through my research I see that the market average for this role, for someone with my years of experience ranges between $X nad $X per year. I am also interested in discussing your overall compensation offering in addition to the base salary.\"", "\"As I am new to my career and this industry, I am happy to negotiate my earnings based on your typical salary for this role. From my research, I see that the average Junior Payroll Administrator in the Chicago area earns an annual salary in the $45K to $50K range. I am looking for compensation comparable to the responsibilities of the role. I trust the overall compensation package will be fair, including base salary and other employee benefits. Could you share with me the compensation plan for this role?\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "How do you remain up-to-date on payroll rules and techniques?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know that you are diligent with remaining in-the-know of payroll rules, laws, and techniques to optimize your time and efficiency. Perhaps you receive email updates from an HR governing body that shares updates, tips, and tricks. Maybe your payroll vendor keeps you in tune with new rules and techniques on their homepage or your dashboard. Or, perhaps you attend payroll-related conferences, seminars, and webinars. Be sure to mention any professional payroll organizations you regularly participate in or hold a membership with. Finally, mention that you network with other payroll professionals in or outside of your company to see what new techniques they are using.", "\"I read a few reputable blogs related to payroll, HR, and compensation law. I also follow a few forums online that hosts people in the payroll industry that I trust. Once per year, my current employer arranges for me to attend a payroll-related conference. When I return from these conferences, I hold a weeks' worth of lunch 'n learns to pass my knowledge on to the department. It's very important to me that I remain in-the-know of payroll-related law and strategies so that I am as accurate and efficient as possible for my employer.\"", "\"Remaining in-the-know is a critical part of maintaining compliance and staying current on industry changes and news. I am an active member of multiple payroll associations such as A, B, and C. I read the news every day and am connected with the IRS/DOL on any changes that may impact my work and the efforts of my team.\"", "\"Receiving daily emails from different agencies regarding updates on payroll regulations definitely help. Attending payroll-related seminars and conferences is another good way of staying in tune with regulatory developments. Furthermore, consistently checking IRS/DOL websites, doing online research, and networking with other payroll professionals prove to be good supplementary practices.\"", "Good answer! You are clearly diligent in remaining updated on payroll rules and techniques. It's terrific that you rely on a range of helpful and reputable sources for your information."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What is the largest payroll run you have been in charge of?", "answers": ["Discuss the largest payroll run you have been in charge of, including details such as dollar amount and total employee headcount. Be sure to mention that you understand how important it is to maintain a high level of detail when working with large sums of money. The interviewer wants assurance that you can manage their payroll volume so be sure to include a qualifying statement at the end of your response.", "\"I have handled payroll runs for medium and large size companies. The largest number of employees I have processed payroll for was 557, with the average run amounting to just under $3M. Thanks to my experience working in a variety of companies, I understand the need for accuracy and precision no matter the dollar amounts I am working with. Rest assured I will be just as careful and accurate with 5 employees as I would with 5,000.\"", "\"In my previous role, I was responsible for a $60M weekly payroll for over 20,000 employees worldwide. There were many variables to manage with different locations and laws in place, depending on the region. I am confident that this extensive experience will ensure my success with your organization, considering you have employees across the globe.\"", "\"The largest payroll I have been in charge of was $100,000 for a weekly payroll belonging to a travel marketing agency with a fluctuating headcount of around 100 employees. This was only one of 50+ companies that I oversaw payroll for, and they each vary in industry, city, and size. I had to account for each respective company's local regulations. With this experience, I understand the need for precision with money at stake.\"", "You would certainly have to be diligent with your work's quality, being responsible for 50  companies! Good answer - it's clear that you take pride in your work."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "If an employee called in with a payroll complaint, how would you handle it?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to see that you express empathy and understand how concerning payroll challenges are for employees. They also want to know that you can handle the issue through critical problem-solving. Perhaps you take detailed notes of the employee's complaint and then get to work solving the issue. Maybe you talk through the issue together so that you can solve the payroll problem right away. Sometimes payroll issues need time to figure out. In these instances, inform the interviewer that you express your apologies to the employee and provide an approximate timeline for a solution.", "\"As a Payroll Specialist, I am a service provider and the employees that I serve always remain one of my primary areas of focus. For that reason, any valid payroll complaint, such as a missing direct deposit, should be dealt with immediately. When I receive a payroll complaint, my first reaction is to apologize and empathize. Then, I look into the matter ASAP. I take detailed notes of the situation and begin to troubleshoot. Often, the issue comes down to a simple coding error, and I can quickly repair the issue. However, there are times when I need to dig deeper. In that case, I keep the employee updated on the progress and offer a written cheque to supplement their financial concerns until I can resolve their payroll issue.\"", "\"For example: \"If an employee reached out with a payroll concern I would listen to the concern, research the issue and find a resolution as soon as possible. I would also note the payroll error and inform the appropriate manager. Payroll concerns are sensitive since employees are relying on their paycheck to be accurate and timely. For that reason, I believe any employee's payroll-related concerns should be resolved within 24 business hours.\"", "\"I would put myself in the employee's shoes to be as empathetic as possible, listen carefully, and apologize that the issue occurred. I would take detailed notes of what happened and assure them that we would investigate and resolve it as soon as possible. I'd give them a timeframe of when it would be resolved and when they would hear from me. As I resolve the issue, I would document the resolution process to prevent future reoccurrences. Then I would reach out to inform them it has been resolved, to apologize once more, and to assure them it would never happen again.\"", "It seems you are highly organized and keen on process, which is fabulous news for a payroll specialist :) You walk through this answer with ease, and your professionalism shines through."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What are the most important attributes a Payroll Specialist should have?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to see that you understand the attributes required to succeed in this role and with this company. Most of all, they are seeking assurance that you possess these attributes yourself. Take a look at the job description before heading to the interview, and you will see what attributes are most important to the role. These characteristics will likely be listed in the 'Qualifications' section of the job posting. You will likely see mention of attributes like great attention to detail, strong verbal and written communication skills, robust interpersonal skills, and the ability to solve complex problems. Discuss what you believe to be the most important attributes for a Payroll Specialist to possess and why. Then, provide evidence that you will bring these characteristics to the workplace.", "\"I believe that attention to detail, accuracy, and precision along with commendable communication skills are some of the most important attributes a Payroll Specialist should possess. I put attention to detail and accuracy at the highest importance. For instance, when I (tell a brief story of a time when your attention to detail directly impacted the workplace). Since the beginning of my career, I have worked hard to ensure that my written and verbal communication is spot on. For instance, I...(give details of how you have worked to perfect your communication skills). With these attributes, I can avoid mistakes, which in this profession is a top priority.\"", "\"I understand that the attibutes the hiring company is looking for, and some of the most important in this role overall include strong interpersonal skills and the ability to work cross-departmentally. I am able to get along with many personalities and work closely with various groups. For instance, when I was completing my internship, I (tell a brief story of a time when your interpersonal skills shined through). Throughout my time in university, I worked hard to ensure that I could work across various groups and with different professors. This skill will come through very well when I liaise between various department. I look forward to showing this organization these attributes, and more, in action.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What have you done to improve your written and verbal communication skills?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know that you put effort into enhancing your communication, regardless of your professional experience level. Discuss your preferred methods for honing your verbal and written communication skills. You can also discuss how you utilize your new skills in the workplace. If you have noticed a marked improvement from your efforts, be sure to mention this improvement.", "\"To improve my verbal communication skills, I attend meetings with a group of international residents in the county and have discussions with them over several topics. I have also been an active member of a photography club where we share information about new techniques and tricks for improving our skills. Apart from that, I attend webinars related to payroll that improve my language skills while keeping me updated on important industry and regulatory changes.\"", "\"Clear communication has been one of my keys to success during school and my recent internship. To continually improve, I use mixed written communication methods while connecting with my leaders and peers. To enhance my verbal communication skills, I recently joined Toastmasters. So far, I have gained a lot of confidence when presenting to small groups.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What are your future plans with the company?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know about your career goals and aspirations for a title promotion over time. Be realistic in your timeline for achieving growth. Show enthusiasm for your work as a Payroll Specialist by keeping the bulk of your answer focused on the way you plan to make an impact in this particular job.", "\"I am excited about the opportunity to work as a Payroll Specialist for your organization. I believe that this will be a great learning opportunity for me. Some years down the line, I want to earn my way into a team lead or payroll supervisory role; however, I have a lot of experience to gain in this role in the meantime.\"", "\"It is important to me that I grow personally and professionally, regardless of potential title promotions. In this Payroll Specialist role, I welcome the opportunity to learn and thrive while eventually taking on a leadership position as I prove my capabilities. Most of all, I plan to add value and build meaningful relationships that serve the greater good of the company.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Give me examples of the payroll reports you have prepared.", "answers": ["Be prepared with a list of reports that you have prepared, and be ready to provide a high-level overview of the data you understand to be found in these reports. The interviewer wants to see that you have experience preparing reports and that you understand the importance of this data. Talk to the interviewer about the ways you can manipulate data within your payroll system to generate the financial reports your company needs. Be sure to mention the systems and formats with which you are familiar such as Word, Excel, or Adobe.", "\"I am well-versed in preparing income statements, new hire reports, promotion reports, deduction reports, leave/absentee reports, and wage types. When necessary, I can manipulate all data provided to me and create reports in any format. Are there any other specifics I can provide you with regarding my payroll reporting experience?\"", "\"Reports are a large part of streamlining and ensuring the accuracy of the payroll process. I run weekly auditing reports, total time and payments reports, and financial reports to provide my company with the knowledge they need. Each payroll run, I audit the inputs and track the organization's paid time off updates. The internal reporting tool we use is great because I can consistently come up with custom reports to meet the needs of my employer.\"", "\"I have primarily used software called Pensoft to generate and customize almost every report crucial to payroll, including but not limited to personnel reports, leave reports, earnings reports, deductions reports, summary reports, accuracy reports, etc. I am also experienced in manipulating data within the system to produce reports in other formats such as Word and Excel. A lot of payroll software function the same on the basic level; thus, my experience will be transferrable.\"", "Wonderful response! You are very specific and sound confident that your experiences and skills will transfer well to this new role."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What is a general ledger?", "answers": ["This basic question will allow the interviewer to gauge your level of experience and knowledge in payroll. It will also show the interviewer your ability to explain a payroll-related term in a way that anyone can understand. People can clearly explain concepts they genuinely understand, after all! Your response should be straightforward and to the point. If you want to add a little pizazz into your answer, you can provide an example of your professional experience working with general ledgers.", "\"A general ledger or G/L is used by businesses to track financial transactions by assets, liabilities, equity, revenue, and expenses. In my current position, I work with general ledgers daily. For instance, I (give an example of a time when your knowledge of G/L use benefitted your employer).\"", "\"While completing my Payroll certification, I learned that a general ledger is the main accounting record for a company or organization. It ties into the profit and loss and accounts for all expenses or monies earned across the board. It is an essential financial tool for a business and a Payroll Specialist.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "How would you familiarize yourself with our payroll system?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to see that you are a go-getter and a self-starter. Tell the interviewer that you would start with independent learning, perhaps by clicking through the system to understand what it looks like or taking in some online tutorials. Perhaps you would visit the vendor's website to see if any how-to lessons are offered. Whatever your approach, show the hiring company that you are an enthusiastic go-getter who will jump on board, ready to learn.", "\"I have always believed in learning by doing. Being tech-savvy certainly helps a lot. I plan to familiarize myself with the company's system by watching online tutorials before my first day. I will also absorb the training I receive once hired. I will be sure to find solutions to any obstacles that I come across and I will ask questions of my more experienced co-workers or my supervisor, when appropriate.\"", "\"Utilizing my 12 years of experience in payroll pricing, testing, and evaluation of many major payroll providers, it will be a seamless transition to familiarize myself with your payroll system. I understand that companies typically customize their payroll system, so it will only be a matter of clicking around to learn how the system works for this organization. I am familiar with many payroll systems such as Workday, ADP, Paychex, Jupiter, and Quickbooks. Could you share with me some details of the systems you use and how they have been customized to suit Company XYZ?\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What is a fiscal year?", "answers": ["This basic question will allow the interviewer to gauge your level of experience and knowledge in payroll. It will also show the interviewer your ability to explain an accounting-related term in a way that anyone can understand. People can clearly explain concepts they genuinely understand, after all! Your response should be straightforward and to the point.", "\"A fiscal year is a 12-month cycle established by each organization for accounting and financial purposes. For instance, an organization may choose to begin their fiscal year on June 1st and end the fiscal year on the last day of May of the following calendar year.\"", "\"While completing my accounting degree, I learned that a fiscal year is the accounting period for a company. Sometimes this is the calendar year. Other times, companies operate on a different cycle such as a September to August fiscal year.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "How does higher management benefit from payroll reports?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer that senior leadership needs payroll reports as part of their role to understand expenses regarding compensation and benefits and payroll taxes. At the end of the day, their job is to ensure the organization is secure financially. There is a good chance that payroll expenses will be one of the highest expenses the organization occurs regularly. To help them stay up-to-date on how payroll expenses affect the organization and ensure they have all of the necessary information to make sound financial decisions, payroll reports are necessary.", "\"Higher management is responsible for ensuring the financial security of the company. Payroll expenses are among the highest expenses an organization incurs. For that reason, higher management will benefit from staying up-to-date on payroll expenses and how they are impacting the organization financially. Higher management can utilize payroll reports to ensuring that they have the necessary information to make sound financial decisions.\"", "\"Higher management can benefit from payroll reports by using the reported data in their forecasting for future staffing and to help make other critical financial decisions. These reports can also be leveraged if the management team is presenting to the board or other stakeholders. Higher management teams can also include payroll reports when reviewing the company's operating expenses and net income.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Why are you interested in this Payroll Specialist position?", "answers": ["It is a good idea to tell the interviewer that you enjoy being in a role that allows you to analyze information and be highly detail-oriented. Perhaps you enjoy being behind the scenes working with numbers, and you like that you are working in a vital role that directly impacts others' financial security. Keep in mind that the interviewer wants to see evidence that you have excitement for the job and you are ready to make a direct contribution by utilizing your specific talents.", "\"Since starting my career in the field of payroll, I have enjoyed working with complex numbers and improving the efficiency of numerous departments. In addition to what I have heard about your organization, I have also done my own research, and I have great interest and respect for the industry you serve and would love to utilize my knowledge and learn and grow my skills with the organization.\"", "\"I am interested in this Payroll Specialist position for many reasons. The most personal and compelling are [give one or two reasons why this job is a stand-out opportunity]. I have spent a lot of time researching and getting to know your company and [discuss your findings with enthusiasm]. This partnership would be mutually beneficial in the sense that [discuss how the findings tie to your career goals]. Should you choose to hire me, I will contribute to [the original highlights you mentioned in the beginning] by [offer details on how you will contribute].\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "How do you ensure that payroll is paid correctly and on time?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know that you will handle their volume and the unique needs of their organization. Show that you will give careful thought to their unique payroll set-up and that you will take the time to learn the ins and outs of their process. You can discuss how you will utilize the notes feature in your payroll software to document any special requirements.", "\"I use Excel and take extensive notes while doing my job. I keep my work organized and plan steps in advance. I have worked around special pay items to make sure that employees are paid correctly and on time. Checklists are an effective practice and I have found they work well in measuring an efficient payroll each cycle. I will create checklist items for any unique contract or special payment terms. Then, I double check to make sure the inputs are accurate before each payroll cycle.\"", "\"One of the most effective practices I have found works well in measuring an efficient payroll each cycle is utilizing checklists. Simply put, I will create checklist items for each special contract or unique payment terms to ensure we are double or triple checking the inputs to measure accuracy each cycle.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Would you ever pay an employee through accounts payable rather than payroll?", "answers": ["This may be a challenging or 'trick' question since employees should be paid through payroll; however, a contractor can be paid through accounts payable (A/P) as a way for the company to write their fee off as an expense. Tell the interviewer that you understand the different circumstances that may arise when considering A/P to pay someone for their work or services.", "\"From my experience, I have only paid contractors through A/P and permanent employees through a regular payroll cycle. There are certain labor expenses that are better handled through accounts payable than through payroll. In this particular scenario, I would ask a range of questions before running a labor-related expense through A/P rather than a usual payroll run.\"", "\"There are several times when I have used A/P to compensate a temporary or contracted associate versus utilizing payroll. All of our contractors on 1099s are compensated through A/P.  Anytime we hire a vendor to do work for our organization, we invoice and pay through accounting, not payroll.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Have you had responsibility for state and federal tax payments?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants an overview of your experience with filing quarterly taxes, year-end taxes, and any other tax-related tasks pertinent to your work as a Payroll Specialist. Discuss how you file tax payments either electronically or by mail. Finally, discuss how you locate payment amounts. Most likely, these amounts come from your payroll software.", "\"In the last organization I worked for, I was responsible for reporting income and employment taxes withheld from the employees on an Employer's Quarterly Federal Tax Return (Form 941). Then, I deposited these taxes in full to an authorized bank. I was also responsible for filing the FUTA return annually and depositing the related tax funds.\"", "\"Yes, I have been responsible for state and federal tax payments, in collaboration with my employers' tax accountants and CPAs. As the liaison for payroll with Company ABC, I have taken on the responsibility of ensuring company compliance for the past ten years, ensuring we remain in compliance with all state and federal tax laws.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Do you plan to open up your own accounting or payroll firm?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know if you view this job opportunity as a stepping stone to your own business endeavors or if you plan to stay with their organization for the long term. Show the employer that you are excited about this opportunity, and you look forward to being on their team for the foreseeable future. Display enthusiasm to learn and grow with the organization, and mention that you are grateful for the opportunity to discuss the Payroll Specialist position.", "\"I have been looking for an opportunity to learn and grow with a larger organization that will offer me the chance to prepare payroll reconciliations at a larger scale. I work well with a diverse team of experts, so, for that reason, owning my own consultancy or working independently does not interest me. I am truly excited about this opportunity with Company XYZ, and plan on growing with your esteemed team for many more years to come.\"", "\"I am new to my career as a Payroll Specialist and it's important to me that I contribute to a team for at least ten years before considering any independent work. It's essential that I contribute to a team while learning and growing from superiors who can teach me the foundations of this role. Right now, and far into the future, it is my greatest interest to be part of a talented team like this one.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Have you performed bookkeeping for small businesses? If so, walk me through your experience.", "answers": ["The interviewer wants you to walk them through your experience working within or consulting as a bookkeeper for a small business. If you have this experience, share how many employees were on staff, the industry of the company, and how you supported their bookkeeping or accounting needs. If you have experience in both small and large work environments, mention any key differences you recognize between small businesses and larger organizations.", "\"I started my career with a small organization, where I was required to perform basic bookkeeping tasks. I was responsible for keeping employee hours and retaining documents for transactions. When I moved to a bigger organization, the bookkeeping tasks were handled by my coworker; however, I continued to keep track of employee- transactions in my department.\"", "\"Near the beginning of my career, I worked as an independent bookkeeper for a smaller, privately-owned dental clinic. I maintained ledgers, recorded transactions, and produced a variety of financial reports for the primary accountant. This experience helped me to gain a solid understanding of the foundations of accounting and payroll while teaching me a great deal about the importance of organization and attention to detail.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Describe your familiarity with the administration of 403b and 457 plans.", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear about your experience administering 403b plans as well as 457 plans.  Share roughly how many employees you have participating in each type of plan, how you utilize your vendor's website to administer the plans, any audits you have been through with each plan, and any additional details that will add value.  \n\nIf you do not have any experience with 403b or 457 plans, tell the employer that although you do not possess this experience, you understand the purpose of these plans.", "\"I understand that a 403b is a special retirement plan typically seen in public schools, tax-exempt organizations, and churches. Alternately, 457 plans are typically seen for governmental employees and independent contractors. The 457 is unique because there is no tax penalty for early withdrawals, and independent contractors may participate. I have a strong level of familiarity with each type of plan.\"", "\"While completing my accounting degree, I briefly learned about 403b and 457 plans; however, I could certainly deepen my knowledge on these topics. During my recent internship, together with the financial controller, I helped with the administration of 403b and 457 plans. We managed the plan contributions with the carrier and our deductions on the payroll end. I look forward to learning more about the administration of these plans with Company XYZ.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Tell me about the payroll forecasting you have been responsible for.", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to understand details around the payroll forecasting you have completed, including how often you have supplied forecasts and who has typically requested the forecasts. Provide details around a recent payroll forecast as a way to support your work through an example. Mention how you gathered your data, what software you utilized for pulling the information, and how you created your projections. Finally, be sure to include who the data was presented to and how you presented it (Excel, Word, email, in-person presentation).", "\"When I was working for Company ABC, the company's finance department requested an estimate of the company's yearly expenses. At the time, I was responsible for providing the organizations' yearly payroll forecast. For the past 4 years, I have been using the yearly employee salary data and forecasts regarding future hires required by other departments. For this provision, I use Excel along with our company's internal system for payroll calculations.\"", "\"My payroll forecasting experience extends to my formal education and my current internship. At Company ABC, we utilize our reporting system to forecast weekly payroll funds, hours, and various payments, taking into account the financial cycle and compensation bonus packages.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What cost-cutting measure have you been in charge of implementing?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants you to discuss the largest, most impressive, cost-cutting measure you have been in charge of. Start by discussing who identified the initiative and how you were selected to lead the implementation. Then, provide a brief overview of the cost-cutting measure, and give an overview of the steps you took during the implementation. Be sure to mention the positive result that was generated following the implementation.", "\"While working at Company ABC, the Payroll Director asked us to look for opportunities to cut costs associated with running payroll. The first thing I did was stop using paper whenever possible. I introduced a new digital process and started to scan copies rather than fax or print them. My co-workers followed suit, and this action reduced paper-related expenses by 49% in just one month. The Payroll Director applauded our efforts, and other departments took notice, working to implement these actions, as well.\"", "\"I have taken on many cost-cutting measures throughout my career. As a payroll professional and a keen 'numbers person,' I am always looking at costs and thinking of creative ways to generate savings for my employer.  For instance, I recently realized that it made sense to bundle our payroll and benefits providers into one solution, saving us $4.50 per employee each payroll cycle. In an organization made up of over 5,000 associates, this will save the company hundreds of thousands of dollars over time.\"", "\"Our company was using an expensive courier at the time, which cut into our profit margin. I proposed to the boss that we switch to a less costly courier for payroll delivery, which ultimately improved our profit margin. That year, I was offered a 30% share of the net profit increase due to this and other profit-boosting implementations.\"", "Good for you! It must have felt very rewarding for you to receive this recognition and be offered a portion of the company's savings."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Walk me through your payroll experience.", "answers": ["This is a comprehensive and very direct question. The key is to provide a high-level overview of your experience. You will want to walk the interviewer through your resume, pointing out highlights of your work and accomplishments that you know relate most to this new opportunity. Tell the interviewer how many years you have been working in a payroll function, the systems you have used, how many employees you have conducted payroll for, the industries you have work in, and any other details that you believe the hiring company will deem important. Be sure to highlight any promotions and accolades you have received along the way.", "\"I have been working in a payroll function for the past 20 years. I started my journey as an intern and am currently employed as a Senior Payroll Manager after receiving several promotions for my performance. During this time, I have primarily used ADP, QuickBooks, Sage, and Paychex. I have handled payroll runs for 50 to 5,000 employees. At Company ABC, I implemented a new timesheet system for recording employee hours which saved the organization thousands of dollars in time and savings. I am comfortable taking control of payroll and troubleshooting issues that arise. I understand that your organization is looking for someone who can jump in, create efficiencies, and find opportunities for cost savings. This is one of my areas of strength and I look forward to putting my experience to work for this organization.\"", "\"I started working in payroll 8 years ago in the automotive industry and then moving to the manufacturing industry. Over these years I worked with Paychex and ADP. I have inputted, managed, audited, and streamlined the payroll process for up to 3,000 employees and have managed payroll runs upwards of $30,000.  Today, my involvement spans from running payroll, training junior payroll clerks on the front end to reconciling the financials with the accounting team on the back end.\"", "\"I am a former Payroll Manager with three years of experience in a wide range of areas in payroll, including but not limited to payroll production/maintenance and management, employment tax depositing/reporting, and regulation compliance. I have primarily used Pensoft, but I am familiar with ADP Workforce Now and QuickBooks. Working for a payroll provider, I have conducted payroll for a total estimate of 1,000 employees and have had 4 people in my department, including me. I was promoted to Payroll Supervisor within 8 months and Payroll Manager within 14 months of my job.\"", "Excellent overview! You did a great job walking through your career highlights and successes. This answer is full of qualifying statements, which is a smart approach."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "How did you get started in a payroll-related career?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know more about your interest in payroll and why you chose a career in payroll.  \n\n- Maybe you took a payroll class in high school, and it intrigued you. \n- Perhaps your parent or guardian worked in a similar function, and you found interest in what they did for a living. \n- Maybe you had a teacher who encouraged you to pursue a career in accounting or payroll because of your detail-oriented nature and keenness in numbers and problem-solving. \n\nWhatever your path, be excited to share it! Discuss any related education and training you have completed along the way. This information will solidify your interest and commitment to your payroll career.", "\"I started my career as a cashier in a big department store. Over time, I was promoted to Floor Manager, then Assistant Store Manager, and finally - Store Manager. I earned these promotions based on my dedication to the job and my keen attention to detail. My cash counts were always accurate, and I helped other cashiers balance their registers at the end of the day. As the Store Manager, I grew a strong interest in payroll responsibilities. From this interest, I decided to pursue an education in accounting, which my company helped fund since their tuition program extended to those in management roles. Once I completed my accounting education, the same department store hired me to work in their payroll processing department. I have been with this employer for 10 years now, and they have provided me with so much opportunity. Now, I am ready to move forward into a payroll position that encompasses an industry outside of retail where I can learn more complex payroll runs and related accounting duties.\"", "\"My initial career interests were in Accounting and Human Resources. In my first professional role as an HR Coordinator, I was responsible for daily payroll management. I found the responsibilities to be fascinating and a great combination of the two areas of business that interested me; HR and finance. I've continued my career in payroll for the past nine years and enjoy adding value to my employer by delivering a smooth process each payroll cycle.\"", "\"I graduated with a Bachelor of Science degree in Business Administration, but I always had an aptitude for numbers and high attention to detail. I got hired by a payroll provider, and that was when I realized my passion for ensuring accuracy in payment processing. I thought about the criticality of timely and accurate processing and how people's livelihoods depended on it, which was what cemented my love for payroll.\"", "Well done! It's apparent that you care about your work and the people who are impacted positively by your accuracy. Your overview is straightforward and focuses on the highlights, which is great!"]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What information do you require before you approve payroll?", "answers": ["Each organization will likely have different controls in place before approving payroll.  Of course, you will need all timesheets approved, compensation changes entered, bonuses allocated, relocation assistance entered, and any other special data for the week addressed.  Be sure to mention these items in addition to what your current process is.  You may have a checklist built into your payroll software, or perhaps you have a checklist in place; be sure to mention these tools too.", "\"It depends on the methodology we are using to calculate the payroll for the employees. If we have a payroll system in place, we always have a ready-to-use checklist, and we need to ensure that all the items in the checklist are in place. But, if there is no system and we have to do it on our own, I prefer using Excel and have my own checklist of items according to which I usually need all timesheets approved, compensation changes entered, bonuses allocated, relocation assistance entered, and any other special data for the week addressed. In the organization that I currently work, we use a payroll system, so we have a checklist that we follow.\"", "\"I take a close look at everything before approving payroll, including the total number of hours, paid time off, bonus and commission payouts, and more. I also look at reported expenses and match them against expected expenditures. It is my duty to take the payroll process seriously, which means ensuring all necessary checks have been carried out and all procedures are followed to the letter.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "There are times when we are placed under extreme pressure on the job. Tell about a time when you were under such pressure and how you handled it.", "answers": ["Payroll is a field with sharp deadlines and high expectations of precision and accuracy. The interviewer wants to hear that you handle the pressure of working as a Payroll Specialist without getting worked up emotionally when roadblocks occur. \n\nThink about a time when you had a pressure-filled day. Prepare to tell your story-based example using the STAR answer method, an acronym for Situation, Task, Action, Result. Describe what made the day complex and pressure-filled and what your responsibilities were in this situation. Next, tell the interviewer how you tackled the stressful situation. Finally, wrap up your response by sharing the positive result of your actions.", "\"While working as a Payroll Manager for Company ABC, my director delegated tasks related to timesheet entries to one of our newer team members. By the end of the month, we received an intimation from the accounts department that they had not received the calculations from our side till that date. This information was delayed by four days. Without further delay, I jumped in and worked overtime to ensure that the information was received before the consequences became dire. I ensured timely salary calculations, and no paycheck delays were caused. My job as a Payroll Specialist is essential as many employees rely on my work for timely disbursement of their salaries.\"", "\"As a payroll processor, we were trained to complete one payroll before moving on to the next. However, on semimonthly days, I had to complete an enormous amount of direct deposits for each company before 12 PM. It was 11 AM, and I realized I didn't have enough time to accomplish it the traditional way. I felt the pressure, but I reassured myself by tending to the most urgent and necessary objectives that needed to be completed first. That was when I created a new system of completing only the direct deposit portion first for each payroll until all direct deposits were completed before the cutoff and coming back to the remaining steps of the process later. All payrolls were completed on time, and I delivered quality service.\"", "You tell this story well - and it's clear that you have done your research on how to formulate and organize responses to behavioral-based interview questions.", "\"We had a change in government and the country's new president wanted all public sectors to be audited.  We were required to produce a 10-yr wage bill for over 800 staff within 7 business days. It was a bit challenging, because some of the data wasn't backed up in the software and I had to source for it manually. I immediately mobilized a small team and disseminated duties amongst us; we worked overtime and weekends to be able to meet up, and we were able to deliver within 5 business days.\"", "Very good! This sounds like a very high-pressure situation, indeed. Your answer is straightforward, and you organize the response very well, allowing the interviewer to easily follow along."]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "We spend considerable time editing our timesheets to ensure no errors are present. How do you approach finding and fixing an error?", "answers": ["Timesheet mistakes will occasionally happen, but that is why you are diligent with checking and editing. Sometimes timesheet errors are 'one and done' situations where you correct the issue move on. Other times, errors occur regularly. In these cases, discuss how you collaborate with your team and troubleshoot to ensure that the issue is fixed so that it does not continue to cause payroll problems in the future.", "\"In payroll, we do account for human error, which occurs when tasks are manual. I do work to automate as many tasks as possible so that our team can avoid unnecessary timesheet errors. I always check the timesheets for errors in advance. If I find an error, I check with the appropriate person or department manager for clarification and then make the necessary adjustments. If the situation occurs regularly, I will work directly with the involved individuals to train them on the current inputs so that their situation does not continue to occur.\"", "\"From what I understand, timesheet errors can be quite common. While completing my practicum with Company ABC, very few payroll tasks were automated. This meant there was more room for human error. Proper timekeeping is crucial to a company, the employees and by law, so it is important that errors are corrected in a timely fashion. If I notice frequent errors from a common denominator, I will work with that team member or department lead to ensure training at the source.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "What is retro pay?", "answers": ["This basic question will allow the interviewer to gauge your level of experience and knowledge in payroll. It will also show the interviewer your ability to explain an accounting-related term in a way that anyone can understand. People can clearly explain concepts they genuinely understand, after all! Your response should be straightforward and to the point.", "\"Retro pay happens when an employee receives a pay increase. In this instance, there is a date the new rate of pay begins. Sometimes this is not communicated to payroll in time for the new paycheck cycle, so we 'retro pay' the employee for wages that should have been received at the newly updated pay rate.\"", "\"Retro pay is retroactive payment for a service or work, typically when payment is overlooked or an error takes place. Retro pay will correct the payment and make the change retroactive to the appropriate effective date.\""]}, {"topic": "Payroll+Specialist", "question": "Can you describe the use of forms W2, W4, and 941?", "answers": ["The interviewer is looking for evidence that you understand the uses of these basic payroll forms. Provide a high-level overview of each of these forms. The way you answer this question will allow the interviewer to gauge your level of experience and knowledge in payroll. It will also show the interviewer your ability to explain an accounting-related term in a way that anyone can understand. Your response should be straightforward and to the point.", "\"W2 form is an IRS mandated form that employers must supply to each employee at the beginning of each calendar year which shows annual earnings, taxes withheld, tips, etc.  This is the form employees utilize for their personal income taxes each year. A W4 is a form that employees complete to tell the employer the amount of taxes to withhold from their paycheck. The employee identifies their marital status as well as the number of exemptions they would like to claim. A 941 is a document related to the employer's quarterly federal tax payment. This form shows the employer's portion of federal income taxes, Medicare tax, and social security tax. I am well versed in each of these forms.\"", "\"I learned about each of these forms while completing my Payroll Compliance education. From my understanding a W2 form is an IRS mandated form that shows annual earnings, taxes withheld, tips, and more for each employee.  An employee completes a W4, telling the employer the amount of taxes they would like withheld from their paycheck. A 941 form shows the employer's portion of federal income taxes, Medicare tax, and social security tax.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How have you monitored, or would you monitor, the performance of your team?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer what you have done or would do to monitor and ensure your team's performance.", "\"I haven't monitored the performance of any team, however, I would meet up with them on a regular basis to ensure they are meeting all expectations, and would conduct performance reviews should expectations not be met. The performance reviews would address areas needing improvement and a timeline for the employee to prove himself, at which date I would meet with him/her again to assess his/her improvement.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Tell me whether you ever had a project go over budget, and how you managed the situation.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about a project that you worked on, and which went over budget, if that applies to you. Provide examples of what you did to manage the situation. In the event this never happened to you, tell the interviewer what you did to stay within budget.", "\"I have never had to manage a project that went over budget as I always do my best to anticipate future expenses. However I realize unforeseen circumstances can occur. It is why I attempt to take unanticipated expenses into account when strategically calculating upcoming costs so as to be able to cover these expenses right away.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "What areas of accounting do you consider your strongest and which ones are you the most passionate about?", "answers": ["Answer this question by providing your strongest areas in accounting and the ones you are the most passionate about, and why.", "\"The areas of accounting I consider my strongest are [X areas], as I have had a lot of experience in these areas in my last position at [X company] as an [X last position title]. As you can see on my resume, I was responsible for [X duties related to strongest areas]. I am also very passionate about [X areas of accounting]; I studied these areas thoroughly in school and these are some I would really like to gain further experience in.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How would you handle disputes with other employees in different departments about costs?", "answers": ["This answer provides information as to your conflict resolution skills. Answer this question by outlining how you would take your colleagues points of view into consideration while respectfully expressing your position.\n\nIt is important to always remain respectful notwithstanding the disputes  and always keep the company's best interests in mind.", "\"I would listen to my colleagues to take their position into consideration, and would then politely explain my own position. The goal is for all team members to feel they are being heard, that they matter, and for the dispute to be resolved in a timely fashion.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Have you ever worked on a project that lasted multiple years?", "answers": ["Provide an answer that provides an accurate representation of your unwavering commitment and enthusiasm for work spanning several years, as well as the ongoing provision of high quality work.", "\"At [X company], I was responsible for the management of all related duties pertaining to [X project] over a 3-year period. I thoroughly enjoyed working on such long-term project as it enabled me to completely immerse myself and become the number one expert in all company matters. I furthermore enjoyed the strong relationship established with the client and was grateful for the level of trust he had in me and my work. I ensured to never take my duties for granted, always conducting my due diligence on a regular basis and making sure I learned all current and upcoming areas relevant to the project.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Where do you see yourself in 5 years from now, or where would you like to be?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer your career goals in 5 years from now, e.g., where you see yourself, the position you would like to hold, whether you would be interested in keeping the same position for the long term, and so on. \n\nAnswer by emphasizing your desire to commit to one employer and grow within the organization. This will demonstrate your commitment to one organization and that you will not leave for a better opportunity.", "\"In 5 years, I hope to have grown within the same company and moved to a position involving more managerial duties, e.g., such as working as a Team Leader, which will enable me to have a greater impact on the success of the company. I wish to commit to one employer and have a long-term career as opposed to a job.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "What steps do you take to keep a project within budget?", "answers": ["Provide the steps you took or would take to ensure the success of a project.", "\"I use a strategic approach by anticipating, and keeping track of, all upcoming expenses. I keep a record of all receipts and update my reports on a regular basis to ensure the most up-to-date information is easily accessible, enabling me to be prepared should an unanticipated expense be required.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "What differentiates you from other accountants?", "answers": ["Answer by emphasizing your greatest strengths against the advertised position. What do you pride yourself on the most? Which strengths will be, in your opinion, most beneficial to this role? Which will contribute to the company's success? Which strengths make you indispensable?", "\"I am a hard worker who does not hesitate to go above and beyond to ensure successful completion of projects, and I am more than willing to take on duties beyond my original job scope. I sincerely believe the company's success is my success.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Provide an example of a project you had to complete in a short period of time, and what you did (alternatively, would do) to successfully complete the project in a timely fashion.", "answers": ["Your answer must provide information as to your time management skills and ability to work under pressure. \n\nAnswer this question by giving an example of a project which you have demonstrated your ability to prioritize, manage your time and go above and beyond to ensure successful project completion. What did you do differently? Did you delegate? Did you work longer hours? Do you enjoy working on such projects?", "\"I completed [X project] in one week even though I had a 2-week timeline. I managed to do so by prioritizing - by identifying which other duties part of my workload were less pressing so as to delegate these duties. I was then able to completely focus on this project and did not hesitate to stay after hours when necessary. I am someone who thrives on challenges and this was a very rewarding project.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about yourself generally and your accounting experience specifically.", "answers": ["Provide an overview of your professional experience while putting emphasis on your accounting experience as per the advertised position, proving you indeed have the qualifications required for this position. \n\nReview the job description before your interview and answer this question by selecting some of the main duties on the posting and telling the interviewer you have performed these duties in the past, when and how.", "\"I pursued a Bachelor's degree in Accounting at UCLA and upon graduation I worked as an Accounting Intern. As an intern, I learned quite a bit about professionalism, confidentiality, working with a team, and working carefully and efficiently. I took it upon myself to take the initiative on extra tasks and always made myself available to help out with projects. I am easy to get along with and take direction and feedback very well. I am ready to take the next step in my career and continue to learn from your team. In my personal life, I am involved with an animal shelter in the community, and I currently have a foster dog. I love being outdoors and exploring with friends.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Please tell me a few of your greatest strengths.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer your greatest strengths which will benefit you in this position specifically.", "\"I am a quick learner, a hard worker and I am incredibly persistent. I do not hesitate to go above and beyond to get the work done, and I am more than available to work after hours if necessary to meet deadlines.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Why did you choose to pursue a career in accounting?", "answers": ["Provide an answer as to the reasons that led you to pursue a career in accounting, and link this answer to the position you are applying for - so as to demonstrate your chosen career field/original career goal is in line with this role.", "\"I decided to pursue a career in accounting because I [X reasons for pursuing that career, such as loving numbers and opportunity to independently manage accounts]. I sincerely feel the position I applied for is a perfect fit as I will be solely responsible for the success of the project and will be able to use my accounting skills and love of numbers on a daily basis.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How do you stay organized as an accountant?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your organizational skills as it pertains to the position you are applying for.", "\"I use to-do lists to keep track of my duties for the day, and prepare to-do lists for the following day each afternoon before leaving for the day. I also set reminders to be reminded of important meetings and deadlines.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How will working for us help you reach your professional goals?", "answers": ["Answer this question by telling the interviewer what seems great about the company, e.g., their services, initiatives, growth opportunities, and so on. \n\nMake sure to answer by providing evidence that you did your due diligence before the interview (e.g., by mentioning something exciting you saw on the job posting, company website or social media pages), which demonstrates you are serious about working for this employer specifically and are not simply looking for any job. Link this evidence to your professional goals proving this position was made for you and it is one in which you will excel. \n\nFor instance, you can point to their seemingly friendly company culture as per some specific programs or initiatives you came across on their website, and say how friendly and how much of a team-player you are - and that this is exactly the type of work environment you are looking for.", "\"I saw on your website that your company is participating in the Run for the Cure benefiting the Breast Cancer Foundation. This is a great initiative contributing to the company morale by strengthening relationships while giving back to the community. I always seek the opportunity to demonstrate my team playing skills and hope to work with colleagues I will consider part of my family.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "To confirm I have the most updated copy of your resume in hand, please confirm your highest degrees granted and the years of obtention.", "answers": ["Answer this question by mentioning all degrees granted and the years of obtention.", "\"I received my Bachelor's degree in Accounting from UCLA in December 2011, and my MBA from McGill University in April 2016.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Describe the systems you have in place for keeping track of assignments given to staff members.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about the tools you use to keep track of the duties of your team members to ensure you are always on track.", "\"I use a combination of staff folders, to-do lists and reminders to be reminded of deadlines and meetings I need to have with my team to ensure everyone is on track and that we are meeting deadlines.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Where do you see yourself in 2 to 3 years from now, or where would you like to be?", "answers": ["Provide an honest answer and do not hesitate to mention you would be open to eventually moving up the ladder should the opportunity arise, i.e., that growth opportunities will be more than welcome. \n\nThis will demonstrate you have leadership skills, a willingness to learn beyond your original job scope, and a desire to commit to your employer.", "\"I see myself working for the same employer, being established and having grown with the organization and contribute to the bottom line. I hope to keep learning and being given the opportunity to prove myself as a valuable team member.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How do you determine accurate labor costs for a particular employee that has worked on several projects?", "answers": ["Answer this question by providing information as to your organizational and project management skills.", "\"I always keep all relevant information pertaining to each employee up-to-date, including charts for each employee and detailed information pertaining to their related projects, and I generate and save new reports on a weekly basis. In that particular case, I would generate an up-to-date report including the projects the employee has worked on, for a given period of time, and gather the relevant documentation I had already saved.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Tell me what your greatest weakness is, and what you are doing to improve yourself in that area.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer your greatest weakness which can nevertheless benefit you in this position.", "\"I am sometimes overly independent and incredibly meticulous as I am used to completing projects on my own instead of delegating them, to complete them in a quicker fashion. But I came to realize that I am working as part of a team of highly educated individuals who are as capable as I am and whose perspective can be greatly valuable. As such, I try to seek my colleagues' input as much as possible as we are all working to benefit the company.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Please provide an example of a situation you were in with a difficult and/or dissatisfied client and how you resolved the situation.", "answers": ["It is important to remain calm, polite and respectful towards the client notwithstanding the difficulty of the situation and your frustration, and to always act as a professional representative of the company.\n\nTell the interviewer that you know you ought to answer clients to the best of your ability, and should you be unable to completely resolve the situation, the best course of action is to forward this client to a superior.", "\"While working at a call center during my undergraduate studies, a client called me when I was working overtime and my superior was out of the office. He was very frustrated because he couldn't access his emails through his company portal. I did my best to listen to him, let him vent and acknowledge his problem. I helped him to the best of my abilities, based upon the training I had received, and when I realized I was not in a position to resolve his issue, I tried to reach out to some of my colleagues to see whether they had encountered such issue. Ultimately, I explained to the client a supervisor would be in touch with him first thing Monday morning, and provided my extension for him to contact me should he not hear back in a timely fashion. I always ensure to remain respectful even if the clients are extremely frustrated and to take their problems seriously. I also always follow up to ensure their issues have been resolved and that they are satisfied with the services received.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "What is an audit query?", "answers": ["Provide an answer as to the definition, purpose of an audit query and example of a query in a given situation.", "\"An audit query is [X definition as per your knowledge] and its purpose is [purpose as per your knowledge]. For instance, an audit query can be conducted in [X and X] contexts.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How would you come to a resolution disputing material costs for a project that you shared materials with?", "answers": ["Provide an answer outlining your team-playing and dispute resolution skills.", "\"I would suggest to my colleagues that we meet so as to present to each other evidence of the material costs for each of us. I would sit down with all parties involved and respectfully listen to what my other team members have to say in that regard. I would then provide my own evidence related to the material costs so that we can efficiently resolve this dispute while we are all face-to-face. It is better to discuss in person than via emails to minimize any miscommunication and quickly resolve all issues so as to move on to the next project.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How do you prioritize when you have multiple deadlines to meet?", "answers": ["Answer this question by providing evidence of your time management skills.", "\"I frequently work on multiple projects simultaneously, which I throughly enjoy. To make sure I meet deadlines, I identify the most pressing project and use to-do lists and a calendar to keep track of all upcoming duties and important events. I review my list every morning and at the end of each day to ensure the duties assigned were completed in a successful fashion. I also do not hesitate to work overtime if necessary.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How do you stay on top of regulation changes in the financial industry?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to ensure you keep yourself updated of changes in the industry to remain current, highly knowledgeable and at the top of your field.", "\"I follow [X organizations] on social media, subscribe to [X newsletters/publications] and attend conferences and seminars, such as [X].\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "On a scale of 1 to 10, rate your proficiency level with respect to Quickbooks, Sage and Simply Accounting.", "answers": ["Honestly rate yourself on a scale of 1 to 10. Should you not be proficient in a certain area, tell the interviewer you love to learn and are more than willing to undertake training. Always provide a truthful answer.", "\"For Quickbooks, I would rate myself 10/10, 8/9 for Sage and 8 1/2 for Simply Accounting.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Please confirm when you received your Certified Public Accountant (CPA) or Certified Management Accountant (CMA) designation, or alternately when you plan on receiving one of these designations.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer whether you already received any of these designations and when, or when you will be receiving them.", "\"The expected obtention date for my Certified Public Accountant (CPA) designation is [X month and X year].\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "What is the largest portfolio you have been responsible for, preferably in a project accounting capacity?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about the largest portfolio you have been responsible for in your career, particularly as it pertains to the role you are applying for, in this case project accounting so as to demonstrate you already have the skills required for this role. \n\nIf you cannot provide an example in a project accounting capacity, answer by mentioning a portfolio managed in another capacity to prove your skills will be transferable. In this case, provide more than one example to ensure the interviewer will have no doubt you can do the job.", "\"I do not have experience managing portfolios in accounting projects, however, I have managed numerous portfolios in my career. For example, at [X company], I worked as an [X position title] and I was responsible for managing portfolios worth [X$]. I also managed a portfolio worth [X$] for [X company name] and [X$] for [X company name].\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Are you planning to obtain your masters' degree (where applicable, i.e., if not already listed on your resume)?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer whether you are planning to obtain your master's degree. If so, and should you plan on pursuing it on a part-time basis, tell the interviewer by saying it will not interfere with your work and that you will remain committed to the employer.", "\"I am planning to obtain my master's degree effective Fall 2017, however on a part-time basis. I applied for your advertised position as I am serious about this role and sincerely believe it is the one that will meet my professional goals. Pursuing my master's degree will not interfere with my commitment to you as I will be attending classes and studying on a part-time basis in the evening and over the weekend.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about your experience with a difficult superior. How did you handle the situation?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your experience with a difficult superior and how you handled the situation.", "\"I once worked with a superior who did not provide any timeline for the projects he assigned to me, yet became extremely agitated when I did not deliver within a few hours. As I had no idea he had such timelines in mind, I requested a meeting with him to tell him about my concerns and that I can absolutely adjust to tight deadlines, however I require prior adequate notice so that I can organize my days accordingly and delegate other duties if necessary - and that I cannot anticipate he would want something done right away upon receipt. He told me he did not realize he had provided unclear instructions and promised to be more clear in the future, which he were.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "What do you do to improve the communication channels within a team?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer a few strategies to improve the communication channels within a team. The emphasis should be on human contact, i.e., meeting fave-to-face as opposed to exchanging  endless emails or using other impersonal mediums.", "\"I prefer meeting in person to talk about a project as opposed to exchanging back-and-forth emails to ensure the exchange of a clear message. Communication can easily be distorted in an email. An in-person meeting also enables the sharing of ideas and promotes true human interactions. However, if I absolutely have to communicate via email, I will do so and then follow up over the phone or in-person to ensure that the recipient understands my message and that we really are on the same page - and that we won't have to start all over again.\""]}, {"topic": "Project+Accountant", "question": "How have you implemented the recent tax changes in your company?", "answers": ["Answer this question honestly to the best of your ability as this pertains to a specific area of the employment opportunity. If you are inexperienced in that area, say so by putting emphasis on your desire to learn and willingness to train.", "\"I have not implemented tax changes in any company, however I am a quick learner and am more than willing to receive training in any area requiring advanced knowledge as my employer will deem necessary.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "While attending University, what was your favorite course and why?", "answers": ["What was your best course, and why was it so? Talk to the hiring manager about your best post-secondary course.", "\"My best course while attending my post-secondary education was Management Accounting and Control. I feel that I did so well because the Professor was very interesting. I really enjoyed learning about budgeting, organizational architecture, product costing and decision making.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "What do you know about our company?", "answers": ["Display that you have researched the company prior to your interview. Talk to the interviewer about your findings.", "\"I have researched your company a great deal prior to the interview and I was also familiar with your firm prior to applying as well. What I enjoy most about your company is your clean reputation in this city. Your brand is a great one and the level of customer service is impressive.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "If hired, how do you intend on making a difference with our company?", "answers": ["Making a difference quickly after being hired is really important to the interviewer. How will you do this?", "\"I plan to make a difference with your company right away by bringing my organizational and strong corporate accounting skills to you. I have the ability to influence clients and mentor staff which I plan to utilize in order to make an impact on your firm immediately.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Why did you choose to pursue a career as an Accountant?", "answers": ["Talk to the hiring manager about how you came to choose Accounting as your career path. You can make the answer a bit personal if you wish.", "\"Growing up, my father was an Accountant and my mother was a bookkeeper. I always took an interest in problem solving and numbers. Accounting was a natural career for me to pursue.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Do you work well on a team? How do you define teamwork?", "answers": ["As an Accountant, much of your work will likely be independent but some project teamwork will be required. Talk to the hiring manager about your ability to work as part of a team.", "\"I am a strong team player and will often take on a leadership role when given the opportunity. To me, teamwork means that everyone ensures that the project is running smoothly by doing their part. On larger projects that require teamwork I feel it is always best to utilize each individuals' strengths and have them feel accountable for their work.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Would you consider yourself a beginner, intermediate or expert user in Excel?", "answers": ["Tell the hiring manager about your level of comfortability with Excel. Have you been tested recently on your Excel abilities? If so, you can certainly talk about that.", "\"Recently I was given the opportunity to test my skills in Excel when I was being considered for an opportunity through a placement agency. They tested me on my Excel skills and I came out as an expert level user.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "What are your short-term career goals as an Accountant?", "answers": ["Talk to the hiring manager about the type of growth that you would like to see in your immediate career. Discuss why this is important to you and what you plan to do to get there.", "\"My short term career goal is to complete my CPA. I have just one course remaining. This will allow me to take on even more senior accounting tasks in the near future.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Would you consider yourself a beginner, intermediate or expert user in QuickBooks?", "answers": ["Tell the hiring manager about your level of comfortability with QuickBooks. Have you been tested recently on your QuickBooks abilities? If so, you can certainly talk about that.", "\"Recently I was given the opportunity to test my skills in QuickBooks when I was being considered for an opportunity through a placement agency. They tested me on my QuickBooks skills and I came out as an Advanced level user.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "What has been the most significant decision you made at work this year?", "answers": ["As a Senior Accountant, you will have to make important decisions on a regular basis. Talk to the hiring manager about the biggest work related decision you have been asked to make.", "\"The most significant decision I have been asked to make this year was when our firm was downsizing. I needed to make recommendations on who to lay off. It was very difficult but I remained diplomatic when making the recommendations.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "How have you monitored the regulations that affect your accounting position?", "answers": ["Discuss with the hiring manager how you keep on top of new regulations that affect the Accounting industry.", "\"I am a member of IFAC and, as such, I am able to stay up to date on new regulations that affect the accounting industry. I am also a strong researcher which helps me to keep on top of the regulations and any changes. \""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "How do you prioritize your work when you have multiple deadlines to meet?", "answers": ["Talk to the hiring manager about how you are able to prioritize your work when there are multiple deadlines present.", "\"When I have multiple deadlines present, I am able to prioritize by keeping a full understanding of what my client is looking for. I realize that all deadlines must be met so I will, of course, work any overtime hours required to meet my deadlines.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Have you ever used an ERP or SAP system before?", "answers": ["Tell the hiring manager about any exposure you have had to SAP or ERP systems. How do you feel that you could improve? Where do you feel your strongest skills are.", "\"Yes, I have used both an ERP and SAP system in my previous roles. I would say that I have approximately 8 years exposure in each. My strongest experience comes with data analysis and documentation through SAP.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about your post-secondary education. What particular Accounting designations do you hold?", "answers": ["Having the proper designations for the role is very important. Tell the hiring manager about your post secondary experience and accounting designations.", "\"I attended my post-secondary education at the University of Florida. Completing my Bachelors of Finance in 2009, I returned to part time studies in 2011 to obtain my CPA.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about a time you handled a complex financial project with a tight deadline that required precise data collection and analysis.", "answers": ["Assure the hiring manager that you are able to meet very tight deadlines on complex projects. Give an example of the project by discussing the clients' needs, any support you have received during the project, what the expectations were, and how you met them."]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Describe to me what qualifications you feel a person applying for this position will need, in order to have the most success?", "answers": ["Tell the hiring manager that you are able to understand the qualifications required to be successful in this position and that you personally possess these qualities.", "\"I feel the qualifications required for this role would be a strong mixture of education and experience. You would really benefit from a candidate who has experience working on more complicated corporate financial portfolio's, which I certainly do.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about your experience as an Accountant.", "answers": ["It's best to start at the beginning of your accounting career, and work your way to your most recent position. Talk about any complicated projects you have worked on, who you have supported, and if you have ever led a team.", "\"I began my career with company XYZ immediately after graduating with my Bachelor's Degree in Finance. I have worked my up from there to a Senior Accountant role with the same company. I primarily work with corporate accounts but do have experience in personal accounting as well.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "How do you stay organized as an Accountant?", "answers": ["Being organized is very important when you are working with numbers and finance. Discuss with the hiring manager how you are able to remain organized on the job.", "\"I stay organized by utilizing all programs provided to me by the firm I currently work for. We use a couple of web based programs that are very easy to use. Also, I ensure that my team meets every day in order to discuss our priorities and upcoming deadlines.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Give me an example where you used your skills to bring down costs for a client.", "answers": ["Tell the hiring manager about a time that you have been able to present cost-savings to a client through the utilization of your accounting skills. Walk them through your example, bringing the situation to life for them.", "\"I am very proud of my ability to bring down client costs through my very thorough analysis process. Last year I was able to save one of my commercial accounts an additional $3500 per month by taking a much closer look at their expenditures and making recommendations for streamlining.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Take me through your latest budget preparation.", "answers": ["Take the hiring manager through your budget preparation steps. Be to the point when giving your answer. If the interviewer would like for you to elaborate on particular steps, they will ask.", "\"My latest budget preparation was a very in-depth project. I began by updating the budget assumptions. Then, reviewed any bottlenecks. Next, I determined whether any step costs existed and then created a budget package.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "What qualifies you for this position, and why should we hire you?", "answers": ["Assure the hiring manager that you are the best possible fit for the role by discussing your qualifications, strengths, and what sets you apart from the others.", "\"In addition to meeting all of the educational experience you are asking for, I also have the additional PMP designation which qualifies me to lead accounting based projects for your firm. This is a unique combination and I feel it is just part of what makes me a stand out candidate.\"", "\"I have years of experience in various accounting roles. I have always been part of the closing process or being responsible for the closing and doing tasks such as completing the period-end close, monthly balance sheet reconciliations, preparing accurate and timely financial statements, review of financial statements for accuracy.\"", "It's nice that you offer up the specific tasks that you are experienced in. Be sure they apply to the job description. I also recommend adding in some soft skills so that your response does not begin to sound like you're just listing off accounting tasks."]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "What is your preferred industry to work in?", "answers": ["Are you a generalist, or do you prefer to be an accountant in a particular industry? Talk to the hiring manager about your industry preference. Be careful not to express interest in an industry that the hiring company does not have work in.", "\"I really do prefer corporate accounting within the hospitality industry. I think this is because I am familiar with the industry and find it easier to uncover unique ways for my clients to leverage their money.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about the latest changes in tax laws.", "answers": ["How do you remain up to date on tax law changes? Talk to the hiring manager about how you ensure that you stay up to date on the latest tax law changes.", "\"I stay up to date on the latest tax laws through subscribing to a variety of finance and accounting related publications such as money.com, Forbes and time.com.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Describe the systems you have in place for keeping track of assignments given to staff members.", "answers": ["Being able to manage the timeline and delivery of multiple assignments is really vital. Talk to the hiring manager about how you remain organized and on track.", "\"Currently, I manage 6 staff members. In order to ensure that all assignments are tracked, I use a web based service called Freedcamp. This allows me to track the stage that each project is in. Everyone can update their progress in office and remotely as well.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "What are your long-term goals as an Accountant?", "answers": ["Talk to the hiring manager about the type of growth that you would like to see in your career, long term. Discuss why this is important to you and what you plan to do to get there.", "\"My long term career goal is to complete my masters' degree in finance. I plan to attend evening and weekend courses. This will allow me to take on even more senior accounting tasks while still remaining employed on a full time basis.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "We require a Senior Accountant with strong technical skills. Are you able to quickly learn new programs?", "answers": ["It is important to be technically savvy. Talk to the hiring manager about your ability to learn new programs and use a variety of software.", "\"I am very savvy when it comes to new technology. Learning new programs and software comes very easily to me. Currently, in my position, I am the Subject Matter Expert when it comes to Excel, Quickbooks and Simply Accounting.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Do you work well under pressure?", "answers": ["As an Accountant, you will often be working on high pressure deadlines. Assure the hiring manager that you are able to be productive even under high pressure situations.", "\"As an Accountant, I am very accustomed to working under very tight and important deadlines. They don't bother me at all and I work quite well under intense conditions.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about your leadership skills. Do you enjoy leading and teaching others?", "answers": ["Are you a natural born leader? Do you enjoy leading a team? Discuss any leadership qualities and experience with the hiring manager. Be sure to use examples of times when you have taken on a leadership role. What was the feedback that you received?", "\"I am a natural leader and I really do enjoy being a leader. I have taken on multiple projects in my current role. Most recently, I was leading a team of 12 junior accountants. The feedback on the project was strong and I felt that the accountants working under me in this project received my guidance openly.\""]}, {"topic": "Senior+Accountant", "question": "How do you control errors in your work?", "answers": ["While working on a project, errors can happen. Talk to the interviewer about how you manage/control these errors.", "\"I am always sure to check in regularly when it comes to the progress of a project. I ensure that my staff members feel comfortable bringing up changes and suggestions to me when they see room for improvement. Having everyone's eye out for required changes and potential errors really helps with controlling any potential mistakes.\""]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What cost-cutting measures have you been responsible for implementing?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear that you are capable of leading department initiatives. Openly share the largest, and most impressive, cost-cutting measure you have been in charge of by sharing who identified the initiative, how you were selected to lead the implementation, providing a brief overview of the cost-cutting measure, and talking through an overview of what steps you took during the implementation. Be sure to mention all of the positive kudos you received following the implementation."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What accounting software packages have you used?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to gain a better understanding of your background to determine the best training you can be provided if you are hired for the position.  Go ahead and list the accounting software packages you have utilized, and describe some of the typical day-to-day functions you were utilizing the software for.", "\"I used QuickBooks during my accounting internship. Also, I used an ERP system called Banner when I was working at College.\"", "It sounds like you have some exposure to accounting software. If you are not sure what is used in this role, it is certainly okay to ask. This way, you can gain a head start in learning the program if it's one that is new to you."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What work objectives did you set for this year and what steps have you taken to ensure you will achieve them?", "answers": ["Interviewers love hearing that you have goals that you are actively working towards.  Think through the goals you have personally set for yourself or projects that you are hoping to complete.  Perhaps these goals will be department-wide instead of personal.  That is okay too!  Go ahead and share 2-3 goals that you have for yourself this year.  Describe your intended deadline, and explain where you are at in the current process.  Be sure to explain what measures you have put in place to keep yourself on track with achieving each goal.", "\"I want to improve my Excel skills this year. I am reviewing my Excel work that I did in college at home.\"", "Nice response! The interviewer should appreciate that you are taking action to improve."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Why are you the best accountant for us?", "answers": ["Talking about ourselves in this way can be challenging. We recommend reaching out to a few colleagues, family members, and friends. Ask them for their opinion. You'll probably be surprised at the consistency in their responses! Their answers will give you the response to the question. Tell the interviewer what sets you apart, and explain how your colleagues, family members, and friends have encouraged you with your gift in this area."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Describe the advantages and disadvantages of the different accounting packages you have used.", "answers": ["The interviewer is hoping to hear that you understand the ins-and-outs of accounting packages.  The key is ensuring you have a positive attitude about any system that is put in front of you.  Think of the pros and cons of the systems you have utilized.  Begin by sharing 3-4 things that you functionally really liked (advantages) about the system.  Next, share one thing you would change if you could (disadvantage) to improve the system."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What motivates you to perform your best?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to learn how you can be encouraged to perform at your best in the workplace. What works best for you? Does having a role model in the department keep you motivated? Are you goal driven? Does working independently keep you motivated? Or, do you prefer working on projects as a team? Simply share what keeps you moving forward with your work each day."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "How proficient are you with Excel?", "answers": ["Be candid with the interviewer sharing if you are a beginner, intermediate, or advanced user of Excel. Then, give a few examples of things you commonly utilize Excel for such as creating charts/graphs, making pivot tables, or analyzing data. Your candid response will help the interviewer understand what type of training you should be provided if you are hired for the role to ensure you will be successful with your assigned tasks."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Are you willing to work overtime, nights, weekends?", "answers": ["Be candid and open with the interviewer expressing what type of availability you have. Be sure to factor in your family's activities, and understand that you may be disqualified from consideration if you are unavailable to work weekends and it is a requirement of the position.  It is better to make this determination during the interview process rather than after starting in the position.", "Wonderful! Any interviewer should appreciate your enthusiasm."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Give me examples of the accounting reports you have prepared.", "answers": ["Start off by listing a handful of reports that you have prepared including a high-level overview of what data can be found in the reports. Expand on this by telling the interviewer how you can manipulate data within your accounting system to generate any reports you are looking for, and mention that you can create reports in many formats including Word, Excel, and Adobe formats."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "If I gave you a ten key pad, and a list of numbers, could you enter them in without looking at the key pad?", "answers": ["Be candid with the interviewer sharing if you would be able to accomplish this task.  Your candid response will help the interviewer understand what training will be necessary if you are selected for the position as well as what workload you can be expected to complete during a given week.  If you have extensive ten key experience, share it!  Explain how long you have been using it as well as how often you were using it each day.", "Wonderful! If appropriate, you can offer to do some testing as well."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What is your greatest weakness? What are you doing to improve it?", "answers": ["Pick one of your weaknesses that is not a necessity for the role. Be candid and humble in your answer recognizing that you really aren't great at something and acknowledging your need to improve. Be sure you have an action plan in place for improving on this weakness too. Perhaps you are watching speakers talk about the weakness, reading the latest-and-greatest book on the subject, or maybe you are taking a seminar at a nearby community center in the near future. We are all human and all have weaknesses, so don't be afraid to share yours!", "\"I am a very focused person, but I tend to sit down and work on the computer for an extended time. \r\nIn my last job, I set the alarm to take a break to refresh my mind. In this way, when I go back to work, I can work more efficiently.\"", "A good example of a weakness, and great job with the action steps you take to make improvements."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Where do you see yourself in 5 years?", "answers": ["Interviewers want to hear that you will be actively involved in the accounting department! Tell the interviewer that you see yourself actively engaged in the organization as a professional member of the accounting team in five years. Explain how you hope you have grown professionally in the department and are viewed as a top-notch leader for the team.  If you have aspirations to be promoted within the department, now is a great time to share them mentioning that you understand it will take several years to accomplish this goal.", "\"My dream is to become a staff accountant. I still want to develop my skills, but I want to involve more volunteer work outside and grow personally.\"", "These are very nice goals! You could also include more details, such as which skills you want to develop and where you would like to volunteer."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "How would your former employer describe you?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to hear that your past employer will describe you in a positive manner. Think about the positive things your former employer has said about you in the past. Instead of listing these things, tell the interviewer what each person has told you. For example, you might say, \"John has told me that I am a hard worker, and he has told me that he really likes how I am always happy to be at work!\" These concrete examples will be sure to impress the interviewer!", "\"John has told me that I am a hard worker, and he has told me that he really likes how I am always happy to be at work!\"", "\"My former employer would describe me as a hard-worker. Also, I am someone who always stays positive and goes the extra mile.\"", "Good for you! These are excellent qualities that any interviewer should appreciate."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What kinds of management reports have you prepared?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to determine if you have experience working with and preparing data for senior staff members.  Begin by sharing if you have experience preparing reports for any staff members mentioning their job titles and the reports that you typically prepared for them.  Then, mention how often you have been preparing these reports as well as the purpose of each report.  Will it be used for a large presentation or a Board meeting?"]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What do you know about our company?", "answers": ["With any job interview, it is crucial to understand the organization you are applying to. We recommend visiting the company website to learn key information such as current seasonal promotions and ongoing events. Watch the videos on their website, and take note of the information on their Careers page if one is available. Come prepared to list 5-6 things you learned from the company's website such as number of locations they have, when the company started, who started the company, mission statement, vision statement, core values, etc...", "\"I see your website, and I like the program that provides a therapeutic classroom for parents.\"", "Go as far as in-depth with the company as you can. This is a great start; however, you will want to give more information."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Tell me about a suggestion or successful contribution you have made in your past job or in college?", "answers": ["Employers are looking for team members who will be actively involved in the department.  How have you been actively involved?  Have you initiated a positive change within the department or on a college project?  Have you thought of a process improvement that was implemented?  Or, have you completed a major project for the team?  Go ahead and share how you have contributed while being actively engaged either in the workplace or in college."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Do you work well under pressure?", "answers": ["Absolutely! The interviewer needs to hear that you can handle a little pressure. Simply tell the interviewer that you are accustomed to meeting deadlines, having a busy workload, and working under pressure. Be sure to mention that you never let pressure get the best of you, and you know how to delegate work to the right people to help you manage your workload when necessary and applicable."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Give us an example of how you have used your creativity to solve a problem on the job.", "answers": ["Interviewers love hearing that you take the initiative to solve a problem!  Think about the problems you have solved within the past year.  Which one required the most creative solution or the most creative problem-solving approach?  Did you have to utilize new resources?  Did you have to reach out to other accountants for possible solutions?  Did your problem require you to put together a committee to come to a resolution?  The key is that you took the initiative to figure out how to solve the problem and had a positive attitude while doing so!  Go ahead and share your unique scenario describing the problem you had to solve, how you approached solving the problem, your resolution, and your positive outcome."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Why have you chosen a career in accounting?", "answers": ["How did you land in the accounting field?  Have you always enjoyed working with numbers?  Did you take a high school or college accounting course that made you interested in the field?  Or, did you have a mentor who encouraged you to pursue the field?  Go ahead and share your story describing what led you to pursue a career in the accounting field."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What are your career goals?", "answers": ["Do you have aspirations to stay in the Staff Accountant role long-term?  Do you hope to become a Manager or VP?  Would you like to transition into Finance and become a Controller?  Do you hope to work for a specific company some day?  Or, do you hope to get your Master's Degree?  Whatever your aspirations may be, go ahead and share them with the interviewer explaining that you understand it may take many years to achieve these goals."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What is your greatest strength? How does it help you as an Accountant?", "answers": ["What things have you repeatedly been complemented for? What are the common positive comments you receive on your performance reviews? These can be great starting points for identifying your greatest strength! Share one of these things with the interviewer stating that others have told you this is your greatest strength. Next, share how this strength will help you as an accountant. You might say something like this, \"I have been told by past managers that my greatest strength is my ability to strike up a conversation with anyone! As an accountant, this will help me build relationships with my clients making us a stronger team.\"", "\"I have been told by past managers that my greatest strength is my ability to strike up a conversation with anyone! As an accountant, this will help me build relationships with my clients making us a stronger team.\"", "\"My boss told me I am methodical. I always take my time; try not to make mistakes. This strength will help me to be successful in this role.\"", "This is an excellent strength to highlight in an accounting interview. Good work!"]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "How have you implemented recent tax changes in your company?", "answers": ["Interviewers want to hear that you keep up-to-date with tax changes.  The first step is describing how you stay in tune with this information.  Do you subscribe to an email service that sends you these updates?  Do you have a third-party that sends you these changes?  After you receive these changes, how do you make the changes happen?  Next, share a couple of recent tax changes that were made, and discuss how you implemented them.  Did your accounting software company automatically make these changes for you?  Did you work with your account representative to make these changes?  Or, did you work together as a team to manually make these changes?"]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "How do you prioritize your work?", "answers": ["Managing your workload is easy for you! What things do you do to ensure you prioritize your work? Do you spend time every Monday morning planning out your work? Do you have a label system on your to-do list to recognize what things are the most urgent? Do you schedule the most urgent tasks on your calendar? Tell the interviewer which methods you utilize on a regular basis to ensure your work remains organized!"]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "How do you handle stressful situations?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer that you understand a Staff Accountant's role involves a lot, but you take it in stride! There are days when you may feel a bit overwhelmed, and you take steps to ensure these situations do not get the best of you. Share that you tend to talk to your co-workers about challenging situations to gain wisdom, and remember that you are a part of a team filled with wise people who are willing to help you out when your workload is not attainable some days."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "What do you consider to be the biggest challenge facing the accounting profession today?", "answers": ["Challenges come with any profession, and the interviewer wants to hear that you are in tune with industry trends.  If you are unsure of the biggest challenge facing the accounting profession today, talk with a few other accounting professionals before arriving for your interview, or check out a copy of a recent accounting magazine for some ideas.  Begin by describing the biggest challenge you see.  Explain what possible options you think the field has to address the challenge, and describe if you have personally seen evidence of this challenge in your career."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "How much money have you saved the company and how did you do this?", "answers": ["Have you had an idea for an efficiency that was implemented?  Have you decreased the amount of late payments the company was making?  Have you implemented a new software system that saved a company time and money?  Think through your work history, and explain the most significant money saving initiative you have been responsible for.  Describe who identified the initiative, how it was recognized, and what steps you took in leading the initiative."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "Are you detail oriented?", "answers": ["Absolutely!  Accountants must be detail oriented, and the interviewer wants to hear that you are confident in your detailed nature.  Begin by sharing that you are a detail oriented person, and explain 2-3 things you do to ensure the details are managed well.  Do you keep checklists to ensure steps in a process are not missed?  Do you color code files to ensure you are processing things correctly?  Sharing your examples will enforce that you are in fact detail oriented."]}, {"topic": "Staff+Accountant", "question": "If hired, how do you intend on making a difference with our company?", "answers": ["Interviewers love hearing that you look forward to improving their company after you have a solid understanding of their culture and current practices. Begin by telling the interviewer that you intend to begin the role gaining an understanding of current practices and spending time observing how things are currently operating. Tell the interviewer that you want to learn the culture and become a part of it. Next, share that once you have an understanding of these things, you will make strategic decisions regarding any possible changes and decisions for the future that will provide the best results for the company."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Tell me about your education.", "answers": ["Since you are working in a data, financial and administrative function, focus on the aspects of your education that will support you in this role. Starting with your college experience, explain how you became interested in doing this type of work. What topics did you enjoy most in school? How did your training prepare you for this role? You can share an example of some of the work you learned to do during training and talk about your technical skills. Share any continuing education or certifications you have received."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What is the most important rule of a treasurer?", "answers": ["What is a guideline you follow that has helped you stay accurate and organized?  When you start a new job, what is the first priority? Learning systems and understanding the current financial status of the company will set you up to be knowledgeable and prepared. Once you're in the position, staying up to date on the financials and being a resource in order to provide sound information to back up decisions are top priority. If you know of a rule that will help you be successful, share it!"]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Tell me about your education. How has it prepared you for a career as a Treasurer?", "answers": ["Provide the interviewer with an overview of your highest level of completed education. If you have attended any recent training seminars or conferences that are directly applicable, feel free to talk about those too! Next, share a few highlights from your education. You might talk about your education preparing you to multi-task and manage a busy workload. You can also consider sharing that your education has provided you with a good foundation, and you understand there will still be things to learn once you are on the job. Be sure to mention that you look forward to learning all that you can!"]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "How do you ensure that confidential information is secure and private?", "answers": ["As you know, you'll be handling confidential information all the time! It's your job. Give an example that proves you are reliable and trustworthy. Your knowledge of how to manage and navigate the software system, contracts and financial documents will instill confidence in your future employer. They want to hear about concrete ways you have handled this type of information so that they know they can trust you with theirs."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What type of accounting/financial experiences do you have?", "answers": ["If you have any trouble talking about your relevant experience, consider framing your response like this: First, discuss your training. If you took courses or received your training from an accredited or well-known entity, share it. Next, talk about your professional experiences. Think about the qualities and strengths required to do the job. How did you express those traits in your previous job? What were some of your greatest accomplishments?"]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Give an example of a time when you made a mistake. How did you handle it?", "answers": ["No one wants to admit weakness in an interview. And you know what? You don't have to! You can explain a situation where you did something wrong or incorrectly. Try to stay detached from it by explaining in a calm manner, \"I accidentally pushed \"send\" on an email before proofing it.\" Now, what did you do once you realized you did something wrong? \"I knew there were typos and I may have phrased something in a way that could be confusing. I called my manager and explained to make sure they didn't take the message the wrong way.\" Show you took initiative in handling it. If the consequences were greater than frustrating your boss or having to apologize, show you handled it by being humble and calm. Next talk about what you learned from it and the actions you will take to make sure it never happens again."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What is your ideal work environment?", "answers": ["Describe the aspects on an office environment that you enjoy most and why. Are you motivated by the positive attitudes of others? Do you thrive when your boss empowers you by giving you autonomy over decisions? It's important to know what you need and what you want out of a work situation. Share some qualities and attributes of the people and environment that you thrive in. Sometimes it's hard to know if the past places you've been employed were not the best for you. Think about an environment where you feel you will learn and grow best and describe that to the interviewer."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Why should we hire you?", "answers": ["Consider the challenges of your future role. How will you go above and beyond to tackle the most difficult tasks? Sharing your accomplishments, skills and characteristics will demonstrate your extensive knowledge and expertise. How have you successfully managed and limited risks? How have you proven yourself reliable and trustworthy to oversee budgets? What qualities do you offer that make you stand out? Review the job description and your resume side by side once more to help you highlight your relevant experience."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "How would you rate your leadership skills?", "answers": ["You are a strong leader with a desire to make a positive impact on others. You have are an influencer in many aspects of your life, but how do you talk about? Working as a treasurer requires you to maintain relationships with creditors, bankers and other financial staff members. In order to influence decisions and earn trust, you will need to set an example. Are you consistent? Do you show up on time? How do you build those important relationships? Give an example of a recent time you successfully led a team or took initiative to solve a problem."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Do you work well under pressure?", "answers": ["Tight deadlines and a manager looking over your shoulder are sure to raise your heart-rate! Stress management and having the ability to calmly and confidently deal with pressure are important skills. Give an example that demonstrates your ability to do this. Here's a sample example:\n\r\n\"Yes, I'm motivated by pressure. Sometimes it helps give me that extra push to complete projects. I stay motivated by setting deadlines on my calendar and milestones for goals I want to achieve, so that I can maintain my momentum each step of the way.\"", "\"Yes, I'm motivated by pressure. Sometimes it helps give me that extra push to complete projects. I stay motivated by setting deadlines on my calendar and milestones for goals I want to achieve, so that I can maintain my momentum each step of the way.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Tell me about your work experience.", "answers": ["Although it may be tempting, try not to list your past jobs in chronological order with all of your responsibilities. Your resume maps out your work history, but it's up to you to highlight your greatest accomplishments. As you prepare for this question, keep the qualifications for this role in mind in order to focus on relevant experience. If you don't have a lot of relevant professional experience, take some time to review your work history. Think about those transferable skills that you got from a volunteer role or administrative job. You can share your last jobs, focusing on the three most recent, and then talk about what you learned, your skills and your achievements."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Tell me about a time when you fell behind your work. How did it happen and how did you catch up?", "answers": ["Be careful not to play the blame game. If you fell behind due to an unexpected circumstance or perhaps your boss piled on a few extra projects, that's okay. As you know, these things happen. Focus on what you did to make up time. Were you willing to work longer hours? Did you recruit extra help?", "\"I got behind on a project due when I got the flu, because I had to miss a couple days of work. I asked a coworker to handle a couple of tasks while I was sick so that when I came back to work I didn't miss any deadlines. I worked late for a few days in order to catch up.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Why have you chosen this career?", "answers": ["What do you enjoy about managing financial information? Why did you choose to be a treasurer rather than a financial adviser? Considering there are so many different career paths within the realm of finance, what led you to where you are now?"]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Tell me about yourself.", "answers": ["What do you want the interviewer to think about you when you leave? Making a good impression will definitely increase your chances of getting a call back. When preparing for this question, consider your past experiences and successes. Think of a few examples you could share. You can also draw upon your strengths, abilities and your current position. What projects are you working on that relate to this new job? What initiatives have you taken to make improvements or motivate your team? This is also a good time to mention any future goals that are relevant to the position."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What decisions are easiest for you to make? What are the most difficult?", "answers": ["You will need to be able to make decisions regarding the financial future of the company. The interviewer is looking for insight into your decision making process. Why are certain decisions more difficult than others? Sometimes the most difficult decisions are the ones you need to make quickly without much time or thought. Do you weigh the pros and cons? If you have been faced with challenging decisions at work, how did you make those decisions? What are the factors you consider?"]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What three words would you use to describe yourself?", "answers": ["Use your insight and self-awareness to prepare for this question. When describing yourself, consider some of your strengths. If you are organized, disciplined and friendly, how do these traits contribute to your ability to make decisions and handle financial data? Although the questions asks about how these words describe you, if you take take it to the next level, you will help the interviewer to see how well you would fit into the role. You want to help them realize how you are the best candidate for the job. Paint a picture of yourself that shows you fit perfectly into their work environment."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What interests you about finance?", "answers": ["What excites you about working in the financial industry? Do you enjoy problem solving and using research and insight to influence financial decisions? Share some of the aspects of the industry that you particularly enjoy. Explain how it allows you to demonstrate your skills and strengths. \n\r\n\"I've always loved math and statistics. It just always made sense to me. I enjoy problem solving and helping companies grow to their potential.\"", "\"I've always loved math and statistics. It just always made sense to me. I enjoy problem solving and helping companies grow to their potential.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What do you know about our organization?", "answers": ["When you take the time to research a company, you gain insight into their values, culture and expectations. You can learn more about their products and successes, which will help you to know if they are the type of company you would want to work for. The more you know, the better you can sell yourself too!  Come prepared to share what you've learned from your research. Your desire to learn about them shows you are invested and you're not just looking for any job. Companies want to see initiative and interest in what they have to offer."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Give me an example that demonstrates your attention to detail.", "answers": ["Attention to detail is vital to your role as a treasurer. You will be investing funds, advising management on policies and financial decisions as well as maintaining systems of policies and behaviors. Show off your precision and accuracy in an example like this: \n\r\n\"When preparing forecasting reports, I am very methodical. I have a process I follow to make sure I am taking into account all the information in order to make accurate and wise recommendations.\"", "\"When preparing forecasting reports, I am very methodical. I have a process I follow to make sure I am taking into account all the information in order to make accurate and wise recommendations.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What does a typical work day look like for you?", "answers": ["Start from the beginning. What's the first thing you do when you get to the office? Explain the tasks you focus on. How do you stay organized? How do you prioritize? You may want to think these questions through in case your interviewer follows up to delve deeper into your answer. The interviewer is looking to make sure you have a clear understanding of the responsibilities. They want to see how you put them into practice on a daily basis."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "If I were to ask your previous employer, what would they say about your job performance?", "answers": ["A fair response to this question would be, \"I did my best to work well with everyone and I always put in 100%. I was consistent, dependable and driven.\" If you did something phenomenal, share it. Just be aware that you only want to share the facts that can be confirmed by anyone on your team your future boss could be in communication with. Highlight your accomplishments and your work ethic. Show off your consistencies and your best traits that were apparent to your previous boss.", "\"I did my best to work well with everyone and I always put in 100%. I was consistent, dependable and driven.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "What are your future goals?", "answers": ["It's important to think about how this position fits into your long term goals even as you apply for jobs. Review your options, career-wise, before your interview. What could you do within the next five years within this role? Would you want to work towards management or moving into another realm of the financial world? If you have plans for trainings, educational courses or projects that could help you grow your career, share those. Think critically about what you really want for your future and share how this role will benefit you by helping you get to the next step."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "How do you ensure accuracy when making projections based on financial data and performance?", "answers": ["This is an opportunity to hone your attention to detail and your process. Like other financial roles, a Treasurer plays an important role in the growth of a company through their financial management and ability to make wise recommendations. Your precision and organization are a couple of skills that will help you in this process. Can you think of a few more? What is your style? What tools help you to do this?"]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "How do you like to be managed?", "answers": ["You may be reporting to the Chief Financial Officer or the owner of the business, so it's important to know what management styles work best for you. Many people prefer someone who is more hands-off, giving you the freedom to make your own decisions. Others may appreciate a little hand-holding in the beginning, preferring a micro-manager. Think about your past managers. What did you like about them? What didn't you like? Make sure you know who you will be reporting to and consider inquiring about their management style. You can also ask what the team is like to get a feel for expectations and how everyone works together."]}, {"topic": "Treasurer", "question": "Tell me about your management experience.", "answers": ["If you have experience with supervising a staff, writing performance reviews, coaching employees, hiring, interviewing, or motivating your team, be sure to mention these things. If you know you'll be responsible for managing or supervising others, talk about how you supervised staff members. What was the experience like for you? How did you handle behavioral issues or conflict? If you do not have management experience, now is the time to be honest about it, and talk about how excited you are to learn. Odds are, the interviewer will ensure you receive more training when you begin your new role because they know you will benefit from the extra knowledge!"]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What is net present value?", "answers": ["Net present value is a common investment term.  It is defined as the value of all future cash flows over the life of an investment, stated in today's dollars.  Be sure to describe what NPV is and how it is used in practice.", "\"Net present value is the value of all future cash flows over the life of an investment, converted into today's dollars.  Net present value is a metric that is used to calculate the economic value of an investment.  It is also a way to convert various investment options into current-day dollars to make comparisons.  In order to calculate, an interest rate must be determined.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What is the working capital ratio and what does it tell about a company\u2019s finances?", "answers": ["The working capital ratio is a common and important way to measure a company's financial liquidity.  The working capital ratio is calculated by dividing current assets by current liabilities.  Higher ratios mean a greater flexibility to expand operations.", "\"The working capital ratio indicates a company's ability to pay off their current liabilities as they become due.  The ratio is calculated by dividing current assets by current liabilities.  A ratio of two or higher would likely indicate that the company is in a good position to pay off its liabilities.  Anything less than one would be considered problematic.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What would you do if you discovered there were accounting transactions that were suspicious or questionable?", "answers": ["This is an opportunity to highlight your integrity and honesty.  The high-level answer should be obvious - that the concern must be addressed immediately.", "\"If I discovered a practice that I found questionable, I would immediately voice my concern to the Treasury Manager.  It could be possible that I am misinterpreting the situation.  If not, my manager would provide good counsel on next steps to resolve the situation.  The most important thing is to be honest and ethical - two character traits that I am proud to say I possess.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What are some methods you use to self-review your work?", "answers": ["The interviewer is trying to evaluate your ability to check your own work and, as a result, save your manager precious time by catching mistakes before they reach his or her desk.  Give specific examples of procedures you have implemented in previous roles to catch mistakes.", "\"Being able to self-review my work and catch mistakes is something I take very seriously.  As a treasury analyst, I'll be spending a lot of time working in the details, which makes it difficult to catch errors.  Given this, I implement checklists that require me to tie out balances, subtotal transactions, and double check other tasks before I move forward in the close process.  In a way, I am auditing my work to catch any mistakes or errors.  This not only saves me time in the long run, but also saves my manager time, as there is less back and forth resolving issues.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What qualities or skills do you believe a good treasury analyst should possess?", "answers": ["This question is a good opportunity to show you have an understanding of what qualities make a good accounting professional.  Some key areas to hit are ethics (honesty/integrity), an ability to interact with colleagues and clients (communication skills, people person), an ability to limit mistakes (focused/attention to detail), and an ability to get to the correct answer (skeptical/inquisitive/problem solver).", "\"First and foremost, I believe a treasury analyst should be honest and have great integrity.  Without this, it would be impossible for the person to perform the role effectively.  Next, the analyst should have the education and technical skills to perform the job.  They should have exceptional people skills as they will be required to communicate effectively with colleagues, external auditors, and other parties.  Finally, they should have an inquisitive mind and a keen attention to detail.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "The treasury department interacts frequently with other departments.  What are some of the ways that you can show professionalism when representing our department?", "answers": ["A treasury analyst represents the treasury department as a whole when they interact with other departments.  Acting professional is not something that comes naturally to people new to the workforce. Take this opportunity to demonstrate your awareness of professionalism in the workplace and provide an example.", "\"It is extremely important to display professionalism when we are interacting with other departments and external auditors.  First and foremost, I know that I must look the part by adhering to the appropriate dress code.  Secondly, I know I must act professionally.  This means speaking respectfully to all personnel, whether it is the company's CFO or a personal assistant.  I shouldn't take personal phone calls or play music loudly.  As a general rule, I shouldn't do or say anything that would harm our department's reputation.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "How are interest rates derived?", "answers": ["Interest rates are the cost of borrowing money, and they indicate what a creditor will earn by lending money.  Interest rates are always changing.  They are mostly determined by central banks that raise or lower rates to make sure there is stability in the economy.  Answering this question intelligently shows that you have a basic understanding of an underlying concept of the financial market.", "\"Interest rates are determined by central banks.  These banks raise or lower interest rates to ensure stability and liquidity in the economy.  Smaller retail banks, such as Bank of America, will also set rates based on the needs of their business, their location, and their customers.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What is the difference between Held-to-Maturity Securities and Available-for-Sale Securities?", "answers": ["Held-to-Maturity and Available-for-Sale securities are two common types of business investments that have different accounting treatment.  A treasury analyst should be able to define each type of investment and point out the difference in accounting treatment.", "\"A Held-to-Maturity security is one in which the organization has the intent and ability to hold until the security reaches maturity.  These securities are reported at amortized cost on the balance sheet.  Available-for-Sale securities, such as stocks and bonds, are reported at fair value on the balance sheet.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "How would you handle working in an increasingly remote environment?", "answers": ["This is a question to gauge if you are disciplined enough to work from home.  Be sure to touch on how you would stay focused and communicate with team members.  Even after things return to normal, remote work may continue to be more common across many industries, including accounting.", "\"I have experience working remotely.  At my internship, we were able to work from home on Fridays in the summer.  I enjoyed working from home, and I was able to stay on task and communicate effectively with my team members.  There were some ground rules I implemented, such as maintaining regular hours, keeping my morning routine as if I was going to the office, and scheduling breaks to take care of non-work related tasks. I also had a standing meeting with my manager and team members every morning to discuss priorities for the day.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What do you do when you don\u2019t know the answer to something?", "answers": ["There is no shame in being stumped - it happens to everyone at all levels of an organization.  This question is an opportunity to highlight your ability to be independent and resourceful.", "\"I have no problem seeking solutions to questions I encounter.  If I am unsure about the accounting treatment for a certain transaction, I can reach out to our external auditors for advice on the appropriate treatment.  Industry guides and other information are also available online, so I can complete research, as needed. If it's something technical, such as using a new Excel formula, I am good at researching online and following examples.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "Are you willing to work extra hours if needed during busier times?", "answers": ["The life of a treasury analyst is tied to the month-end close calendar and tax filing deadlines, which could result in a schedule that is 'lumpy' and not a typical 9-5.  The candidate should expect there to be some additional time worked during busier times and should highlight that they are flexible.", "\"Yes, I am willing to work extra hours as needed.  I understand that the work required ramps up during month-end close, tax filings, and other busier times.  I am happy to be flexible and work as needed to make sure the job gets done.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "Are you proficient in Excel?", "answers": ["Excel proficiency is a must for not only a treasury analyst, but any role in accounting.  At a minimum, a treasury analyst should be able to sort through large amounts of data, and analyze that data using pivot tables.", "\"Yes, I am proficient in Excel.  I have used Excel extensively throughout my time in school, as well as in my previous role.  For example, I used data sorting and filtering, as well as pivot tables to organize large amounts of data.  Additionally, I have experience using V-Lookups and H-Lookups to pull together analysis for our external auditors.  I have even dipped my toes into data visualization software such as Tableau, but that is a skill I would like to continue to nurture.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What are bank covenants and what are some common examples?", "answers": ["Bank covenants are clauses in bank loan agreements that require the borrower to maintain certain financial ratios in order to keep the loan open.  Some common examples of covenants included in a loan agreement are Debt Service Ratio, Working Capital Ratio, Current Ratio, and Debt-to-Equity Ratio.", "\"Bank covenants are stipulations included in the language of loan agreements.  They typically require the borrower to maintain certain ratios in order to not be in default of the loan agreement.  Some common ratios included in debt covenants are Debt-to-Equity, Current Ratio, and Working Capital Ratio.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What is the debt-to-equity ratio and what does it tell about a company\u2019s finances?", "answers": ["The debt-to-equity ratio is a common and important way to measure a company's financial leverage.  Simply, it measures the degree to which a company is financing their operations through debt (loans, etc.) vs. wholly-owned funds.", "\"The debt-to-equity ratio is an important metric that is used by outside investors and other stakeholders to determine the financial health of the company.  It is calculated by taking total liabilities divided by total equity.  The ratio will measure how leveraged a company is, and if the company would be able to cover operations in an economic downturn.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "How is corporate investment income taxed?", "answers": ["The current corporate tax rate for US corporations is 21%.  However, interest, dividend, and royalties are taxed at 30% if they are not connected with the corporation's main business activity.", "\"Corporations are currently taxed at a flat 21%.  However, investment income is treated differently if the income is not directly connected to the company's main business activity.  Dividends, interest, royalties, and realized gains are taxed at a flat 30%.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "How do you keep up with the latest developments in financial news, rules, and regulations?", "answers": ["This question is asked to confirm that you take initiative to stay current on the latest developments in your field.  If you are a CFA or have another professional license, talk about how you use mandatory continuing education requirements to stay up to date on the latest trends and regulations.", "\"I stay up to date in various ways.  First, I subscribe to industry e-newsletters to keep up to date on the latest trends, rules, and regulations.  Additionally, since I am a CFA, I stay up to date with new standards through continuing education courses.  I try to select courses that align nicely with the roles and responsibilities of my current position.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "How do you manage your manager?  In other words, what steps do you take to make sure you get what you need from your boss and make both your lives easier?", "answers": ["Also known as 'managing up', 'managing your manager' is a soft skill that can be developed over time.  It essentially means doing whatever is necessary to make your manager's job easier.  Some clear-cut benefits of managing up include increased productivity and better working relationships between a boss and employee.", "\"I am a firm believer in the benefits of managing my manager.  At the end of the day, I want to make sure our work runs as smoothly as possible.  One area I really focus on is communicating and prioritizing workload on a regular basis.  This ensures that I'm always working on the highest-priority items.   Another thing that is crucial is understanding my manager's style.  For example, do they like regular check-ins by email throughout the day, scheduled catch-up meetings, etc.  Then, I tailor my communication to their style.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What is your experience interacting with senior executives at various organizations?", "answers": ["A treasury analyst will at times be expected to interact with senior leadership of the organization.  Highlight that you not only have experience presenting in front of leadership, but also that you are comfortable with it.  Be specific with what you presented.", "\"I have ample experience getting in front of leadership and presenting.  In my previous role as staff accountant, I would meet with the Controller and CFO to discuss the monthly close.  I always felt the need to prepare in advance for any questions that might arise, and would often follow-up with anything that developed during those meetings. Even though these were low-risk conversations, the interactions gave me confidence at an early stage in my career.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "How would you interact with our organization\u2019s external auditors?", "answers": ["An organization's treasury department will often lean on external auditors for guidance and advice.  Additionally, during their field testing, an auditor may request documentation relating to treasury transactions.", "\"I understand that I will need to have a good working relationship with the organization's external auditors.  They will be a good resource for accounting treatment of unique transactions and other general advice.  Additionally, they will likely be testing some of our transactions and I will need to provide them with my work papers.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What are some internal controls related to cash?", "answers": ["Internal controls over cash aim to ensure cash doesn't go missing, either by accident or intentionally via theft.  Some common controls include: reconciling cash regularly, keeping all physical cash under lock and key, not sharing passwords, requiring regular password changes, documenting transfers, and recording cash receipts when received.", "\"Internal controls help a company safeguard one of their most coveted assets.  Preventing misappropriation of cash, when intentional or accidental, is of utmost importance to an organization.  Some examples of controls related to cash include keeping physical cash and banking records in a secure location, requiring regular password updates and not sharing passwords, documenting all receipts, payments and transfers, and having more than one person perform cash duties to institute segregation of duties.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What are the steps involved in the bank reconciliation process?", "answers": ["Bank reconciliations are a key responsibility of the treasury analyst role.  These days, most accounting software packages (such as Quickbooks) make the process easy.  However, an analyst should know the steps that are involved.", "\"In order to complete a bank reconciliation, a bank statement or export file of bank activity needs to be obtained for the prior month.  The analyst should enter the ending bank balance in the accounting software.  Next, the analyst should check off the transactions that have cleared the bank.  There may be some transactions that need to be added to the general ledger, such as bank charges.  If the reconciliation ties out to the bank balance, the reconciliation is complete.  If not, differences should be investigated.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What have you done at your previous job to reduce costs or save time?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know if you have the ability to improve processes.  Speak to a specific action you took that resulted in reduced costs, saved time, or better insights gained.", "\"My last role was accountant for a small, established company.  However, my predecessor did not have established procedures in place and it sounded like he had made constant mistakes.  One of the first things I did when I started was I made a monthly checklist that detailed all the steps I took during the monthly close.  Included in these steps were 'checks' I performed to self review my work.  The checklist served as a cover sheet that I would hand off to my manager so that she would know exactly what steps I completed.  This led to increased efficiency, as we estimated it saved 4-6 hours per month in error corrections.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "Are you a detail-oriented person?", "answers": ["The treasury analyst position requires great attention to detail as the role is in charge of producing and maintaining meticulous financial records.  It is expected that the analyst can catch mistakes before reporting is provided to leaders of the organization.", "\"Yes, I am extremely detail oriented.  Part of what makes me a great analyst is my organization skills and ability to self-review my work.  I know that providing financial information containing errors creates doubt among leadership that the financial records are accurate.  Therefore, I implement systems that allow me to check the details, such as monthly checklists and reviews.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "Why did you want to become a treasury analyst?", "answers": ["This question allows the interviewer to find out a little bit about your interest in the position.  Be honest and direct - don't give a phony answer that the interviewer will see through.", "\"Since I was young, I have always liked math and have been good with numbers.  I took an accounting class in high school and really enjoyed it; the concepts came naturally to me.  Additionally, I am interested in financial markets and investments.  I also aspire to be a key contributor to an organization, and I know that the analyst role is visible to leadership.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Analyst", "question": "What accounting softwares are you familiar with?", "answers": ["Speak specifically to the accounting systems you have used and some of the functions you performed.  Many job descriptions specifically state which accounting software the company uses.  In any event, make sure to highlight that you are quick to learn new software systems.", "\"In my last role, I used SAP to book journal entries and run queries.  As an independent contractor, I also used Quickbooks to complete monthly bookkeeping for various clients.  I used that software to book journal entries, complete bank reconciliations, run monthly reports, and invoice customers.  Since I have an underlying understanding of accounting, I am easily able to learn new software packages.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Tell me about the biggest cash flow issue you have resolved.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about the biggest cash flow issue you have resolved in your career, in any position (i.e., it does not have to be in a formal capacity of Treasury Assistant but can be in a position wherein you had treasury duties).\n\r\nShould you not have experienced such issues, tell the interviewer why that is the case.", "\"Fortunately, I have never had to resolved cash flow issues. I believe my high degree of meticulousness ensured such situation would rarely occur as I always review my work numerous times before submission to ensure the information is accurate.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Tell me about your post-secondary education and how it prepared you for this position.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your post-secondary education by mentioning knowledge and/or experience acquired throughout your studies, such as courses taken, group projects, and so on.", "\"As you can see on my resume, I graduated from the (X university) with a bachelor's degree in accounting. Throughout my studies, I acquired advanced accounting knowledge, such as (X courses). I furthermore gained some hands-on experience while working on projects such as (X projects that helped you develop accounting skills).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Tell me the accounting programs and software that you are best versed in. What is your level of proficiency in each?", "answers": ["Ensure to review the job description before the interview to familiarize yourself with the accounting programs and software required for this role. \n\r\nShould none be listed on the job posting, answer this question by mentioning the most relevant accounting programs and software you are proficient in, on a scale of 1 to 10.", "\"I would rate myself 9/10 in (X accounting program) and 9 1/2/10 in (X software).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What bookkeeping experience do you have?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your bookkeeping experience in any capacity, i.e., professional (paid/unpaid) or volunteer. The objective is to show the interviewer you have the bookkeeping skills required for this position and as such, will be successful in this role.", "\"I worked as Volunteer Bookkeeping Assistant for (X company name) during my first summer break from university, and as a Bookkeeping Intern for (X company name) upon graduation from (X university.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "As a Treasury Assistant it is of utmost importance to have your work done on a daily basis. How do you stay focused and on deadline?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your organizational and time management skills.", "\"I use a calendar to be reminded of upcoming meetings and deadlines, as well as daily/weekly to-do lists, by prioritizing the most important duties, to ensure I am on top of things. I review and amend my lists every morning, throughout the day, and in the afternoon before leaving for the day.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Why are you the best Treasury Assistant for us?", "answers": ["Ensure to review the job description before the interview to familiarize yourself with the personality traits or profile required for this role. Answer this question by outlining a few of the listed qualifications that you also possess, making you the best candidate for this role.\n\r\nAlternatively, mention your top qualifications and qualities which will ensure your success in this role.", "\"As you can see on my resume, I have the required educational qualifications, holding a bachelor's and master's degree in accounting, as well as years of relevant treasury experience. I furthermore am a hard worker, a team player and work tirelessly.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "In your opinion, what are the top 3 qualities every Treasury Assistant should possess?", "answers": ["Always review the job description before the interview to familiarize yourself with the personality traits required from the successful incumbent. \n\r\nAnswer this question by mentioning 3 qualities from the job posting, if provided, and provide an example of these qualities in a professional capacity. Alternatively, provide your top 3 qualities, which you believe will highly benefit you in this role, and provide an example of these qualities in a professional setting.", "\"The top 3 qualities a Treasury Assistant should possess are time management skills, metiiculousness and hardworking capabilities, which I possess. These qualities served me well in my last position at (X company name) where I was employed as a/an (X position title). In this role, I (X confirmation re: how/why your qualities benefitted you in this role).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "How strong are your skills in cash flow and general analysis?", "answers": ["You may answer this question by rating yourself on a scale of 1 to 10, and why. \n\r\nShould you lack skills in certain areas, ensure to mention you are more than willing to undertake training. This will show the interviewer you are committed and are serious about working for this employer.", "\"I would rate myself 9/10 with respect to cash flow, and 6/10 with respect to general analysis. My last roles entailed mostly cash flow related duties, and little general analysis. I am however familiar with general analysis and am more than willing to undertake required training in that area if necessary in order to reach expert level.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Tell me about your expertise in posting deposits, maintaining financial records, and reconciling bank accounts.", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your experience against the position you applied for, obtained in a professional or volunteer capacity. Ensure to respond to all aspects of the question.\n\r\nIt is mandatory to do your due diligence before your interview by reviewing the job description and the company website/social media pages to familiarize yourself with the work involved and services offered at the company.\n\r\nExample of an answer to the above question: \"My experience posting deposits was obtained while working for (X company name) as a/an (X position title). My daily duties entailed (X duties). Regarding the maintenance of financial records and reconciliation of bank accounts, I perform these duties extensively while working for (X company name) as a/an (X position title). My daily duties in this role entailed (X duties).\"", "\"My experience posting deposits was obtained while working for (X company name) as a/an (X position title). My daily duties entailed (X duties). Regarding the maintenance of financial records and reconciliation of bank accounts, I perform these duties extensively while working for (X company name) as a/an (X position title). My daily duties in this role entailed (X duties).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Where do you see yourself in 2 to 3 years from now?", "answers": ["Answer by telling the interviewer about your short-term goals, however by ensuring your goals are related to the position and company you applied for. \n\r\nShould your short-term goals significantly differ from the position or company, the interviewer may assume you will leave eventually the position if hired, for a better opportunity at another company, should one presents itself. As a result, you may be instantly disqualified.", "\"In 2 to 3 years from now, I would like to have grown within the company and having established myself as a treasury expert. I hope to eventually move up the ladder and become a Treasury Manager or Team Lead within the department. I wish to commit to my employer and contribute to the company's success.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What is your greatest strength and how does it help you to be a successful Treasury Assistant?", "answers": ["Answer by telling the interviewer what your greatest strength is, related to the position you applied for. Ensure to mention how this strength will contribute to your success as a Treasury Assistant.", "\"My greatest strength is that I am extremely meticulous. I also always review my work at least twice before submission to superiors or colleagues to ensure that my work is accurate.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What do you know about our organization?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your knowledge of the company you applied for. It is imperative to always conduct your due diligence before an interview by reviewing the job description, company website and social media pages to familiarize yourself with the company and work involved. It is also important to show the interviewer you did not apply to the advertised position simply because you are looking for just any job, but that you wish to work for this company specifically.", "\"I reviewed the job description and website before this interview and know you are a company specializing in (X services you noticed on the company website). I am particularly excited about (X programs/initiatives) that I saw on your (website/social media pages) as I (X reasons you are excited about these programs/initiatives, such as passion or similar initiatives undertaken in school or volunteer capacity).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What are your long term career goals?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your career goals in ~7 to 10 years from now. Ensure to link your career goals to the company you are applying for to show the interviewer you can be a long-term asset for the company and that you are looking for stability.", "\"In 7 to 10 years from now, I would like to have grown within the same company I started off with, having acquired skills enabling me to establish myself as a treasury expert. I would love to be responsible for more managerial duties and ultimately lead a team of professionals.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What is your greatest weakness, and what are you doing to improve it?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer what your greatest weakness is, however by ensuring that this weakness can be a strength in this position.", "\"I am a very hard-worker and find hard to stop working at the end of the day, resulting in numerous long days at the office. To improve in that area, I did my best to do lists every morning by prioritizing the work that needs to be done by the end of the day, and the following tasks that are not as urgent. Doing this significantly improved my time management skills and made me more productive at work.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What have you done in the past year to increase your knowledge in treasury?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about the courses you took (or are taking), seminars/conferences you attended or will be attending, or past/future volunteer experiences that increased or will increase your knowledge in this field.", "\"I am currently enrolled in (X course), which I am pursuing on a part-time basis online. I am also planning to attend (X upcoming conferences).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "How would your former employer describe you?", "answers": ["Always review the job posting before an interview to familiarize yourself with the personality traits the employer is seeking. Answer this question by mentioning some of the familiarity traits listed by providing an example in a professional setting.", "\"My former employer would say that I am a highly meticulous individual and a very hard worker. I always review my work at least twice before submission and am one of the first employees in the office every morning.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Have you ever lead a team of individuals? In the affirmative, do you enjoy taking on a leadership role?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your team management experience, should you have any, in a professional, volunteer, or educational capacity (alternatively). \n\r\nShould you have none, mention that you are more than willing to gain leadership skills and would love to take on a leadership role - and why you are a good leader. \n\r\nIf the interviewer asks such a question, it is likely that the position entails leadership duties - current or future, which will most of the time already be outlined on the job posting. As such, he/she will assume you applied to this role upon having adequately read the job posting, and that you have an interest in team mananegement and/or team management experience. \n\r\nTry to provide an example related to treasury as much as possible. If you cannot do so, provide any example by telling the interviewer you are positive your skills will easily be transferable.", "\"I lead a team of individuals in a volunteer capacity when working as (X position title) for (X organization). In this role, I was responsible for 10 sales representatives and (X further related responsibilities). I realize this particular experience is not related to treasury, however the team management skills acquired in this role will highly benefit me in this position at your company. I thoroughly enjoyed taking on a leadership role as I love leading team members to success.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Are you interested in obtaining your Masters' degree in Business and/or Accounting (in the event not listed on resume)?", "answers": ["Ensure to review the job posting several times before an interview to familiarize yourself with the qualifications required for a role. \n\r\nShould advanced degrees be required, the interviewer will assume you are aware of these requirements and that you will be willing to pursue advanced degrees, if required (should there be no master's degrees already listed on your resume). This applies even in the event you only have a bachelor's degree and the position requires a master's degree, yet you were nevertheless granted an interview.\n\r\nAnswer this question by pointing out you are serious about the position you applied for and as such, should you pursue a master's degree as per the position requirements, your education will not interfere with your new position. Employers are looking for seriousness and commitment.", "\"Effective (X start date), I will be enrolled in a Master's degree program in Accounting at (X university), however on a part-time basis in the evenings. I am serious about this position at your company and you can rest assured my education will not interfere with my work.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "In addition to the degree(s), do you have any certifications, licenses or designations not listed on your resume?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer the certifications, licenses and/or designations that you have, even those not related to the position you are applying for - for the sake of full disclosure. Mention the year of obtention and name of the educational institutions.", "\"I obtained (X certification) in (X year) from (X university), and (X license) in (X year) from (X institution).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "How well do you get along with your colleagues?", "answers": ["Should the interviewer ask you about team playing skills, these are likely to be required in this role, e.g., having to work on collaborative projects. As such, tell him/her about such skills by providing an example in a past role.", "\"I thrive in a team environment and consider myself a team player. For instance, in my last role of (X position title) at (X company), we had to work on numerous collective projects on a weekly basis, such as (...) (X description of collaborative projects and how you contributed to the team's success).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What software or program do you use for tracking financial records?", "answers": ["Ensure to review the job posting before the interview to familiarize yourself with the software and programs required for this role, and try to mention one (or several) of the software or programs listed (should you be knowledgeable in any of those listed). \n\r\nShould none be listed, mention the ones you use the most by emphasizing that you will remain willing to undertake training as required by the employer. This will show commitment to the employer and that you are serious about this position.", "\"I use (X software/program) for tracking financial records. However, I read on your job posting that you require knowledge of (X software). I am not very familiar with this software but am absolutely willing to undertake training.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "Being a Treasury Assistant can be stressful. What do you do to blow off steam, when necessary?", "answers": ["Tell the interviewer about your stress management skills and ability to work under pressure.", "\"I thrive under pressure and always remain calm in stressful situations. I sincerely believe that exercising on a regular basis significantly helps me stay calm in stressful situations.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What is your preferred industry to work in?", "answers": ["Ensure to do your due diligence before the interview by reviewing the job posting and company website/social media pages to familiarize yourself with the position, services offered at the company, and industry the company is in.\n\r\nAnswer this question by mentioning you wish to work in the same industry the employer is in to demonstrate you have done your due diligence and wish to work for this employer specifically - and that you are not simply looking for just any job. Add the reasons why you wish to work in such industry.", "\"I saw on your website that you are in (X industry) and this is precisely the industry I wish to establish myself in because (X reasons why, such as passion for the industry and/or related courses taken in university that sparked your interest).\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "What do you look for in an employer?", "answers": ["Ensure to review the job posting and company website/social media pages before the interview to familiarize yourself with the company. Do your best to answer by including something you saw on the job description or website to show you did your due diligence before the interview and that you are serious about working for this employer specifically.", "\"I am looking for an employer who values its employees and who will give me the opportunity to grow. I also saw on your job posting that your company is a family environment, which is exactly the type of environment I wish to work in.\""]}, {"topic": "Treasury+Assistant", "question": "As a Treasury Assistant you will spend a great deal of time at your desk. Are you okay with being in a sedentary job?", "answers": ["Firstly, it is mandatory to always review a job posting before your interview. Secondly, the interviewer will value candidates who reviewed the job posting before applying for this position, and who did not apply to just any position. \n\r\nAs such, by virtue of the duties outline on the job posting, you should already know whether the position will be sedentary, and the answer the interviewer is seeking in a successful incumbent. It is therefore imperative to answer by saying you reviewed the job posting several times before your interview, are aware of the position requirements, and applied as you are perfectly comfortable being in a sedentary job.\n\r\nDo not simply provide a yes or no answer. Always elaborate.", "\"I am absolutely okay being in a sedentary job. I reviewed the job posting several times since applying online, and understood this was such a position.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Why are you the best candidate for us?", "answers": ["Two-sided question. One one side, it may be looking to see if you are too bold, while it may also be looking to see if you are humble. \n\r\nTalking about ourselves in this way can be challenging. We recommend reaching out to a few colleagues, family members, and friends. Ask them for their opinion. You'll probably be surprised at the consistency in their responses! Their answers will give you the response to the question. Tell the interviewer what sets you apart, and explain how your colleagues, family members, and friends have encouraged you with your gift in this area.", "\"I know that you may have received applications from several applicants that have the same qualifications as I do, but what possibly makes me different and better from the others is my excellent risk analysis skills accompanied with the fact that I trained under the best in this profession. Also, I am very punctual and organized and have a great attention to detail which also means I make almost no errors in my work.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Why do you want a career as an underwriter?", "answers": ["You can add a personal touch when answering this question. Be sure that your passion for your career comes through in your answer.", "\"I love working as an underwriter because I feel that by doing this job I am being valuable not only for the organization that I am working for but also for the society. I get to use my analytical skills, critical thinking and decision making every day. The challenges that I face every day as an underwriter and the risks that we face is an extra bonus in itself.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What are the steps you follow to study a problem before making a decision?", "answers": ["The best way of answering this question is by making sure that you are not completely giving a bookish answer but also not something that is totally vague and irrelevant. Divide your working style in several defined steps and present it in front of the interviewer. This will help the interviewer in determining how well organized and efficient you are in handling your work. \r\nThe Problem Solving process consists of a sequence of sections that fit together depending on the type of problem to be solved. These are: \r\n*Problem Definition \r\n*Problem Analysis \r\n*Generating possible Solutions \r\n*Analyzing the Solutions \r\n*Selecting the best Solution(s) \r\n*Planning the next course of action (Next Steps) \r\nIt may also be important to indicate where you seek out confirmation, validation and/or approval at various steps", "\"While solving a problem my first step is to define the problem.Then I gather all the relevant data and examine what could be the root cause, the scale of the problem and the possible solutions based on the analysis. The next step is always to analyse the solutions and figure out which one could be the best and based on the selection I make the suggestions.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Give an example of a time when you made a mistake because you failed to actively listen to a supervisor.", "answers": ["Failing is normal, natural. No candidate can answer this with a 'it has never happened.'\nBe honest on this one, and present a short summary of your example. As is the case with other questions, the importance is to indicate how you learned and developed from making this mistake. \nActive listening is just listening and saying 'yes or OK' and not asking for clarification, confirmation of what you think you heard, or at a minimum, summarizing the instructions. \nAs a student, this may be that time that you wrote an entire essay only to find out you were supposed to write a one-page summary.", "\"When I was a trainee I was asked to perform a simple task of collecting data of our clients and I spent two days in doing that. When I submitted my final report I realized that I had made a mistake and had collected the wrong data. The reason was that although I was paying attention there was a part which I could not listen to the instructions given by my senior clearly and since I was new, I hesitate to ask questions. He bought this to my knowledge and I admitted my mistake and apologized and collected the right information. Since that day I make sure that I listen to everything and ask questions if anything is not clear. I have learned that if you hesitate in asking questions if things are not clear you will end up making mistakes which will be even worse than the hesitation in  asking questions in the first place.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "If not an underwriter, what other role within insurance would you like to be in?", "answers": ["This is an opportunity for you to show your knowledge of other roles, either as potential other roles that are open at this time in the company, roles that feed into becoming an underwriter, and roles that work with underwriters but have additional or other skills. You can begin with expressing how much you enjoy doing your job as an underwriter but at the same time also let the interviewer know that if not an underwriter then you would have been doing some job that is something similar to an underwriter's job.", "\"Although I enjoy being an underwriter to the core as it gives me freedom to use my analytical as well as problem solving skills and I can't imagine myself doing any other job as I am in love with this one, but if I still end up in a situation where I need to pick up an alternative career then I think I would like to be a budget analyst. The reason behind this choice is that in this job too I will get to utilise my skills and be valuable for the organization I work for.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Tell me something about yourself that is not on your resume.", "answers": ["This is a common question used to evaluate culture fit. Don't not mention any activities that are specific to race, color, religion, sex, and national origin. \r\nIf you are a competitive or non competitive athlete, do improv, volunteer, jump out of airplanes, save whales, etc., this is an opportunity to mention them.", "\"Something about me that many do not know is that I was a competitive dancer for many years. I gave it up once I started working as an underwriter. Despite it being unrelated to this profession, it truly did teach me about discipline and dedication.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What motivates you as an underwriter?", "answers": ["Underwriting is a complex mix of task and process orientation. Processes have to be followed per company and government regulations while the role also is key to getting deals completed for the organization.\n\r\nYour answer should indicate how your motivations are to add value to the organization by completing your work accurately and under time constraints. You will need to be able to indicate that your motivations match to the organization's needs and the job duties.", "\"I love working as an underwriter because I feel that by doing this job I am being valuable not only for the organization that I am working for but also for the society. I get to use my analytical skills, critical thinking and decision making everyday. The challenges that I face everyday as an underwriter and the risks that we face is an extra bonus in itself.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "How would you compare your current job to that of an underwriter?", "answers": ["Be prepared to provide at least three aspects of your current role that are transferrable to becoming an underwriter. Specific experience in reviewing documents for completeness and accuracy, adherence to corporate policy, and legal compliance in other industries may be the best examples you can bring to the table.\n\r\nAdditional skills in gathering research  and developing financial risk assessments would be good.", "\"My current job involves reviewing a lot of documents, analysing them for financial risks, a lot of research and time management. I believe that these skills are of equal importance for the job of an underwriter as well. In addition to all this, I have a very good understanding of the tasks an underwriter needs to perform and thus I believe that I will be a very good match for this job.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "How do you keep track of work so that it gets done on time?", "answers": ["If you have a daily planning period, now is the time to bring this up. For example \"Every morning I spend 30 minutes planning my day over coffee, entering my 'to-dos', reviewing my long and mid-term projects on XYZ application.\"\n\r\nIf you also have an end of the day ritual, where you go over what you got done, bring it up now.", "\"Every morning I spend 30 minutes planning my day over coffee, entering my 'to-dos', reviewing my long and mid-term projects on XYZ application.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What do you know about our company?", "answers": ["With any job interview, it is crucial to understand the organization you are applying to. We recommend visiting the company website to learn key information such as current events and hirings or promotions or anything that qualifies as a news. Watch the videos on their website, and take note of the information on their Careers page if one is available. Come prepared to list off 5-6 things you learned from the company's website such as number of clients they have, number of branches they have, when the company started, who started the company, mission statement, vision statement, core values, etc.."]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What do you dislike the most about being an underwriter?", "answers": ["The best way of answering this question is to be positive and not to say anything that makes you appear like a pessimist. You should appear to be interested in this profession on a whole and make the interviewer feel that this is not just a few days stop for you. Its your choice for a long term career.", "\"Sometimes there are times when the work comes to our desk in bulk and becomes a bit difficult to manage. But it is as necessary as any other and with better planning and time management skills it can be easily managed. As an underwriter, I work as hard as I can to get it done, quickly and correctly, and not dwell on any negatives.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Tell me about your financial training and education.", "answers": ["Some companies prefer candidates who have bachelors degrees most specifically in finance, mathematics, economic, accounting etc. but most of the times either a degree in the above mentioned or a related experience is sufficient along with good knowledge of computers. For senior positions a candidate may be required to have certain certifications. \n\r\nBe prepared to present your skills in standard financial applications (most important would be MS Excel or comparable) spreadsheets. Strong skills (pivot tables, if-then, multi-variables) would be ideal.", "\"I have a bachelors degree in accounting in addition to an year long training done under a senior underwriter. During that training I got a practical knowledge of how to excel in our job by making use of several financial applications. Also, I learnt how important attention to detail is in our job.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Do you have strong computer skills? Which programs are you most experienced in?", "answers": ["As an underwriter you may be required to use several high level software and programs. In addition to standard office tools, be prepared to show your skills in job specific tools and other skills that you have (web tools, scripting, programming, etc.). Don't sound over-confident but an answer that exhibits confidence in this scenario is highly appreciated by the recruiting managers. What is important is that you have a conceptual technical knowledge that helps you in solving the problem at hand and communicate it effectively to the stakeholders.", "\"I am well versed in using SQL and SAP and have the basic knowledge of Netsuit and Microsoft Dynamics along with Excel. I am capable of analysing several complicated cases using these and also of communicating the results to the clients.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "If hired, how do you intend on making a difference with our company?", "answers": ["Your answer can best be framed along the lines that you are interested in the underwriter role and seeing how you can provide suggestions on efficiencies in the role, opportunities for expanding cross-functional collaboration, being a super user and subsequent trainer of new hires. If you are interested, being a resource for future college outreach/recruiting, may also be attractive to a rapidly growing company.", "\"First of all I would like to say that I understand the requirements of the company and also that I know what might be the expectations from this job. I would make sure that I add value to the company through my presence and work. Also, if needed I would love to volunteer my services as and when needed for any other tasks including training the interns, giving presentations at some other locations on behalf of the company, doing any voluntary work. I will make sure that I understand the company's culture and become an integral part of it and help it in future growth.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What has been your greatest accomplishment as an underwriter so far?", "answers": ["Start with giving an example of a project or task where you excelled and were also commended by your seniors and team members. Explain the overall idea, what you personally accomplished, and if there were team members, how you helped them, etc. Also be able to explain how this project fit within the overall organization or was of significance in terms of customer size (if work related). In all cases, be able to drill-down into what you contributed, the challenges if any (tech, people, timing, etc.), and how you met these challenges.", "\"So far the greatest accomplishment of my career has been managing to acquire a big client which was at that time the biggest client in our books. I was responsible for contacting that client, holding the discussions and analyzing the risk related to this deal.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What has been your biggest disappointment as an underwriter so far?", "answers": ["A typical example may be a project that required a great deal of activity and then was cancelled, a lost sale, even a failed business venture. The important part of this question is your ability to show how you gained knowledge and grew from the disappointment.\r\nDon't talk about any personal loss that you may have incurred or about anything funny in here. The interviewer is not looking for an emotional outburst but something that helps in acknowledging your decision making and problem solving skills. Also, anything that might make you sound like an arrogant or a negative person is a big no. \r\nAlso, try not to dodge the question as it might end up resulting in a negative comment from the interviewer.", "\"I have always worked hard in my whole career for ensuring that we get the best clients for our organization but this one time I was really disappointed when we lost one of our big accounts to a competitor because they got a better deal with them. This took me by surprise as this was a really old account and they always used to renew with us only. Although this deeply saddened me but I decided that instead of being sad about losing this one, I would rather focus on bringing changes in our strategy and focusing on getting some new clients. As a result of our efforts we were able to acquire some big accounts and since then we have always ensured to review our strategy on a regular basis to see if there is any scope for improvement.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What is the most difficult situation you have had to face and how did you tackle it?", "answers": ["This can be answered with a difficult project encountered while in school or work. Difficult situations can be related to team dynamics, unrealistic expectations, incomplete directions, etc.\n\r\nDescribe the project, the difficulty and how/why it was difficult. Then describe how you dealt with it. Example might be taking a project team member aside and walking through the project elements, how they need to work on specific areas. If it was with a difficult teacher/boss, then describe how you communicated the issue(s) you were encountering, what you proposed to \r\nsolve the issues, and ultimately the resolution.", "\"In my career there have been many difficult situations but what I would like to mention here is one incident where a loan application came to me and we had a very little time to process it. We had to do everything quickly which required the cooperation of the whole team. One of our team members decided to quit the job at that same time, because of which we were in an even worse situation. That is when I decided to overtake the work that other team member was handling. With proper team work and coordination we finished the project on time and also got the contract.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Give me a time when you went above and beyond the requirements for a project.", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know that you are the type of employee who will go above expectations for a customer. You are willing to do what it takes to make sure that your performance is at its best and your team gets the most out of it. If possible, share what project you were working on, what your basic requirements were, and how you went above-and-beyond. Be sure to mention why you decided to do it for that project to help the interviewer see your drive to be successful in your work.", "\"This happened when I was working under a senior underwriter and we were working on an important case which could have bought in some real big profit for our organization but my boss got very sick at the last stages when we had to submit our findings and decision. There was no way we could have completed this job without his supervision as I was fairly new and didn't have much experience. It was then that I decided to do my own research and spent the whole weekend in the library and over the internet, going through as many cases as I could and finally I was able to complete that project on my own. That was the first big project of my career that I did on my own and although it was a huge risk that I took, when my senior came back he praised me for my pro-activeness and we also got that client. After all our job is all about taking risks.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Have you ever had difficulty with a supervisor?", "answers": ["What was your relationship like with your most recent supervisor? Assure the interviewer that you are able to take instruction well and that you show respect to your leaders in the workplace. Although, there are occasions that you may have had certain disagreements but try to project everything in a positive manner avoiding anything that might portray you as a difficult employee to work with.\n\r\nIf you have not had difficulty with a supervisor: \"My most recent supervisor and I had a strong work relationship and she will be willing to give you a strong reference on my behalf. We did not run into any difficulty while working together.\" \n\r\nIf you did have difficulty with a supervisor: \"In my career I have had many different supervisors with an array of personalities. I did have one supervisor in the past who was not the type of leader that I would have chosen for myself. We disagreed on occasion but nothing severe enough to affect my work performance.\"", "\"My most recent supervisor and I had a strong work relationship and she will be willing to give you a strong reference on my behalf. We did not run into any difficulty while working together.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Have you ever been overloaded with work? What did you do to ensure your deadlines were met?", "answers": ["This question drills deeper into how you manage your time, projects and what happens when things got out of your hands? Were you able to come out of such a situation on your own? Did you have to ask for help? What did you exactly do?\r\nThe best way to answer this question would be through giving an example of a situation where such a thing happened with you and how you tackled with it. In case this never happened then explain how you manage your work everyday, how you prioritise things at work etc.\r\nKey to this is recognizing that there are limits to your capabilities, that you are able to recognize them, and for the better of the company, you were willing to take the corrective measures. \r\nAlso, if you are giving an example then try to state something from the initial days of your career, something thats not recent.", "\"Working as an underwriter means that there will be times when there might be a lot of work on your hands. But if you are good at your job and keep things organized and plan well in advance then you can avoid situations where things might go out of your hands because of the overload.\r\nBeing a part of the industry even I have been overloaded with work once or twice. This happened when I had just joined and was a trainee working under a senior underwriter. I used to work on small assignments and for some reason used to spend more than required time on each assignment just trying to be extra careful with everything I did. As a result I was overloaded with work in no time. At first I got panicked but then I got hold of myself in some time and decided to sort it all out. I arranged all the cases according to the level of importance, the deadlines and also on the kind of cases they referred to and then started working on them. I did have to put in a few extra hours of work to sort this all out but eventually I was able to finish it all. I did miss a deadline or two but was excused as I was still a beginner. \r\nIt was on that day that I learnt that in order to avoid such situations planning is the best tool. Since then I devote the first 15 minutes of my work day in organizing my day and arranging my tasks based on the priority. My supervisors always praise me for I never miss on deadlines.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What professional goals have you set for yourself this year?", "answers": ["Be honest while answering this question. The motive of the interviewer is to find out if you will be a good fit for the organization and will stay with the organization for a long time. The hiring managers are not interested in going ahead with a candidate who doesn't see himself/herself as a part of the organization in the long term or not even for a year for that matter. Thus make sure you state realistic goals which are in sync with the career defined by the company.", "\"This year I want to learn and grow as much as I can in this profession. I want to gain more and more knowledge about this profession working for a good company like yours.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What do you do when your time schedule or project plan is upset by unforeseen circumstances?", "answers": ["Assure the hiring manager that you are able to successfully cope with schedule changes and other unforeseen circumstances. How do you react and what do you do to integrate these changes in your plans?", "\"When my day unravels a bit due to unforeseen circumstances, I will take a minute to reassess my priorities. Asking for assistance where needed is also important, at times, to ensure that I am not taken off schedule too much. All in all, I handle unforeseen projects and schedule changes quite well. it's always one step at a time for me.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What initially attracted you to the insurance industry, and what keeps you here?", "answers": ["You can add a personal touch when answering this question. Be sure that your passion for your career comes through in your answer.", "\"I love working as an underwriter because I feel that by doing this job I am being valuable not only for the organization that I am working for but also for the society. I get to use my analytical skills, critical thinking and decision making everyday. The challenges that I face everyday as an underwriter and the risks that we face is an extra bonus in itself.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "When will your current project be completed, or when will be the next logical time to be able to leave on good terms with your team?", "answers": ["This question demands for an honest answer, but at the same time you also need to be aware of the company's requirements and if there is an urgent need then you need to be prepared for that as well. \r\nIf you are unable to leave your current job for certain time period, you should say so right here. You can figure out some way together to meet their requirements if needed. Similarly, if you have a project bonus that is paid out on a certain date, let the interviewer know.", "\"My current projects are all stable and green. I can transition them to another team member (or my boss) and be able to start with a two-week notice.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Give an example where you have supported a loan that did not comply with FHA loan guidelines?", "answers": ["The objective of this question is to figure out if you always go by the book or you also take your own decisions if required. This is a very tricky question as the company might be very strict about the guidelines and might not select you if you have supported some such loan even if that was a very good decision. So you may want to exercise a little bit of caution here. Make sure you do your homework about the company and its culture. \r\nIf you have worked on non-compliant loans, answer this with how in your past you worked on researching and analyzing non FHA loans. Expand on what the differences are, how you conducted your research and analysis. It is OK to present a loan that was not funded as your contribution to the decision is most important, not the result.", "\"I usually don't support loans that don't comply with FHA guidelines but there are always some exceptions to it. I have done a lot of research on non FHA loans, about the differences etc. (here you can add your findings) Sometimes it is OK to present a loan that is not funded as its our contribution to the decision is what matters the most. We can't control the results but make the best effort for doing something useful.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Give an example where you have had to challenge loan documentation based on fraud detection processes you use.", "answers": ["This question intends to find out how far does the circle of your knowledge go and whether you are able to make decisions that sometimes want you to go against the decisions of others. Provide an example including the fraud tools or methodologies that you are most familiar with. It is important to not disclose any proprietary tools or ratios that a competitor uses.", "\"I believe that this is a situation that every underwriter has to face every now and then in their career. To be honest it is our job to deliver fair and justified decisions irrespective of who are the parties involved. I can remember an incident where I was presented with a loan application and it was for some really old client of ours but there were a few discrepancies and it simply didn't pass the few methods that I use for making a decision. I decided to take a stand and got this to notice of the other team members. It eventually turned out that the application did have many discrepancies and could have put us at huge risk had it been passed. It did result in some people getting offended in the end but it was for the benefit of the company and thus my decision was appreciated at a later level.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What are your general guidelines related to applicable ratios (i.e Debt ratios, loan-to-value)", "answers": ["This question is a way to determine if you understand industry guidelines for these ratios. They should be almost second nature."]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "What is your greatest strength? How does it help you as an Underwriter?", "answers": ["What things have you repeatedly been complemented for? What are the common positive comments you receive on your performance reviews? These can be great starting points for identifying your greatest strength! Share one of these things with the interviewer stating that others have told you this is your greatest strength. Next, share how this strength will help you as an underwriter.", "\"I have been told by past managers that my greatest strength is that I am disciplined. I work hard and stay focused on the task at hand. My consistency makes me reliable and gives others confidence in me. I try to ensure that I make no errors in my work for which I check and recheck my work before submission, which has always been praised by my supervisors.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Are you efficient with your time?", "answers": ["Through this question the interviewer wants to know how good you are at managing your time and deadlines. The best way to answer this question is to start by explaining that you understand the importance of time and also the repercussions of missing deadlines for any project. \r\nYou can also add how you plan your day or week's work and how you prioritise your tasks, if you keep any reminders or use post-its etc.", "\"Yes, I am!. I understand that all underwriters have a lot of work to accomplish every day, and I must be efficient with how I use your time to achieve your goals. I spend first 15 minutes of time each day prioritizing my focus for that day to ensure that I am meeting deadlines, responding to urgent needs, and staying on track with meeting goals.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Share an experience you had in dealing with a difficult person and how you handled the situation.", "answers": ["This is quite a common question for an interviewer to ask as they want to hear if you can describe a work colleague conflict and how you handled it. They are also looking to see how you handle working with changing personalities in a team environment. Talk about how you reached your ultimate solution and any lessons you learned from that. \n\r\nDescribe the situation and how this person was difficulty. It is important to indicate the how/why they were difficult. Examples might be conflicting objectives or project goals, they had a different management or work style, etc. \n\r\nThen describe how you dealt with it. Example might be taking time to sit with this person 1:1 and walking through the project elements, how the two of you needed to work on specific areas for mutual gain. \n\r\nIf it was with a difficult colleague/boss/client, then describe how you communicated the issue(s) you were encountering, what you proposed to solve the issues, and ultimately the resolution."]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Tell me about your education. How has it prepared you for a career as a Underwriter?", "answers": ["Provide the interviewer with an overview of your highest level of completed education. If you have attended any recent training seminars or conferences that are directly applicable, feel free to talk about those too! Next, share a few highlights from your education. You might talk about your education preparing you to multi-task and manage a busy workload. You can also consider sharing that your education has provided you with a good foundation, and you understand there will still be things to learn once you are on the job. Be sure to mention that you look forward to learning all that you can!", "\"I did my bachelors in Accounting and then trained under a senior underwriter for around one year. Since then I have done XYZ certifications to update my skill set. I read a lot as I understand that having the basic knowledge only is not sufficient in any profession, but we need to constantly upgrade ourselves by trying to learn more and more. My education provided me with the base to start working as an underwriter while my constant efforts to keep learning something new helped me in staying ahead of the others in this profession.\"", "\"My degree is in Psychology, so concerning underwriting, there is no direct correlation, but my schooling, in general, provided me with a base that I believe carries over. It helped me realize that I am a better student, co-worker, employee, and better person when I'm constantly aiming to upgrade myself. As long as I stay in the mindset of learning at least one new thing a day, I can't fail.\"", "Wonderful! Although your education is not directly related, you did an excellent job in qualifying yourself."]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Do you consider yourself to have strong research skills?", "answers": ["As an underwriter it is very important to be analytical. Tell the hiring manager the ways in which you showcase your analytical skills. \n\r\nSample", "\"I am a highly research oriented individual and consider it a vital skill for being a successful internal underwriter. I would consider myself most research oriented when I am presented with a brand new case, or client. I always want to start the analysis of the loan with the correct foundation.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "If I were to speak with your social circle, what would your friends say about you?", "answers": ["Were you late or absent a lot? Did you get along well with the team? How do you handle tough situations? Refrain from making up answers that aren't true, as you're never sure if they'll make a call to your previous boss. Instead, focus on 2-3 traits of yours that have been highly complimented and tie them in to the role you're applying for.", "\"It depends on who you talk to. As far as I know I was never late for my work and always got the better of deadlines. Also, I check and double check my work before final submission  which means there is always little or no chance of an error in my work.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Successful underwriters must have good judgement and common sense. Would you consider yourself to fit in those categories?", "answers": ["The job of an underwriter is something that needs a lot of analysis and presence of mind. From this question the interviewer wants to understand if you have a good combination of analytical skills and common sense. Give an example of an incident where you used both and were able to achieve great results as well.", "\"I consider myself to have a good judgement and common sense but yes I do believe in my instincts. I make decisions based on the analysis that I conduct but there are instances where the analysis might tell you something which may not be good for the company in the longer run. At such times I do favour my instincts as well.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Do you consider yourself more analytical or a free thinker?", "answers": ["Being analytical is of course a very good thing as far as this job is concerned, but there are instances when a combination of instinct and analysis is useful. The hiring manager wants to know if you give more preference to your instincts or do you base your decisions on your analysis of the data and situations. \r\nFor answering this question you can take an example of a situation and stating which of the two you prefer but yes giving more weight to your analysis is always a good idea as this job is more focused on your analytical skills. An underwriter is not supposed to be more of a thinker.", "\"I consider myself to be more analytic as this is a major part of our job but yes I do believe in my instincts and sometimes I make decisions based on both of these as the analysis might tell you something at times which may not be good for the company in the longer run. At such times I do favour my instincts as well.\""]}, {"topic": "Underwriter", "question": "Give an example where you have had to use your negotiation skills.", "answers": ["An employee who has excellent negotiation skills and is a good communicator apart from being good at his job is a very rare combination which most of the employers are looking for. Make sure you present an example where you were able to use your negotiation skills and diplomacy to come up with a win-win situation for the company and the client as well. \r\nYou may choose to give an example from your personal life but thats not advisable as the interviewer is looking for a professional achievement which can be of value for the company in the future. Remember your purpose for being there; you are not there to present rosy or sad stories from your personal life to get some emotional reactions from the interviewer.\r\nBe able to show how you drove to consensus, got to a point where everyone was satisfied with the result.", "\"In my last job, we were once dealing with this new prospective client who was not sure whether he wanted to go for our services or not. There were a few points in our policy that he was not happy with in particular. I decided to sit with him and talk to him about the whole situation. Once I got to know what his problem was, I gave him examples of situations where those clauses could actually be beneficial for him and also for his satisfaction made a minor change to the contract. In the end we got the contract and he was happy with our services too. We were happy because we got a big client.\""]}]